<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="ugelem-1">



<title>Elements of Trusted Extensions</title>
<toc>
<itemizedlist>
<para>This chapter explains the key elements of Trusted Extensions. The chapter
discusses these topics:</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="ugelem-10">Basics of Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="ugtour-4">Files and Applications in Trusted
Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="ugelem-40">Password Security</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="ugelem-42">Front Panel Security (CDE)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="ugelem-10">
<title>Basics of Trusted Extensions</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-283">
<primary>Trusted Extensions</primary>
<secondary>basic features</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>After you have successfully completed the login process, you can work
within Trusted Extensions. Your work is subject to security restrictions. Restrictions
that are specific to Trusted Extensions include the label range of the system,
your clearance, and your choice of a single-level or multilevel session. As
the following figure illustrates, four features distinguish a system that
is configured with Trusted Extensions from a Solaris system.</para>
<figure xml:id="ugelem-fig-1">

<title>Solaris Trusted Extensions Multilevel CDE Desktop</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/workspace.basic.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Screen shows labels on windows and icons, the trusted
stripe with the trusted symbol and workspace label.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Label displays – All windows, workspaces, files, and
applications have a label. The graphical interface provides stripes and other
indicators for viewing an entity's label.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-284">
<primary>trusted stripe</primary>
<secondary>location in CDE</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-285">
<primary>trusted stripe</primary>
<secondary>location in Java DS</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-286">
<primary>visibility</primary>
<secondary>trusted stripe</secondary>
</indexterm>Trusted stripe – Is a special graphical security mechanism.
In CDE, the <emphasis>trusted stripe</emphasis> is always displayed at the
bottom of the screen. In Java DS, the stripe can be at the top of the screen.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Limited access to applications from the workspace –
The workspace provides access only to those applications permitted in your
user account.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-287">
<primary>Trusted Path menu</primary>
<secondary>location</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-288">
<primary>finding</primary>
<secondary>Trusted Path menu</secondary>
</indexterm>Trusted Path menu – In CDE, the switch area in the Front
Panel provides access to the Trusted Path pop-up menu for performing security-related
tasks.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-26">
<title>Labels on Trusted Extensions Desktops</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-289">
<primary>labels</primary>
<secondary>displayed in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<itemizedlist>
<para>As discussed in <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ugintro-32">Mandatory Access Control</olink>,
all applications and files in Trusted Extensions have labels. Trusted Extensions displays
labels in several places:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Window label stripes above the window title bar</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Window icon label stripes under the minimized window</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Window Label indicator in the trusted stripe</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Query window label indicator – Trusted Path menu item
that displays the label of the window or icon specified by the pointer location</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="ugelem-fig-1">Figure 4–1</olink> shows how labels
display on a system that configured to display labels. The system is using
CDE as its desktop. A site can also be configured to hide labels. Even if
your administrator has configured the system to hide labels, labeling is still
in effect. The Query Window Label menu item can be used to display the label
of a window. For an illustration, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="ugelem-fig-7">Figure
3–5</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-20">
<title>Trusted Stripe</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-290">
<primary>trusted stripe</primary>
<secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm>In CDE, the <emphasis>trusted stripe</emphasis> appears in a reserved
area at the bottom of the screen in all Trusted Extensions sessions. In Java DS,
the trusted stripe can appear at the top of the screen.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>The purpose of the trusted stripe is to give you a visual confirmation
that you are in a legitimate Trusted Extensions session. The stripe indicates
when you are interacting with the trusted computing base. The stripe also
displays the labels of your current workspace and current window. The trusted
stripe cannot be moved or be obscured by other windows or dialog boxes. The
trusted stripe has two elements:</para>
<listitem>
<para>The trusted symbol – Displays when screen focus is security-related</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The window label – Optional. Displays label of active
window</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<figure xml:id="ugtour-35">

<title>
<literal>PUBLIC</literal> Window Label in the
Trusted Stripe</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/win.label.public.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Screen shows the trusted stripe without the trusted symbol
and with a workspace label of PUBLIC.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<sect3 xml:id="ugelem-8">
<title>Trusted Symbol</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-291">
<primary>trusted symbol</primary>
<secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-292">
<primary>trusted computing base (TCB)</primary>
<secondary>symbol of interacting with</secondary>
</indexterm>Whenever you access any portion of the trusted computing base,
the <emphasis>trusted symbol</emphasis> appears at the left of the trusted
stripe area. If your configuration suppresses labels, then the trusted  symbol
appears with the trusted stripe. In CDE, the symbol appears to the left of
the Front Panel.</para>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/shield.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Illustration shows the trusted symbol.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The trusted symbol is not displayed when the pointer is focused in a
window or area of the screen that does not affect security. The trusted symbol
cannot be forged. If you see the symbol, you can be sure that you are safely
interacting with the trusted computing base.</para>
<caution>

<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-293">
<primary>no trusted symbol</primary>
<secondary>troubleshooting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-294">
<primary>trusted symbol</primary>
<secondary>missing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-295">
<primary>Security Administrator role</primary>
<secondary>contacting for missing trusted symbol</secondary>
</indexterm>If the trusted stripe is missing from your workspace, or if the
trusted symbol is missing when you are attempting a security-related action,
notify your Trusted Extensions administrator at once. The problem on your system
could be serious. If the trusted stripe is visible when the screen is locked, notify
your Trusted Extensions administrator at once.</para>
</caution>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="ugelem-9">
<title>Window Label Indicator</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-296">
<primary>Window Label indicator</primary>
</indexterm>The <emphasis>Window Label</emphasis> indicator displays the label
of the active window. In a multilevel session, the indicator can help identify
windows with different labels in the same workspace. The indicator can also
show that you are interacting with the trusted computing base. For example,
when you change your password, the Trusted Path indicator displays in the
trusted stripe.</para>
<figure xml:id="ugtour-fig-9">

<title>
<literal>Trusted Path</literal> Indicator
in the Trusted Stripe</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/win.trusted.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Screen shows the trusted stripe without the trusted symbol
and with a label of Trusted Path.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="ugtour-4">
<title>Files and Applications in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>All applications in Trusted Extensions have sensitivity. Applications are <emphasis>subjects</emphasis> in any data transactions. Subjects must dominate the <emphasis>objects</emphasis> that the subjects try to access. Objects can be files,
and sometimes can be other processes. The label information for an application
is displayed in the window label stripe. The label is visible when a window
is open and when the window is minimized. An application's label also appears
in the trusted stripe when the pointer is in the application's window.</para>
<para>Files are objects in data transactions in Trusted Extensions. Files can
only be accessed by applications whose labels dominate the files' labels.
A file can be viewed from windows that have the same label as the file.</para>
<para>Some applications use initialization files to configure the environment
for the user. Two special files in your home directory help you access initialization
files at every label. These files enable an application at one label to use
an initialization file that originates in a directory at a different label.
The two special files are <filename>.copy_files</filename> and <filename>.link_files</filename>.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="ugfile-2">
<title>
<filename>.copy_files</filename> File</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-297">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>
<filename>$HOME/.copy_files</filename>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-298">
<primary>
<filename>.copy_files</filename> file</primary>
<secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<filename>.copy_files</filename> stores file names to be copied when
you first change to a workspace with a higher label. <filename>.copy_files</filename> is
stored in your home directory at your minimum label. This file is useful when
you have an application that always writes to a file in your home directory
with a specific name. <filename>.copy_files</filename> enables you to enable
the application to update the file at every label.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugfile-5">
<title>
<filename>.link_files</filename> File</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-299">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>
<filename>$HOME/.link_files</filename>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-300">
<primary>
<filename>.link_files</filename> file</primary>
<secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<filename>.link_files</filename> stores file names to be linked when
you first change to a workspace with a higher label. <filename>.link_files</filename> is
stored in your home directory at your minimum label. This file is  useful
when a specific file needs to be available at multiple labels, but the content
should be identical at every label.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="ugelem-40">
<title>Password Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-301">
<primary>passwords</primary>
<secondary>user responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-302">
<primary>user responsibilities</primary>
<secondary>password security</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-303">
<primary>responsibilities</primary>
<secondary>users for password security</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-304">
<primary>users</primary>
<secondary>responsibilities</secondary>
<tertiary>password security</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<itemizedlist>
<para>Users who change passwords on a frequent basis shorten the window of
opportunity for intruders to use illegally obtained passwords. Therefore,
your site's policy can require you to change your password regularly. The Solaris OS can
set content requirements for passwords, and can enforce resetting requirements.
 The following are possible resetting requirements:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Minimum number of days between changes – Prevents you
or anyone else from changing your password for a set number of days.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Maximum number of days between changes – Requires you
to change your password after a set number of days.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Maximum number of inactive days – Locks your account
after the set number of days of inactivity if the password has not been changed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Expiration date – Requires you to change your password
by a specific date.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>If your administrator has implemented one of the preceding options,
you should receive a message that warns you to change your password prior
to the cutoff date.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>Passwords can have content criteria. At minimum, passwords in the Solaris OS must
meet the following standards:</para>
<listitem>
<para>The password must be at least eight characters long.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The password must contain at least two alphabetic characters
and at least one numeric character or one special character.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The new password must differ from your previous password.
You cannot use a reverse or circular shift of the previous password. For this
comparison, uppercase letters and lowercase letters are considered to be equal.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The new password must have at least three characters that
are different from the old password. For this comparison, uppercase letters
and lowercase letters are considered to be equal.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The password should be difficult to guess. Do not use a common
word or a proper name. Programs and individuals who try to break into an account
can use lists to try to guess users' passwords.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>You can change your password from the Change Password menu item. For
the steps, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="ugelem-16">Performing Trusted Actions (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="ugelem-42">
<title>Front Panel Security (CDE)</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-305">
<primary>Front Panel</primary>
<secondary>description of trusted applications on</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-306">
<primary>CDE</primary>
<secondary>trusted applications on Front Panel</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-307">
<primary>trusted applications</primary>
<secondary>on Front Panel</secondary>
</indexterm>The Front Panel in Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) is very similar to the Front Panel
that is used in standard CDE. The Trusted Extensions Front Panel restricts access
to only those applications, files, and utilities that you are allowed to use.
By clicking mouse button 3 anywhere in the workspace switch area, the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="glossary-1.xml" targetptr="uggloss-61">Trusted Path menu</olink> is displayed.</para>
<para>Before you can access a device through the Removable Media Manager,
that device must be allocated using the Device Allocation Manager. The Device
Allocation Manager is accessed from the Tools subpanel, which is above the
Style Manager icon in the Front Panel.</para>
<tip>

<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-308">
<primary>troubleshooting</primary>
<secondary>minimized Front Panel</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-309">
<primary>Front Panel</primary>
<secondary>restoring when minimized</secondary>
</indexterm>If you minimize the Front Panel, you can restore the panel by
clicking anywhere in the Trusted Stripe.</para>
</tip>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, Install Icon dropsites are limited to the applications
and files that you are permitted to use at the label of the current workspace.</para>
<para>For more information on standard CDE, see the <citetitle>Common Desktop
Environment User's Guide</citetitle>.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-12">
<title>Workspace Switch Area</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-310">
<primary>workspace switch area</primary>
<secondary>in Trusted Extensions CDE</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, the workspace buttons not only define separate workspaces,
but also require you work at particular labels. When you begin a multilevel
session, each workspace is set to the lowest label that you can use. If your
administrator has color-coded the labels at your site, the workspace buttons
display the color of the label. The Trusted Path menu is available from the
workspace switch area.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-32">
<title>Trusted Path Menu</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-311">
<primary>Trusted Path menu</primary>
<secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The Trusted Path menu contains menu items that affect security.</para>
<figure xml:id="ugelem-fig-3">

<title>Trusted Path Menu – Basic</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/tpmenu.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Screen shows the basic Trusted Path menu.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>For example, you change your password with this menu. You can allocate
devices with this menu. For details, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="ugelem-16">Performing
Trusted Actions (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
<para>The Trusted Path menu has two versions. The Workspace <replaceable>Name</replaceable> version
includes workspace options. The selections that appear in your menu depend
on how the administrator configured your account.</para>
<figure xml:id="ugtour-fig-20">

<title>Trusted Path Menu - Workspace <replaceable>Name</replaceable> Version</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/wsmenu.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Screen shows the Trusted Path menu that is accessed from
a workspace switch.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-13">
<title>Clock Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-312">
<primary>clock security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, only an administrator can change the date and time
for your workstation.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-14">
<title>Calendar Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-313">
<primary>calendar security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The calendar shows the appointments for you at the label of your current
workspace only. To view appointments at a different label, you need to open
the calendar at that label.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-15">
<title>File Manager Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-314">
<primary>File Manager</primary>
<secondary>security in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, the File Manager displays files at the label of the
current workspace. To view files at more than one label at a time, you run
File Manager from workspaces at different labels. You then use the Occupy
Workspace command to display the different File Managers in the same workspace.</para>
<para>The File Manager enables you to change a file or folder's basic permissions
and access control list (ACL). If you are authorized, you can also move or
link files between File Managers at different labels. For details on File
Manager use, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="txwork-4">How to View Your Files in a Workspace</olink> and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="ugelem-16">Performing Trusted Actions (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-17">
<title>Text Editor Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-315">
<primary>Text Editor security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The Text Editor can edit files at the label of the current workspace
only. If you are authorized, you can copy information between text editors
at different labels.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-18">
<title>Personal Applications Subpanel</title>
<para>The default applications in the personal applications operate basically
the same as in the standard CDE environment. The Terminal icon launches the
default shell assigned to you by your administrator. To access a web server,
the label of your browser must be the same as the label of the web server.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-19">
<title>Mailer Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-316">
<primary>mail security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, all mail messages are labeled.   When you send a
message, the message goes out at the label of your mail tool. Only hosts and
users that are cleared for that label receive the message. Only users who
are working at that label can see the message.</para>
<para>If you need to use the vacation message option in your mail application,
you must explicitly enable vacation message replies for each label at which
you typically receive mail. Check with your security administrator for your
site's security policy on vacation messages.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-21">
<title>Printer Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-317">
<primary>Printer tool security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The Print Manager in the Personal Printers subpanel displays icons for
all printers that are accredited up to your clearance. However, you can use
only those printers that are accredited to print documents at the label of
the current workspace.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>A typical print job in Trusted Extensions includes labels and extra pages:</para>
<listitem>
<para>A banner page at the beginning of the print job identifies
the print job, handling instructions and labels that are appropriate to the
site</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Body pages are labeled at the header and the footer</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A trailer page at the end of the print job signals the end
of the job</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-318">
<primary>printing</primary>
<secondary>typical labeled banner page</secondary>
</indexterm>A typical banner page appears in the following figure. The words <literal>JOB START</literal> indicate the banner page.</para>
<figure xml:id="ugelem-fig-9">

<title>Typical Print Banner Page</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/TypicalPrintBanr.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Illustration shows job number and handling instructions
on a typical print banner page.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>For the exact security information regarding printing at your site,
see your administrator.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-23">
<title>Style Manager Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-319">
<primary>Style Manager</primary>
<secondary>limitations in Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>With three exceptions, the Style Manager operates in the same manner
as it operates on a Solaris system.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The Style Manager cannot be run from the Application Manager
when Trusted Extensions is configured, because the Style Manager requires the
 trusted path. Run the Style Manager from the Front Panel and the Workspace
menu, where the Style Manager has the trusted path.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The Screen Blanker and Screen Lock options are limited. Your
administrator specifies the maximum amount of time that your system can be
idle prior to being secured. You can reduce the idle time. You cannot increase
the idle time above the maximum. You can still choose a pattern for when the
screen is locked. See your administrator if you are not familiar with the
policy at your site.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The Startup control sets your startup session settings according
to the label or clearance that you specify at login. Thus, you can save a
different workspace configuration for each label in your account label range.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-24">
<title>Application Manager Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-320">
<primary>Application Manager security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The Application Manager provides access to only those applications and
utilities that your administrator has assigned to you. In a role, you have
access to a different set of applications and capabilities. Remember that
the ability of a function to operate on a file depends on the label of the
current workspace.</para>
<para>Similarly, although you can add applications to the Personal Application
submenu by dropping icons onto the Install Icon dropsite, you can only run
an application if your administrator has assigned the application to you.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ugelem-25">
<title>Trash Can Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-321">
<primary>Trash Can security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, the trash can stores files to be deleted by label.
Although you can drop files at any label in the trash can, the trash can displays
files at the current label only. You should delete sensitive information as
soon as the information is in the trash can.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
