<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="managezones-1">



<title>Managing Zones
in Trusted Extensions</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-511">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>managing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-512">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<toc>
<para>This chapter describes how non-global zones work on a system that is
configured with Trusted Extensions.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-16">Zones in Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-4">Zone Administration Utilities
in Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-6">Managing Zones (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="managezones-16">
<title>Zones in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-513">
<primary>global zone</primary>
<secondary>difference from labeled zones</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-514">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>global</secondary>
</indexterm>A properly configured Trusted Extensions host consists of a global
zone, which is the operating system instance, and one or more labeled non-global
zones. During configuration, Trusted Extensions attaches a unique label, which
creates a labeled zone. The labels come from the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file.
The installers can create a zone for each label, but are not required to.
It is possible to have more labels than labeled zones on a system. It is not
possible to have more labeled zones than labels.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-515">
<primary>directories</primary>
<secondary>accessing lower-level</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-516">
<primary>accessing</primary>
<secondary>home directories</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-517">
<primary>home directories</primary>
<secondary>accessing</secondary>
</indexterm>On a Trusted Extensions system, the file systems of a zone are usually
mounted as a loopback file system (<literal>lofs</literal>). All writable
files and directories in a labeled zone are at the label of the zone. By default,
a user can view files that are in a zone at a lower level than the user's
current level. This configuration enables users to view their home directories
at lower labels than the label of the current workspace. Although users can
view files, they cannot modify those files. Users can only modify files from
a process that is the same label as the file.</para>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, the global zone is an administrative zone. The labeled
zones are for ordinary users. Users can work in a zone whose label is within
the user's accreditation range.</para>
<para>Every zone has an associated IP address and security attributes. A zone
can be configured with multilevel ports (MLPs). Also, a zone can set a policy
for Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP) broadcasts, such as <command>ping</command>.</para>
<para>Zones in Trusted Extensions are built on the Solaris zones product.
For details, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="zone">Part II, <citetitle remap="chapter">Zones,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.
In particular, patching and package installation issues affect Trusted Extensions.
For details, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="z.pkginst.ov-1">Chapter 24, <citetitle remap="chapter">About Packages and Patches on a Solaris System With Zones Installed (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink> and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="gclkx">Chapter 28, <citetitle remap="chapter">Troubleshooting Miscellaneous Solaris Zones Problems,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="managezones-2">
<title>Zones and IP Addresses in Trusted Extensions</title>
<itemizedlist>
<para>Your installation assigned IP addresses to the global zone and the labeled
zones. There are three possible configurations.</para>
<listitem>
<para>The machine has one IP address for the global zone and all
labeled zones.</para>
<para>This configuration is useful on a machine that
uses DHCP software to get its IP address. All the labeled zones can share
one address with the global zone. If no users are expected to log in, an LDAP
server might have this configuration.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The machine has one IP address for the global zone, and one
address that is shared by all zones, including the global zone. Any zone can
have a combination of a unique address and a shared address.</para>
<para>This
configuration is useful on a machine that ordinary users are going to log
in to. This configuration saves IP addresses. It can also be used for a printer
or an NFS server.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The machine has one IP address for the global zone, and each
labeled zone has a unique IP address.</para>
<para>This configuration is useful
for providing access to separate physical networks of single-level systems.
Each zone would typically have a different physical network as well as a unique
IP address.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="managezones-31">
<title>Zones and Multilevel Ports</title>
<para>By default, a zone cannot send packets to and receive packets from any
other zone. Multilevel ports (MLPs) enable particular services on a port to
accept requests within a range of labels or from a set of labels. These privileged
services can reply at the label of the request. For example, you might want
to create a privileged web browser port, that can listen at all labels, but
whose replies are restricted by label. By default, labeled zones have no MLPs.</para>
<para>The range of labels or set of labels that constrains the packets that
the MLP can accept is configured by the zone's IP address. The IP address
is assigned a remote host template in the <filename>tnrhdb</filename> database.
The label range or set of labels in the remote host template constrains the
packets that the MLP can accept.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>On a system where the global zone has an IP address, and each
labeled zone has a unique IP address an MLP for a particular service can be
added to every zone. For example, the system could be configured so that the <command>ssh</command> service, over TCP port <literal>22</literal>, is an MLP in the
global zone, and in every labeled zone.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In a typical configuration, the global zone is assigned one
IP address, and labeled zones share a second IP address. When an MLP is added
to a shared interface, the service packet is routed to the labeled zone where
the MLP is defined. The packet is accepted only if the remote host template
for the labeled zone includes the label of the packet. If the range is <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> to <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>, then all packets
are accepted. A narrower range would discard packets that are not within the
range.</para>
<para>At most, one zone can define a particular port to be an
MLP on a shared interface. In the preceding scenario, where the <command>ssh</command> port
is configured as a shared MLP in a non-global zone, no other zone can receive <command>ssh</command> connections on the shared address. However, the global zone
could define the <command>ssh</command> port as a private MLP for receipt
of connections on its zone-specific address. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>On a system where the global zone and the labeled zones share
an IP address, an MLP for the <command>ssh</command> service could be added
to one zone. If the MLP for <command>ssh</command> is added to the global
zone, then no labeled zone can add an MLP for the <command>ssh</command> service.
Similarly, if the MLP for the <command>ssh</command> service is added to a
labeled zone, then the global zone cannot be configured with an <command>ssh</command> MLP.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For an example of adding MLPs to labeled zones, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-13.xml" targetptr="managetnet-33">Example 13–14</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="managezones-26">
<title>Zones and ICMP in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>Networks transmit broadcast messages and send ICMP packets to machines
on the network. On a multilevel system, these transmissions could flood the
system at every label. The network policy for labeled zones, by default, requires
that ICMP packets be received only at the matching label.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managezones-4">
<title>Zone Administration Utilities in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>Some zone administration can be done from the command line. However,
the simplest way to administer zones is to use the GUIs that Trusted Extensions provides.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Configuring the security attributes of zones is done by using
the Trusted Network Zones tool in the Solaris Management Console. For a description of the tool,
see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="txtool-14">Trusted Network Zones Tool</olink>. For examples
of zone configuration and creation, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7314" targetptr="txconf-1">Chapter 4, <citetitle remap="chapter">Configuring Trusted Extensions,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle>
</olink>, and <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-5">How to Create a Multilevel Port for a Zone</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-518">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>zones from Java DS</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-519">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>administering from Java DS</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-520">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>
<command>/usr/sbin/txzonemgr</command>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-521">
<primary>scripts</primary>
<secondary>
<command>/usr/sbin/txzonemgr</command>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-522">
<primary>
<command>/usr/sbin/txzonemgr</command> script</primary>
</indexterm>The shell script, <command>/usr/sbin/txzonemgr</command>, provides
a menu-based wizard for creating, installing, initializing, and booting zones.
If you are administering zones from Java DS, use <command>txzonemgr</command> rather
than CDE actions. <command>txzonemgr</command> uses the <command>zenity</command> command.
For details, see the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>zenity</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> man page.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Configuring and creating zones can be done from desktop utilities.
In CDE, actions in the Trusted_Extensions folder are used. In Java DS, applets
can be used. For a description of the actions, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="txtool-3">Trusted
CDE Actions</olink>. For procedures that use the actions, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="commontasks-42">How to Launch CDE Administrative Actions in Trusted
Extensions</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managezones-6">
<title>Managing Zones (Tasks)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-523">
<primary>Managing Zones (Tasks)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-524">
<primary>tasks and task maps</primary>
<secondary>Managing Zones (Tasks)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-525">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>administering</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-526">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>zones</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The following table describes zone management that is specific to Trusted Extensions.</para>
<informaltable frame="all" pgwide="1">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>View all zones</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>At any label, see the zones that are dominated by the current zone.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managetnet-12">How to Display Ready or Running Zones</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>View mounted directories</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>At any label, see the directories that are dominated by the current
label.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managetnet-11">How to Display the Labels of Mounted
Files</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Enable ordinary users to view an <filename>/etc</filename> file</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Loopback mount a directory or file from the global zone that is not
visible by default in a labeled zone.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-10">How to Mount a File That is Usually
Not Visible From a Labeled Zone</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Prevent ordinary users from viewing a lower-level home directory from
a higher label.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>By default, lower-level directories are visible from higher-level zones.
When you disable the mounting of one lower-level zone, you disable all mounts
of lower-level zones.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-3">How to Disable the Mounting of Lower-Level
Files</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Configure a zone to enable changing the labels on files.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Labeled zones have limited privileges. By default, labeled zones do
not have the privilege that enables an authorized user to relabel a file.
You modify the zone configuration to add the privilege.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-8">How to Enable Files to be Relabeled
From a Labeled Zone</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Move a file or directory into or out of a labeled zone</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Change a file or directory's level of security by changing its label.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-30">How to Use Two File Managers to Relabel
a File</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Configure a new zone</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Create a zone at a label that is not currently being used to label a
zone on this system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7314" targetptr="txconf-11">
<citetitle remap="section">Specify Zone Names and Zone Labels</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle>
</olink>
</para>
<para>Then, follow the procedure that the install team used to create the
other zones. For the steps, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7314" targetptr="txconf-20">
<citetitle remap="section">Creating the Labeled Zones (Tasks)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create a multilevel port for an application.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Multilevel ports are useful for programs that require a multilevel feed
into a labeled zone.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-5">How to Create a Multilevel Port for
a Zone</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Troubleshoot NFS mount and access problems</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Debug general access issues for mounts, and possibly for zones.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-20">How to Troubleshoot Mount Failures</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Remove a labeled
zone</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Completely remove
a labeled zone from the system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="z.inst.task-44">
<citetitle remap="section">How to Remove a Non-Global Zone</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managetnet-12">

<title>How to Display Ready or Running
Zones</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-527">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>displaying status</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-528">
<primary>displaying</primary>
<secondary>status of every zone</secondary>
</indexterm>This procedure creates a shell script that displays the labels
of the current zone and of all zones that the current zone dominates.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the System Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Use the Admin Editor action to create the <filename>getzonelabels</filename> script.</para>
<para>Supply the pathname to the script, such as <filename>/usr/local/scripts/getzonelabels</filename>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-529">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>
<filename>getzonelabels</filename>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-530">
<primary>scripts</primary>
<secondary>
<filename>getzonelabels</filename>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-531">
<primary>
<filename>getzonelabels</filename> script</primary>
</indexterm>Supply the following content and save the file.</para>
<screen>#!/bin/sh
#
echo "NAME\t\tSTATUS\t\tLABEL"
echo "====\t\t======\t\t====="
myzone=`zonename`
for i in `/usr/sbin/zoneadm list -p` ; do
        zone=`echo $i | cut -d ":" -f2`
        status=`echo $i | cut -d ":" -f3`
        path=`echo $i | cut -d ":" -f4`
        if [ $zone != global ]; then
                if [ $myzone = global ]; then
                        path=$path/root/tmp
                else
                        path=$path/export/home
                fi
        fi
        label=`/usr/bin/getlabel -s $path |cut -d ":" -f2-9`
        if [ `echo $zone|wc -m` -lt 8 ]; then
                echo "$zone\t\t$status\t$label"
        else
                echo "$zone\t$status\t$label"
        fi
done</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Test the script in the global zone.</para>
<para>When run from
the global zone, the script displays the labels of all ready or running zones.
Here is the global zone output for the zones that were created from the default <filename>label_encodings</filename> file:</para>
<screen># getzonelabels
NAME            STATUS          LABEL
====            ======          =====
global          running         ADMIN_HIGH
needtoknow      running         CONFIDENTIAL : NEED TO KNOW
restricted      running         CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
internal        running         CONFIDENTIAL : INTERNAL
public          running         PUBLIC</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="managetnet-21">

<title>Displaying the Labels of All Ready or Running Zones</title>
<para>In the following example, a user runs the <filename>getzonelabels</filename> script
in the <literal>internal</literal> zone.</para>
<screen># getzonelabels
NAME            STATUS          LABEL
====            ======          =====
internal        running         CONFIDENTIAL : INTERNAL
public          running         PUBLIC</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managetnet-11">

<title>How to Display the Labels of Mounted Files</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-532">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>accessing from dominating labels</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>This procedure creates a shell script that displays the mounted file
systems of the current zone. When run from the global zone, the script displays
the labels of all mounted file systems in every zone.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the System Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Use the Admin Editor action to create the <filename>getmounts</filename> script.</para>
<para>Supply the pathname to the script, such as <filename>/usr/local/scripts/getmounts</filename>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-533">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>
<filename>getmounts</filename>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-534">
<primary>scripts</primary>
<secondary>
<filename>getmounts</filename>
</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-535">
<primary>
<filename>getmounts</filename> script</primary>
</indexterm>Supply the following content and save the file.</para>
<screen>#!/bin/sh
#
for i in `/usr/sbin/mount -p | cut -d " " -f3` ; do
        /usr/bin/getlabel $i
done</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Test the script in the global zone.</para>
<screen>% /usr/local/scripts/getmounts
/:      ADMIN_LOW
/dev:   ADMIN_LOW
/kernel:        ADMIN_LOW
/lib:   ADMIN_LOW
/opt:   ADMIN_LOW
/platform:      ADMIN_LOW
/sbin:  ADMIN_LOW
/usr:   ADMIN_LOW
/var/tsol/doors:        ADMIN_LOW
/zone/needtoknow/export/home:   CONFIDENTIAL : NEED TO KNOW
/zone/internal/export/home:     CONFIDENTIAL : INTERNAL USE ONLY
/zone/restricted/export/home:   CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/proc:  ADMIN_LOW
/system/contract:       ADMIN_LOW
/etc/svc/volatile:      ADMIN_LOW
/etc/mnttab:    ADMIN_LOW
/dev/fd:        ADMIN_LOW
/tmp:           ADMIN_LOW
/var/run:       ADMIN_LOW
/zone/public/export/home:  PUBLIC
/root:          ADMIN_LOW</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="managezones-19">

<title>Displaying the Labels of File Systems in a <literal>restricted</literal> Zone</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-536">
<primary>displaying</primary>
<secondary>labels of file systems in labeled zone</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-537">
<primary>labels</primary>
<secondary>displaying labels of file systems in labeled zone</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-538">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>displaying labels of file systems</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>When run from a labeled zone by an ordinary user, the <filename>getmounts</filename> script
displays the labels of all the mounted file systems in that zone. On a system
that created zones for every label in the default <filename>label_encodings</filename> file,
the following is the output from the <literal>restricted</literal> zone:</para>
<screen>% /usr/local/scripts/getmounts
/:      CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/dev:   CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/kernel:        ADMIN_LOW
/lib:   ADMIN_LOW
/opt:   ADMIN_LOW
/platform:      ADMIN_LOW
/sbin:  ADMIN_LOW
/usr:   ADMIN_LOW
/var/tsol/doors:        ADMIN_LOW
/zone/needtoknow/export/home:   CONFIDENTIAL : NEED TO KNOW
/zone/internal/export/home:     CONFIDENTIAL : INTERNAL USE ONLY
/proc:  CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/system/contract:       CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/etc/svc/volatile:      CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/etc/mnttab:    CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/dev/fd:        CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/tmp:   CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/var/run:       CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED
/zone/public/export/home:       PUBLIC
/home/gfaden:   CONFIDENTIAL : RESTRICTED</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managezones-10">

<title>How to Mount a File That is Usually
Not Visible From a Labeled Zone</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-539">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>loopback mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-540">
<primary>mounting</primary>
<secondary>files by loopback mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>This procedure enables a user in a specified labeled zone to see
files that are not exported from the global zone by default.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the System Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Halt the zone whose configuration you want to change.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> halt</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Loopback mount a file or directory.</para>
<para>For example, enable
ordinary users to view a file in the <filename class="directory">/etc</filename> directory.</para>
<screen># zonecfg -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>
 add filesystem
 set special=/etc/<replaceable>filename</replaceable>
 set directory=/etc/<replaceable>filename</replaceable>
 set type=lofs
 end
 exit</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>3. Start the zone.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> boot</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="managezones-14">

<title>Loopback Mounting the <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> file</title>
<para>In this example, the security administrator wants to enable testers
and programmers to check that their local passwords are set. The <literal>sandbox</literal> zone is first halted, then it is configured to loopback mount the <filename>passwd</filename> file, then the zone is restarted.</para>
<screen># <userinput>zoneadm -z sandbox halt</userinput>
# <userinput>zonecfg -z sandbox
 add filesystem
    set special=/etc/passwd
    set directory=/etc/passwd
    set type=lofs
    end
 exit</userinput>
# <userinput>zoneadm -z sandbox boot</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managezones-3">

<title>How to Disable the Mounting of Lower-Level
Files</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-541">
<primary>restricting</primary>
<secondary>access to lower-level files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-542">
<primary>restricting</primary>
<secondary>mounts of lower-level files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-543">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>preventing access from dominating labels</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-544">
<primary>protecting</primary>
<secondary>files at lower labels from being accessed</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-545">
<primary>
<constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege</primary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>By default, users can view lower-level files. Use this procedure to
prevent the viewing of all lower-level files from a particular zone.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the System Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Halt the zone whose configuration you want to change.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> halt</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Configure the zone to prevent viewing.</para>
<para>Remove the <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege from the zone.</para>
<screen># zonecfg -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>
 set limitpriv=default,!net_mac_aware
 exit</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>3. Start the zone.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> boot</screen>
<para>For a description of the <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege,
see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2252" targetptr="privileges-5">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>privileges</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
5
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="managezones-11">

<title>Preventing Users From Viewing Lower-Level Files</title>
<para>In this example, the security administrator wants to prevent users on
this machine from being confused. Therefore, users can only see files at the
label at which the users are working. So, the security administrator prevents
the viewing of all lower-level files. On this system, users cannot see publicly
available files unless they are working at the <literal>PUBLIC</literal> label.</para>
<screen># <userinput>zoneadm -z restricted halt</userinput>
# <userinput>zonecfg -z restricted
 set limitpriv=default,!net_mac_aware
 exit</userinput>
# <userinput>zoneadm -z restricted boot</userinput>
</screen>
<screen># <userinput>zoneadm -z needtoknow halt</userinput>
# <userinput>zonecfg -z needtoknow
 set limitpriv=default,!net_mac_aware
 exit</userinput>
# <userinput>zoneadm -z needtoknow boot</userinput>
</screen>
<screen># <userinput>zoneadm -z internal halt</userinput>
# <userinput>zonecfg -z internal
 set limitpriv=default,!net_mac_aware
 exit</userinput>
# <userinput>zoneadm -z internal boot</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Because <literal>PUBLIC</literal> is the lowest label, the security
administrator does not run the commands for the <literal>PUBLIC</literal> zone.</para>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managezones-8">

<title>How to Enable Files to be Relabeled From a
Labeled Zone</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-546">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>relabeling privileges</secondary>
</indexterm>This procedure is a prerequisite for a user to be able to relabel
files.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the Security Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Halt the zone whose configuration you want to change.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> halt</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Configure the zone to allow relabeling.</para>
<para>Add the appropriate
privileges to the zone. The windows privileges enable users to use drag and
drop, and cut and paste.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To enable downgrades, add the <constant>file_downgrade_sl</constant> privilege
to the zone.</para>
<screen># zonecfg -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>
 set limitpriv=default,win_dac_read,win_mac_read,win_dac_write,
 win_mac_write,win_selection,file_downgrade_sl
 exit</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>To enable upgrades, add the <constant>sys_trans_label</constant> and <constant>file_upgrade_sl</constant> privileges to the zone.</para>
<screen># zonecfg -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>
 set limitpriv=default,win_dac_read,win_mac_read,win_dac_write,
 win_mac_write,win_selection,sys_trans_label,file_upgrade_sl
 exit</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>To enable both upgrades and downgrades, add the both privileges
to the zone.</para>
<screen># zonecfg -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>
 set limitpriv=default,win_dac_read,win_mac_read,win_dac_write,
 win_mac_write,win_selection,sys_trans_label,file_downgrade_sl,
 file_upgrade_sl
 exit</screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step>
<para>3. Start the zone.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> boot</screen>
<para>For the user and process requirements, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7307" targetptr="setflabel-3tsol">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>setflabel</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
3TSOL
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="managezones-7">

<title>Enabling Upgrades From the <literal>internal</literal> Zone</title>
<para>In this example, the security administrator wants to enable authorized
users on this machine to upgrade files. When you upgrade information, you
protect the information at a higher level of security. In the global zone,
you use the following zone administration commands.</para>
<screen># <userinput>zoneadm -z internal halt</userinput>
# <userinput>zonecfg -z internal
 set limitpriv=default,sys_trans_label,file_upgrade_sl
 exit</userinput>
# <userinput>zoneadm -z internal boot</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Authorized users can now upgrade <constant>internal</constant> information
to <constant>restricted</constant> from this zone.</para>
</example>
<example xml:id="managezones-9">

<title>Enabling Downgrades From the <literal>restricted</literal> Zone</title>
<para>In this example, the security administrator wants to enable authorized
users on this machine to downgrade files. Because the administrator does not
add windows privileges to the zone, authorized users cannot use the File Manger
to relabel files. They can use the <command>setlabel</command> command.</para>
<para>When you downgrade information, you allow users at a lower level of
security to access the files. In the global zone, you use the following zone
administration commands.</para>
<screen># <userinput>zoneadm -z restricted halt</userinput>
# <userinput>zonecfg -z restricted
 set limitpriv=default,file_downgrade_sl
 exit</userinput>
# <userinput>zoneadm -z restricted boot</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Authorized users can now downgrade <constant>restricted</constant> information
to <constant>internal</constant> or <constant>public</constant> from this
zone by using the <command>setlabel</command> command.</para>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managezones-30">

<title>How to Use Two File Managers to Relabel a
File</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-547">
<primary>labels</primary>
<secondary>changing on files and directories</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-548">
<primary>directories</primary>
<secondary>changing labels</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-549">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>procedure for changing labels</secondary>
</indexterm>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>The zone of the source file must be configured with the appropriate
privileges. For details, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-8">How to Enable
Files to be Relabeled From a Labeled Zone</olink>.</para>
<para>You must be authorized to downgrade or upgrade labels. For the required
authorizations, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="commontasks-7">Rules When Changing the
Level of Security for Data</olink>. To assign a required authorization, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="manageusers-40">How to Create a Convenient Authorizations Rights
Profile</olink>.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>In CDE, open File Managers in workspaces at two different labels.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Move the target File Manager to the workspace of the source file.</para>
<para>Place the windows side by side.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the source File Manager, navigate to the directory of the file
that is to be moved.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the target File Manager, navigate to the directory where you
plan to place the file.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Drag the file with the mouse from the source File Manager to the
target File Manager.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Read the information in the Selection Confirmer.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If the information is correct, click OK.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Otherwise, cancel the operation.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managezones-5">

<title>How to Create a Multilevel Port for a Zone</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-550">
<primary>Trusted Network Zones tool</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-551">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>creating MLP</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-552">
<primary>multilevel ports (MLPs)</primary>
<secondary>example of web proxy MLP</secondary>
</indexterm>This procedure is part of a larger project. You create a Multilevel
Port (MLP) in a labeled zone to enable a particular port to communicate with
the zone for a specific reason. In this procedure, a web proxy communicates
with the zone. The Solaris Management Console is used to add the MLP.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the Security Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Launch the Solaris Management Console.</para>
<para>For details, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="roles-15">How to Launch the Solaris Management Console</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Choose the Files toolbox.</para>
<para>The title of the toolbox
includes <literal>Scope=Files, Policy=TSOL</literal>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Add the proxy host and the webservices host to the list of computers.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Navigate to the Computers and Networks tool.</para>
<para>In the
Computers tool, click the Action menu and choose Add Computer. For the proxy
host and the webservice host, do the following.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Add the host name and IP address.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Apply the changes.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Configure the zones and the MLPs.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Navigate to the Trusted Network Zones tool.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If the zone names do not appear in the list, click the Action
menu and choose Add Zone Configuration.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Assign a label to each zone.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the MLP Configuration for Local IP Addresses, specify the appropriate
port/protocol field.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Apply the settings.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Customize a template for each zone.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Navigate to the Security Templates tool.</para>
<para>Click the
Action menu and choose Add Template. For each host, create a template. Assign
the template a recognizable name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create the template.</para>
<para>Use the host name for the template
name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify CIPSO for the Host Type</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Use the label of the zone for the Minimum Label and for the Maximum
Label.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Assign the zone label to the Security Label Set.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the Hosts Explicitly Assigned tab.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Add an Entry section, add the IP address that is associated
with the zone.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Apply the settings.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Close the Solaris Management Console.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>3. Start the zones.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> boot</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the global zone, add routes for the new addresses.</para>
<para>If
the zones have a shared IP address, do the following.</para>
<screen># route add proxy <replaceable>labeled-zones-IP-address</replaceable>
# route add webservice <replaceable>labeled-zones-IP-address</replaceable>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
