<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="printconcept-76595">



<title>Managing Printing Services (Overview)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter provides information about managing printers in the Solaris Operating System (Solaris
OS).</para>
<para>This is a list of the overview information in this chapter.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="printconcept-42">What's New in Printing?</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="printconcept-15">Where to Find Printer Tasks</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="printconcept-40">Printing in the Solaris Operating System</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="printconcept-31908">The LP Print Service</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="printconcept-49">The Solaris Print Client-Server Process</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="egkan">IPP Listener Support</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="erfaz">Expanded Printer Support</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="printconcept-42">
<title>What's New in Printing?</title>
<para>This section describes new and changed printing features in this Solaris
release. For a complete listing of new Solaris features and a description
of Solaris releases, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2183">
<citetitle remap="book">What’s New in Solaris Express</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>For information on new or changed printing features in the Solaris 10
initial release, see the following references:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="erfaz">Expanded Printer Support</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="egkan">IPP Listener Support</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="gdodg">
<title>Internet Printing
Protocol Improvements</title>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Solaris Express 8/06:</emphasis> In this Solaris
release, improvements have been made to the Internet Printing Protocol (IPP)
feature that was introduced in the Solaris 10 OS. In the Solaris 10 OS, the
implementation of IPP provided server side listening support for the protocol.
In this Solaris release, client side support for IPP has been added to the
Solaris Print Service.</para>
<para>IPP client side support was added to enable Solaris client systems to
communicate with IPP-based print services, such as those on the Linux and
Mac OS X operating systems, as well as other platforms. Small improvements
were made to the IPP Listening Service (server side support) to promote better
interoperability. Listening service improvements include some relatively minor
changes to converge toward more commonality in representation in printer and
job attribute data.</para>
<para>The IPP server and client implementation in the Solaris OS is one of
several <trademark>OpenSolaris</trademark> printing projects that are currently
under development. Open printing provides a set of specifications and implementations
of software that enables you to create standardized, scalable printing components
for the Solaris and Linux software, or any operating system that contains
a set of POSIX interfaces.</para>
<para>For more information about server side support for IPP, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="egkan">IPP Listener Support</olink>.</para>
<para>More information about OpenSolaris Printing can be found at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://opensolaris.org/os/community/printing/">
</link>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="gdkmc">
<title>PAPI Print Command and IPP Implementation</title>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Solaris Express 8/06:</emphasis> The Free Standards
Group (FSG) Open Printing Application Programming Interface (PAPI) implementation
provides applications with a single interface for interacting with LPD (bsd/lpd
protocol) and IPP based servers, as well as name service storage of configuration
data. PAPI is protocol-independent, so applications can be written to use
the PAPI. Because these applications are not tied to a particular print server,
you can replace one print service with another print service without impacting
the layers above. PAPI implementation includes support for PAPI, Version 1.0
of the specification.</para>
<para>PAPI implementation in the Solaris OS includes the modification of several
commonly-used BSD and SYSV print commands. The modified print commands are
layered on top of the PAPI. As a result, you can run the commands on top of
multiple protocols or services.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>Some advantages of these new command implementations include:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Improved consistency between desktop applications and command-line
interfaces (CLI)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Multiple print protocol and service support from the command
line</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>IPP client side support for improved interoperability with
other operating systems and platforms, such as Linux, Mac OS X, and other
IPP based print services</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Enhanced remote capability when using IPP between print client
and print server</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Ability to disable network services and retain access to local
printers</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about the BSD and SYSV command changes, see the
following man pages:</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="accept-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>accept</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="cancel-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>cancel</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="disable-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>disable</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="enable-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>enable</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lp-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lp</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lpc-1b">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpc</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1B
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpmove-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpmove</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lpq-1b">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpq</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1B
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lprm-1b">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lprm</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1B
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lpstat-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpstat</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The PAPI implementation in this Solaris release also includes server
side support for IPP, which is layered on top of the API. This support includes
a set of protocol-specific libraries and an Apache module, Versions 1.0 and
2.0. As with the print command implementation, the IPP Listening Service can
be used with any print service that supports the PAPI. For more information,
see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="gdodg">Internet Printing Protocol Improvements</olink>.</para>
<para>The PAPI print command and IPP implementation in the Solaris OS is one
of several OpenSolaris printing projects that are currently under development.
Open printing provides a set of specifications and implementations of software
that enables you to create standardized, scalable printing components for
the Solaris and Linux software, or any operating system that contains a set
of POSIX interfaces.</para>
<para>To learn more about OpenSolaris Printing, go to <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://opensolaris.org/os/community/printing/">
</link>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="fwmxi">
<title>Device URI Protocol</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1">
<primary>device URI protocol</primary>
<secondary>Uniform Device Identifer</secondary>
<tertiary>Solaris printing features</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-2">
<primary>Uniform Device Identifier (URI)</primary>
<secondary>Solaris printing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Solaris Express 6/05:</emphasis> The Solaris
printer software has been modified to support remote printer access. This
feature is new in the Solaris Express 2/05 release. You can now specify a
Uniform Device Identifer (URI) device when adding a network printer. You can
use the command-line or Solaris Print Manager to specify a <replaceable>device-uri.</replaceable>.</para>
<para>To specify a <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> from the command-line,
use the <command>lpadmin</command> command with the <option>
v</option> and <option>
m</option> options.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p <replaceable>printer</replaceable> -v <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> -m <replaceable>uri</replaceable>
</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Note that the <option>
v</option> option is still a valid option for
specifying devices other than a <replaceable>device-uri.</replaceable>.</para>
<para>For example, to add the printer <literal>Lucille</literal>, specifying
the <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> <filename>smb://server/queue</filename>,
and the interface script that is included in the Solaris printing software,
you would type:</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p lucille -v smb://server/queue -m uri -n /usr/lib/lp/model/ppd \
/system/foomatic/Epson/Epson-Stylus_Color_777-Stc777p.upp.ppd.gz</userinput>
</screen>
<note>

<para>You must use the <option>
m</option> option in the command-line
syntax to specify an interface script, or the back-.end process ignores the
print request. The script can be the interface script that is included in
the Solaris printing software or another <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> aware
interface script.</para>
</note>
<para>The following <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> formats are currently
supported:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>smb://server/printer</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>smb://workgroup/server/printer</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>smb://username:password@server/printer</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>smb://username:password@workgroup/server/printer</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>More information can be found at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://us1.samba.org/samba/docs/man/smbspool.8.html">
</link>.</para>
<para>The types of modifications that were made to the Solaris printing software
can potentially support additional <literal>device-uri</literal> schemes.</para>
<para>To specify a <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> when using Solaris
Print Manager to add a new network printer, select the <literal>URI</literal> option
in the <literal>Protocol</literal> drop-down menu of the New Network Printer
page. Provide a supported <replaceable>device- uri</replaceable> in the destination
field.</para>
<para>Other modifications include the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The Solaris spooler has been modified to enable the passing
of the <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable> information to the back-end interface
script as the environment variable, <literal>DEVICE_URI</literal>.  Since
this information is passed to the printer as an environment variable, the
existing interface scripts are not able to take advantage of this information.
However, these scripts are not adversely impacted.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <filename>/etc/lp/model/uri</filename> file communicates
with the printer through the use of helper applications and the <replaceable>device-uri</replaceable>. The interface script also has the ability to process PPD files
and uses Foomatic to convert print data to a printer-ready format.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="fnyww">
<title>
<literal>Never Print Banner</literal> Option Available
in Solaris Print Manager</title>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Solaris Express 3/05:</emphasis> Solaris Print Manager has
been expanded to include an additional <literal>Never Print Banner</literal> option.
Using this option ensures that banner pages are never printed for the specified
print queue.</para>
<para>Previously, you only had two choices for printing banner pages in Solaris
Print Manager:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>You could enable the <literal>always print banner</literal> option
in Solaris Print Manager.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>You could select the banner <literal>on</literal> or <literal>off</literal> option when you submitted a print job.</para>
<para>By default,
this option was set to <literal>on</literal>. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Within Solaris Print Manager, a drop-down menu with the following selections
is now available:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<literal>Always Print Banner</literal>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>When this option is selected, banner page printing is turned
on, regardless of the command options that are typed on the command line.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<literal>User Selectable - Default=on</literal>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>When this option is selected, banner page printing is turned
off, if the appropriate <command>lp</command> command-line option is used.
If you do not specify an option from the command line when submitting a print
job, banner page printing is turned on by default.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<literal>Never Print Banner</literal>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>When this option is selected, banner page printing is turned
off, regardless of the command options that are typed on the command line.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>These banner page printing options reflect the options that are available
when using the <command>lpadmin</command> command for printing to local print
queues. For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpadmin-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpadmin</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
<para>For more information about the available printing options for a given
Solaris release when using the Solaris Print Manager, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermka">Table 1–2</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printconcept-15">
<title>Where to Find Printer Tasks</title>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec3" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Printer Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For More Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Set up printers with Solaris Print Manager and the LP print service</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-33230">Chapter 3, Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Administer printers with the LP print service after the printers are
set up</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-15883">Chapter 4, Administering Printers (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Manage character sets, filters, forms, and fonts</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12319">Chapter 5, Managing Character Sets, Filters, Forms, and Fonts (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Customize the LP print service</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-6.xml" targetptr="printcust-66310">Chapter 6, Customizing the LP Print Service (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printconcept-40">
<title>Printing in the Solaris Operating System</title>
<para>The Solaris printing software provides an environment for setting up
and managing client access to printers on a network.</para>
<para>The Solaris printing software contains these tools:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Print Manager – A graphical user interface (GUI)
that provides the ability to manage printing configuration on a local system
or in a name service.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The LP print service commands – A command-line interface
(CLI) that is used to set up and manage printers on a local system or in a
name service. These commands also provide functionality that extend beyond
the other print management tools.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Even if you do use Solaris Print Manager to set up printing, you will
have to use some of the <command>lp</command> print service commands to completely
manage printing on the Solaris Operating System. For more information, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-15883">Chapter 4, Administering Printers (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
<para>The limitations of Solaris print software include the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>No support for print servers defined as <literal>s5</literal> (the
System V print protocol) in previous Solaris releases</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>No print filtering on print clients</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-86">
<title>Solaris Print Manager</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-3">
<primary>Solaris Print Manager</primary>
<secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Solaris Print Manager is a Java technology-based GUI that enables you
to manage local and remote printer configuration. This tool can be used in
the following name service environments: LDAP, NIS, NIS+,  and files. You must be logged in as superuser or assume an equivalent
role to use this tool.</para>
<para>Solaris Printer Manager  centralizes printer information when
used in conjunction with a name service. Using a name service for storing
printer configuration information is desirable because a name service makes
printer information available to all systems on the network. This method provides
easier  printing administration.</para>
<para>Solaris Print Manager recognizes existing printer information on the
printer servers, print clients, and in the name service databases.  No conversion
tasks are required to use Solaris Print Manager as long as the print clients
are running either the  Solaris 2.6, 7,
8, 9, 10, or Solaris Express  releases.</para>
<para>The Solaris Print Manager package is <literal>SUNWppm</literal>.</para>
<para>For step-by-step instructions on setting up new printers with Solaris
Print Manager, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-33230">Chapter 3, Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-85">
<title>Printing Support in the Name Service Switch</title>
<para>The <literal>printers</literal> database in <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename>,
the name service switch file, provides centralized printer configuration information
to print clients on the network. </para>
<para>By including the <literal>printers</literal> database and corresponding
sources of information in the name service switch file, print clients automatically
have access to printer configuration information without having to add it
to their own systems.</para>
<para>The default printers entry in the <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename> file
for files, LDAP, NIS, and NIS+ environments are described in the following
table. The <literal>nisplus</literal> keyword represents the <filename>printers.org_dir</filename> table. </para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="36.16*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="63.84*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Name Service Type</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Default <literal>printers</literal> Entry</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>files</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>printers:	user files</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>ldap</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>printers:	user files ldap</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>nis</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>printers:	user files nis</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>nis+</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>printers:	user nisplus files</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>For example, if your name service is NIS, printer configuration information
on print clients is searched for in the following sources in this order:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>user</literal> – Represents the user's <filename>$HOME/.printers</filename> file</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>files</literal> – Represents the <filename>/etc/printers.conf</filename> file</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>nis</literal> – Represents the <filename>printers.conf.byname</filename> table</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2251" targetptr="nsswitch.conf-4">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>nsswitch.conf</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
4
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3194">
<citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Naming
and Directory Services (DNS, NIS, and LDAP)</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="eekes">
<title>LDAP Print Support Guidelines</title>
<para>Keep the following in mind when you manage printer information in the
LDAP name service:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Print Manager uses the <command>ldapclient</command> command
to determine the default LDAP server name. If more than one server is specified,
the first server is automatically selected. For more information, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="ldapclient-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>ldapclient</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Print Manager always displays printer entries from
the current LDAP server. If the current LDAP server is not the domain's LDAP
master server, the list of printers displayed might not be the current list
of printers. The LDAP replica server might not have been updated by the master
server, and as a result, is out of sync with the master. Replica servers can
have various update replication agreements. For example, a change is made
on the master, and the replica servers can be updated immediately or once
a day.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the selected LDAP server is an LDAP replica server, any
updates are referred to the master server and are done there. This situation
again means that the printer list could be out of sync with the master server.
For example, a deleted printer might still appear in the displayed printer
list until the replica is updated from the master server.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Users can use the LDAP command-line utilities, <command>ldapadd</command> and <command>ldapmodify</command>, to update printer entries in the directory. However,
this method is not recommended. If these utilities are used, the user must
ensure that the <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> attribute value is
unique within the <literal>ou=printers</literal> container. If the <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> attribute value is not unique, the result of modifications
done by Solaris Print Manager, or by the <command>lpset</command> command,
might not be predictable.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-68">
<title>Choosing a Method to Manage Printers</title>
<para>Adding printer information to a name service makes access to printers
available to all systems on the network. Generally, doing so makes printer
administration easier because all the information about printers is centralized.</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="198*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="198*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Name Service Configuration</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Actions to Centralize Printer Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row rowsep="0">
<entry>
<para>Use a name service</para>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Do not use a name service</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Adding the printer adds the printer information to the printer server's
configuration files only. Print clients will not automatically know about
the printer.</para>
<para>You will have to add the printer information to every print client that
needs to use the printer.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>The following table describes the major printer-related tasks and the
tools available to perform the printing tasks.</para>
<table frame="topbot" xml:id="edhix">

<title>Solaris Printing Tools and Their Features</title>
<tgroup cols="6" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="67*"/>
<colspec colwidth="64*"/>
<colspec colwidth="64*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colwidth="67*"/>
<colspec colwidth="67*"/>
<colspec colname="column3" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Printing Tool</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Availability</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Graphical User Interface?</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Configures Network Printers?</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Manages Print Clients and Servers?</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Uses LDAP, NIS, or NIS+?</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Solaris Print Manager</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Solaris Express, Solaris 10, and compatible
versions and Solaris Easy Access Server 3.0</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<command>lp</command> commands </para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Solaris Express, Solaris 10, and compatible
versions</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Not available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>After using the preceding table to determine which printing tool is
best for your network environment, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-33230">Chapter 3, Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink> for printer setup information.</para>
<para>Most printing configuration tasks can be accomplished with Solaris Print
Manager. However, if you need to write interface scripts or add your own filters,
you need to use the LP print service commands. These  commands underlie Solaris
Print Manager. Performing printing administration tasks with LP print service
commands is described in <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-15883">Chapter 4, Administering Printers (Tasks)</olink>. </para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printconcept-31908">
<title>The LP Print Service</title>
<para>The <emphasis>LP print service</emphasis> is a set of software utilities
that allows users to print files while the users continue to work. </para>
<para>For background information about the LP print service, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="printref-76596">Chapter 7, LP Print Service (Reference)</olink>.</para>
<para>Other LP print service topics are described in the following sections.
Included are cross-references for further information.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-64">
<title>Managing Network Printers</title>
<para>A <emphasis>network printer</emphasis> is a hardware device that is
connected directly to the network. A network printer  transfers data directly
over the network to the output device. The printer or network connection hardware
has its own system name and IP address.</para>
<para>Network printers often have software support provided by the printer
vendor. If your printer has printer vendor-supplied software, then use the
printer vendor software. If the network printer vendor does not provide software
support, Sun supplied software is available. This software provides generic
support for network-attached printers. However, this software is not capable
of providing full access to all possible printer capabilities.</para>
<para>For step-by-step instructions on setting up a network printer, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-33230">Chapter 3, Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-66">
<title>Administering Printers</title>
<para>After you set up print servers and print clients, you might need to
perform these administration tasks frequently: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Delete a printer</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Delete remote printer access</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Check the status of printers</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Restart the print scheduler</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For step-by-step instructions on how to perform these printer administration
tasks, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-15883">Chapter 4, Administering Printers (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-65">
<title>Setting Definitions for Printers</title>
<para>Setting definitions for the printers on your network is an ongoing task
that lets you provide a more effective print environment for users. For example,
you can assign printer descriptions for all your site's printers to help users
find where a printer is located. Or, you can define a class of printers to
provide the fastest turnaround for print requests. </para>
<para>For information on setting up printer definitions, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="printconcept-76596">Chapter 2, Planning Printers on Your Network (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-67">
<title>Administering Character Sets, Filters,
Forms, and Fonts</title>
<para>Depending on your site's requirements and the types of printers you
have on the network, you might have to set up and administer printer-specific
features of the LP print service. For example, you can assign different print
wheels, filters, and forms to different printers. For background information
and step-by-step instructions on how to set up character sets, print filters,
forms, and fonts, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12319">Chapter 5, Managing Character Sets, Filters, Forms, and Fonts (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-72556">
<title>Customizing the LP Print Service</title>
<para>Although the LP print service is designed to be flexible enough to handle
most printers and printing needs,  the LP print service does not handle every
possible situation. You might have a print request that is not accommodated
by the standard features of the LP print service. Or, you might have a printer
that does not quite fit into the way the LP print service handles printers.</para>
<para>You can customize the LP print service in the following ways:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Adjust the printer port characteristics.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Adjust the <command>terminfo</command> database.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Customize the printer interface program.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Create a print filter.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Define a form.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For detailed descriptions and step-by-step instructions on customizing
the LP print service, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-6.xml" targetptr="printcust-66310">Chapter 6, Customizing the LP Print Service (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printconcept-49">
<title>The Solaris Print Client-Server Process</title>
<para>This section provides an overview of how Solaris printing works.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-51">
<title>The Print Client Process</title>
<para>The following figure illustrates the path of a print request from the
time the user initiates the request until the print request is printed.</para>
<figure xml:id="printconcept-fig-69">

<title>Overview of the Print Client Process</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/print_over2.fig30.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Illustration of the print client process in 5 steps.
See the following description of these 5 steps.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A user submits a print request from a print client.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print command checks a hierarchy of print configuration
resources to determine where to send the print request.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print command sends the print request directly to the
appropriate print server. A print server can be any server that accepts Berkley
Software Distribution (BSD) printing protocol, including SVR4 (LP) print servers
and BSD <command>lpd</command>-based print servers.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print server sends the print request to the appropriate
printer.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print request is printed. </para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-52">
<title>Using Print Clients</title>
<para>This section of the overview focuses on the <emphasis>print client</emphasis>,
a system that can send print requests to a print server. This section also
discusses print commands, which enable the print client to initiate print
requests.</para>
<para>The following figure highlights the part of the print process in which
the user submits a print request from a print client.</para>
<figure xml:id="printconcept-fig-70">

<title>The User Submits a Print Request from
a Print Client</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/print_over2.fig5.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Illustration of what happens when a user submits a print
request. See the following section for a description of these 5 steps.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-53">
<title>What Is a Print Client?</title>
<para>A system becomes a print client when you install the Solaris print software
and enable access to remote printers on the system. </para>
<para>The Solaris print software checks the following resources to locate
printers and printer configuration information:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The command-line interface by using the <command>lp</command> <option>
d</option> command (atomic or POSIX format)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A user's <literal>LPDEST</literal> or <literal>PRINTER</literal> variables</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <literal>_default</literal> variable in the sources configured
for the <literal>printers</literal> database in the <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename> file</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The user's <filename>$HOME/.printers</filename> file</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The local <filename>/etc/printers.conf</filename> file</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The LDAP, NIS, or NIS+ name service database</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The print client sends its requests to the print server's queue. The
print client does not have a local queue. The client writes the print request
to a temporary spooling area only if the print server is not available, or
if an error occurs. This streamlined path to the server decreases the print
client's use of resources, reduces the chances for printing problems, and
improves performance. </para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-57">
<title>Printer Configuration Resources</title>
<para>This section describes the resources that the print software uses to
locate printer names and printer configuration information.</para>
<para>The print software can use a name service, which is a network (shared)
resource for storing information that can be accessed on a network. The name
service can be used for storing printer configuration information for all
printers on the network. When you add a printer in
the name service, all print clients on the network can access the printer. </para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-58">
<title>How the Print Software Locates Printers</title>
<para>The following figure highlights the part of the print process in which
the print software checks a hierarchy of printer configuration resources to
determine where to send the print request.</para>
<figure xml:id="printconcept-fig-72">

<title>How the Print Client Software Locates
Printers</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/print_over2.fig19.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Illustration of the steps the print client software uses
to locate printers. Also shows the various printer sources. See the following
description.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A user submits a print request from a print client by using
the <command>lp</command>  or <command>lpr</command> command. The user can
specify a destination printer name or class in any of three styles:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Atomic style, which is the <command>lp</command> command and
option, followed by the printer name or class, as shown in this example:</para>
<screen>% <userinput>lp -d neptune</userinput> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
</screen>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>POSIX style, which is the print command and option, followed
by <replaceable>server:printer</replaceable>, as shown in this example:</para>
<screen>% <userinput>lpr -P galaxy:neptune</userinput> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
</screen>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Context-based style, as shown in this example:</para>
<screen>% <userinput>lpr -d thisdept/service/printer/</userinput>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
</screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print command locates a printer and printer configuration
information as follows: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The print command checks to see if the user specified a destination
printer name or printer class in one of the three valid styles. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the user didn't specify a printer name or class in a valid
style, the command checks the user's <literal>PRINTER</literal> or <literal>LPDEST</literal> environment variable for a default printer name.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If neither environment variable for the default printer is
defined, the command checks the sources configured for the <literal>printers</literal> database
in the <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename> file. The name service sources
might be one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>LDAP directory information tree in the domain's <literal>ou=printers</literal> container</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>NIS <filename>printers.conf.byname</filename> map</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>NIS+ <filename>printers.conf_dir</filename> map</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-61">
<title>Using Print Servers</title>
<para>The print server is a system that has a local printer connected to it
and makes the printer available to other systems on the network. The following
figure highlights the part of the print process in which the print server
sends the print request to the printer.</para>
<figure xml:id="printconcept-fig-73">

<title>The Print Server Sends a Print Request
to the Printer</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/print_over2.fig58.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Illustration of a print server sending a print request
in 5 steps. See the following description of these 5 steps.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The print client submits a print request.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print request is processed on the print client.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print request goes to the print server.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print request goes to the printer.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The print output is produced on the printer.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printconcept-62">
<title>The BSD Printing Protocol</title>
<para>The print commands use the BSD printing protocol. One of the big advantages
of this protocol is that it can communicate with a variety of print servers: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>lpd</command>-based print servers </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>SunOS 5.10 and compatible SVR4 (LP) print servers </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Any other print server or printer that accepts the BSD printing
protocol </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The BSD printing protocol is an industry standard that is widely used
because it provides compatibility between different types of systems from
various manufacturers. </para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Starting with
the Solaris Express 8/06 release</emphasis>, PAPI has been implemented in
the Solaris OS. PAPI support includes the modification of the majority of
the common BSD and SYSV printing commands. These new command implementations
are layered on top of the PAPI. As a result, these commands can now work with
a number of print services.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about the BSD and SYSV command changes, see the
following man pages:</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="accept-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>accept</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="cancel-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>cancel</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="disable-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>disable</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="enable-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>enable</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lp-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lp</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lpc-1b">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpc</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1B
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpmove-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpmove</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lpq-1b">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpq</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1B
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lprm-1b">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lprm</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1B
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="lpstat-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpstat</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="gdkmc">PAPI Print Command and IPP Implementation</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="egkan">
<title>IPP
Listener Support</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-4">
<primary>IPP listener</primary>
<secondary>Internet Printing Protocol listener</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-5">
<primary>Internet Printing Protocol listener</primary>
<secondary>IPP listener</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Support for the Internet Printing Protocol (IPP) Listening Service was
introduced in the Solaris 10 release. IPP supports a standardized printing
protocol on a network. The IPP implementation in the Solaris OS is one of
several ongoing OpenSolaris printing projects. Open printing provides a set
of specifications and implementations of software that enables you to create
standardized, scalable printing components for the Solaris and Linux software,
or any operating systems that contain a set of POSIX interfaces. </para>
<para>The IPP Listener provides a single, standard interface for querying
printing systems that are on a network. In the Solaris OS, the IPP Listener
performs by listening for <literal>HTTP</literal> requests on port 631. The
listener receives print client requests and communicates those requests to
the printing system.</para>
<note>

<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Starting
with the Solaris Express 8/06 release</emphasis>, improvements have been made
to the listening service. In addition, client side support for IPP has been
introduced. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="gdodg">Internet Printing Protocol Improvements</olink> and <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="gdkmc">PAPI Print Command and IPP Implementation</olink> for more
information about these changes.</para>
</note>
<para>To implement the IPP listener on your network, set up a print server
on your local system. For more information on setting up a print server, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-20070">Setting Up a Print Server</olink>. Once the print
server has been configured, the IPP listening service automatically starts.
If you want to stop (disable) the service, you can use <command>svcadm</command> with
the IPP listener's FMRI (svc:/application/print/ipp-listener). For information
on how to use <command>smf</command> and <command>svcadm</command>, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2252" targetptr="smf-5">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>smf</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
5
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="svcadm-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>svcadm</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man pages.</para>
<para>You also need to configure a print client in order to access the printer
system. For example, on the Microsoft Windows operating system, you configure
a network printer with the network path set to <literal>http://</literal>
<replaceable>server-name</replaceable>
<literal>:631/printers/</literal>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>. </para>
<para>The Solaris OS implementation of the IPP listener is in the form of
an Apache web server module (<literal>mod-ipp.so</literal>). The default configuration
in the Solaris OS enables all of the implemented operations for the IPP listener.
To modify the configuration information, edit the <literal>/etc/apache/httpd-standalone-ipp.conf</literal> file. Then stop and restart the IPP service. </para>
<para>More information about OpenSolaris Printing can be found at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://opensolaris.org/os/community/printing/">
</link>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="erfaz">
<title>Expanded Printer Support</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-6">
<primary>PPD files</primary>
<secondary>PostScript Printer Description files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-7">
<primary>printer support</primary>
<secondary>features of</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-8">
<primary>Raster Image Processor</primary>
<secondary>RIP</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10:</emphasis> Specific modifications
have been made to incorporate the RIP feature and PPD files into the Solaris
print subsystem. Two interface scripts, <command>standard_foomatic</command>,
and <command>netstandard_foomatic</command>, are available. These interface
scripts provide the generic Solaris interface between the Solaris spooler
and the back-end process of the Solaris print server.</para>
<para>The following are examples of the types of printers that are supported:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Lexmark Optra E312</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Epson Stylus Photo 1280</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Canon BJC-55</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>QMS magicolor 2+</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="ermjp">
<title>Expanded Printer Support Features</title>
<para>This section describes the following expanded printer support features: <indexterm xml:id="indexterm-9">
<primary>Expanded Printer Support</primary>
<secondary>Raster Image Processor (RIP)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-10">
<primary>Expanded Printer Support</primary>
<secondary>adding printers with PPD files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-11">
<primary>Expanded Printer Support</primary>
<secondary>modifications to Solaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-12">
<primary>Expanded Printer Support</primary>
<secondary>changes to <command>lpstat</command> command output when using PPD files</secondary>
</indexterm>
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermjy">Raster Image Processor Support</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermjz">Support for PostScript Printer Description Files</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermkb">Solaris Print Manager Options</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermju">Using the <option>
n</option> Option to the <command>lpadmin</command> Command</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermjr">Using the <command>lpstat</command> Command to Determine if a PPD File Was Used to Create a Print Queue</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect3 xml:id="ermjy">
<title>Raster Image Processor Support</title>
<para>The RIP enables you to print to printers that do not have resident PostScript
processing  capabilities. The Solaris printing software provides the print
server RIP and supporting technologies. The RIP occurs behind the scenes.
However, to use the appropriate driver you need to configure each printer,
by using either Solaris Print Manager or the <command>lpadmin</command> <option>
n</option> command. For step-by-step instructions on using the <command>lpadmin</command> <option>
n</option> command, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="ertru">How to Add a New Attached Printer by Using LP Print Service Commands</olink>.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="ermjz">
<title>Support for PostScript Printer Description Files</title>
<para>The <command>lpadmin</command> and <command>lpstat</command> commands,
as well as the Solaris Print Manager printer definition screens, support the
use of PPD files.</para>
<para>The following new software packages are associated with this feature:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWa2psr</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWa2psu</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWespgs</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWffiltersr</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWffiltersu</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWfppd</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWgimpprint</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWhpijs</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWimagick</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>SUNWpsutils</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about supported printers, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="ermjs">Where to Find Information On Supported Printers</olink>.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="ermkb">
<title>Solaris Print Manager Options</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-13">
<primary>Solaris Print Manager</primary>
<secondary>modifications to printer definitions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Starting with the Solaris 10 release, the following options are available
in Solaris Print Manager:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The Use PPD files option is the default option when creating
a new print queue in Solaris Print Manager. You can choose to not use PPD
files by removing the checkmark from this option. To switch back to using
PPD files, recheck the Use PPD files option.</para>
<note>

<para>If Solaris Print Manager cannot locate the <filename>ppdcache</filename> file
to use, the Use PPD files option in the Print Manager drop-down menu is greyed
out and not available for use.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If you create a new print queue or modify an existing print
queue with PPD files in Solaris Print Manger, you cannot assign the printer
type or file content type printer definitions. However, If you do not use
PPD files when creating a print queue, you can assign these printer definitions
by deselecting the <literal>Use PPD files</literal> option in the Solaris
Print Manager drop-down menu.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When creating a new print queue or modifying an existing print
queue with PPD files, the following Solaris Print Manager screens are available:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>New Attached Printer</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Modify Printer Properties (for an attached printer)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>New Network Printer</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Modify Printer Properties (for a network printer)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For these screens, when creating a print queue with PPD files, you are
required to provide the following information:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Printer Make</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Printer Model</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Printer Driver</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>This table describes the printer definitions that are used by Solaris
Print Manager, and their availability, depending on which Solaris software
release you are running.</para>
<note>

<para>The printer make, model, and driver printer definitions are only
available when you create a print queue with the Use PPD files default option
in the Print Manager drop-down menu selected. This is the default option .
Conversely, the printer type and file content type printer definitions are
only available when you have deselected the <literal>Use PPD files</literal> option.</para>
</note>
<table frame="all" xml:id="ermka">

<title>Printer Definitions Used by Solaris Print
Manager</title>
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="30.69*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec3" colwidth="32.48*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec4" colwidth="35.82*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Printer Definition</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available in Solaris 9 Release?</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available Starting With the Solaris 10 Release?</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Name</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Server</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Description</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Applicable</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Applicable</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Port</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available, for attached printers</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available, for attached printers</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Type</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
<para>Not available by default in the Solaris 9 9/04 release.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available, by deselecting the <literal>Use PPD files</literal> option
in Print Manager drop-down menu</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>File Content Type</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
<para>Not available by default in the Solaris 9 9/04 release</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available, by deselecting the <literal>Use PPD files</literal> option
in Print Manager drop-down menu</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Make</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Not available</para>
<para>Yes, available in the Solaris 9 9/04 release</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Model</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Not available</para>
<para>Available in the Solaris 9 9/04 release</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Printer Driver</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Not available</para>
<para>Available in the Solaris 9 9/04 release</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Fault Notification</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Destination</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available for a network printer</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available for a network printer</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Protocol</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available for a network printer</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available for a network printer</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Options</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>User Access List</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>Default Printer</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>Always Print Banner</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>User Selectable - Default=on</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>Never Print Banner</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
<entry>
<para> <literal>Always Print Banner</literal> (Default option)</para>
<para>
</para>
<para>
<literal>User Selectable - Default=on</literal> (Available
when <literal>Always Print Banner</literal> option is deselected)</para>
<para>
<literal>Never Print Banner</literal> (Not available)</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available (Default option for Solaris 10 release)</para>
<para>
<literal>User Selectable - Default=on</literal> </para>
<para>
<literal>Never Print Banner</literal>
</para>
<para>Starting with the Solaris Express 3/05 release,  these options are located in a pull-down menu within
Solaris Print Manager.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>For a detailed description of the printer make, printer model, and printer
driver printer definitions, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="printplan-30">Setting Printer Definitions</olink>.</para>
<note>

<para>Using PPD files is a per-queue configuration option, and is not
a requirement. PPD files are not required for printers that already contain
the RIP feature.  You can continue to use Solaris Print Manager to configure
these printers the same way that you did for previous Solaris releases. To
do so, you must remove the checkmark from the <literal>Use PPD files</literal> default
option in the Print Manager drop-down menu in Solaris Print Manager before
adding the new printer.</para>
</note>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="ermju">
<title>Using the <option>
n</option> Option to the <command>lpadmin</command> Command</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-14">
<primary>Expanded Printer Support</primary>
<secondary>
<option>
n</option> option to <command>lpadmin</command> command for specifying PPD files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-15">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>
<option>
n</option> option</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The <option>
n</option> option to the <command>lpadmin</command> command
enables you to specify the PPD file that you want to use when creating a new
print queue or modify an existing print queue.</para>
<para>For example, to add the print queue, <literal>foobar</literal>, to a
Lexmark printer, you type the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p foobar -v <replaceable>device</replaceable> -I postscript -m standard_foomatic \
-n /<replaceable>path</replaceable>/Lexmark-Optra_E312-Postscript.ppd.gz</userinput>
</screen>
<para>When using the <option>
n</option> option to the <command>lpadmin</command> command,
specify the full path and file name to the PPD file.</para>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpadmin-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpadmin</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="ermjs">
<title>Where to Find Information On Supported Printers</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-16">
<primary>supported printers</primary>
<secondary>where to find information</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-17">
<primary>information about supported printers</primary>
</indexterm>
<caution role="caution">

<para>The location of the PPD files and the <filename>ppdcache</filename> are private interfaces, as is the contents of the <filename>ppdcache</filename> file.
The placement of these files and the contents of the <filename>ppdcache</filename> are
subject to change in future releases. You should not build software that relies
on these files being in their current location or that relies on the data
being in the format that is currently used.</para>
</caution>
<para>If the file that is required by your printer is not available, you can
add your own PPD file. If you use the <command>lpadmin</command> <option>
n</option> command
to create a new print queue, you can store your own PPD files anywhere that
you choose. However, if you use Solaris Print Manager to create the print
queue, the PPD file must have an entry in the <filename>ppdcache</filename> file.</para>
<para>Directories of PPD files are located in the <filename>/usr/lib/lp/model/ppd/</filename> directory. The output of the <command>ls</command> command lists
all the PPD files for a particular printer manufacturer. The names of the
files reflect the printer model that is supported.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="ermjv">
<title>Specifying Your Own PPD Files</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-18">
<primary>Expanded Printer Support</primary>
<secondary>specifying your own PPD files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-19">
<primary>specifying your own PPD files</primary>
<secondary>Expanded Printer Support</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-20">
<primary>PPD files</primary>
<secondary>specifying your own</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>When you use the <command>lpadmin</command> command with the <option>
n</option> option
to specify a PPD file, you are required to provide the full path to the PPD
file. If you choose to use a PPD file that is located in a different directory,
you must specify the full path to that file.</para>
<para>For example, to specify the <filename>xyz.ppd</filename> file that is
located in the user's home directory, you would type the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p foo -n /home/<replaceable>user</replaceable>/stuff/xyz.ppd -m \
standard_foomatic -I postscript -v /<replaceable>device</replaceable>
</userinput>
</screen>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ermjr">
<title>Using the <command>lpstat</command> Command to Determine
if a PPD File Was Used to Create a Print Queue</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-21">
<primary>
<command>lpstat</command> command</primary>
<secondary>changes when using PPD files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>If a PPD file was used to create a print queue, the PPD file that the
specified queue is configured to use is now listed in the <command>lpstat</command> command
output. If you do not specify a PPD file when creating a new print queue,
the <command>lpstat</command> command continues to display the same output
as it did previously. For an example of the <command>lpstat</command> command
output when using PPD files, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-55230">How to Check the Status of Printers</olink>.</para>
<para>You can use Solaris Print Manager to modify queues that were created
without the use of PPD files. In such cases, Solaris Print Manager uses the
previous printer definitions, which do not include the printer make, model,
and driver printer definitions.</para>
<para>For tasks that are associated with expanded printer support, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-2">Setting Up Printing (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
