<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="managefiles-1">



<title>Mounting Files in Trusted Extensions</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter describes how LOFS mounts and NFS mounts work on a system
that is configured with Trusted Extensions.</para>
<itemizedlist remap="jumplist">
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-16">File Systems in Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txnet-10">File System Mounts in Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-31">Access to NFS Mounted Directories in Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-26">Trusted Extensions Software and NFS Protocols</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-6">Managing Files and File Systems
(Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="managefiles-16">
<title>File Systems in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-553">
<primary>file systems in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm>Trusted Extensions software supports the same file systems and file
system management commands as the Solaris OS. In addition, Trusted Extensions attaches
a unique label to every non-global zone. All the files and directories that
belong to that zone are mounted at the label of the zone. Any shared file
systems that belong to other zones or to NFS servers are mounted at the label
of the owner. Trusted Extensions prevents any mounts that would violate the MAC
policies for labeling. For example, a zone's label must dominate all of its
mounted file system labels, and only equally labeled file systems can be mounted
read-write.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="txnet-10">
<title>File System Mounts in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-554">
<primary>mounting</primary>
<secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm>Mounting file systems on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions is
similar to mounting file systems on a Solaris system. For permanent
mounts, you enter the standard mounting information in the <filename>vfstab</filename> file
on the client and the sharing information in the <filename>dfstab</filename> file
on the server. For dynamic mounts, use the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="mount-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>mount</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> command.</para>
<para>Labels affect which file systems can be mounted. File systems are shared
and are mounted at a particular label. For a Trusted Extensions client to write to
a file system that is NFS-mounted, the file system must be mounted read-write <emphasis>and</emphasis> be at the same label as the client. If you are setting up a
mount between two Trusted Extensions hosts, the server and the client must have
compatible remote host templates of type <literal>cipso</literal>. If you
are setting up a mount between a Trusted Extensions host and an unlabeled host,
file systems that are at the single label that is specified for the unlabeled
host in the <filename>tnrhdb</filename> file can be mounted.</para>
<para>Labels also affect which file systems can be viewed. By default, lower-level
objects are not available in a user's environment. Therefore, in the default
configuration, an ordinary user cannot view files that are in a zone at a
lower level than the user's current level. If site security permits, you can
make these lower-level objects visible to the user.  Files that are mounted
with LOFS can be viewed, but cannot be modified. For details on NFS mounts,
see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-31">Access to NFS Mounted Directories in
Trusted Extensions</olink>.</para>
<para>The <filename>/export/home</filename> pathname is the exception to lower-level
visibility. By default, users can see their lower-level home directories from
a higher label. For details, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txnet-12">Home Directory
Creation in Trusted Extensions</olink>.</para>
<para>The mount policy in Trusted Extensions has no MAC overrides. MAC policies
enforce the default configuration, and are invisible to ordinary users. Ordinary
users cannot see objects unless they have MAC access to them.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managefiles-31">
<title>Access to NFS Mounted Directories in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>By default, NFS-mounted file systems are visible at the label of the
exported file system. If the file system is exported read-write, users at
that label can write to the files. With the exception of home directories,
NFS mounts that are at a lower label than the user's current session require
administrative intervention to be visible to the user.</para>
<para>To make lower-level directories that are NFS-mounted visible to users
in a higher-level zone, the administrator of the global zone on the NFS server
exports the parent directory. The parent directory is exported at its label.
On the client side, the administrator of the global zone must configure each
zone that can mount the exported directory. Each zone must have the privilege <constant>net_mac_aware</constant>.</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Server configuration</term>
<listitem>
<para>On the NFS server, you export the parent directory in a <filename>dfstab</filename> file. The <filename>dfstab</filename> file must be modified
in the labeled zone of the directory that is being exported. For an example,
see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txconf-43">How to Share File Systems</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Client configuration</term>
<listitem>
<para>The <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege must be specified
in the zone configuration file that is used during initial zone configuration.
So, a user who is permitted to see all lower-level home directories must have
the <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege in every zone except the
lowest one. For an example, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txconf-41">How to Mount
File Systems</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<example xml:id="managefiles-22">

<title>Providing Access to Lower-Level Home Directories</title>
<para>On the home directory server, the administrator modifies the <filename>dfstab</filename> file in every labeled zone. The <filename>dfstab</filename> file
exports the <filename>/export/home</filename> directory with <literal>rw</literal> access,
so that when the directory is mounted at the same label, the home directory
is writable. To export the <filename class="directory">/export/home</filename> directory
of <literal>PUBLIC</literal>, the administrator creates a workspace at the <literal>PUBLIC</literal> label on the home directory server, and modifies the <filename>dfstab</filename> file in that zone.</para>
<para>On the client, the administrator of the global zone checks that every
labeled zone except the lowest label has the <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege.
This privilege permits the mount. This privilege can be specified by using
the <command>zonecfg</command> command during zone configuration. The lower-level
home directory can be viewed only. MAC protects the files in the directory
from modification. The files can only be modified by a process at the same
label of the files.</para>
</example>
<sect2 xml:id="txnet-12">
<title>Home Directory Creation in Trusted Extensions</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-555">
<primary>creating</primary>
<secondary>home directories</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-556">
<primary>home directories</primary>
<secondary>creating</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Home directories are a special case in Trusted Extensions. You need to make
sure that the home directories are created in every zone that a user can use.
Also, the home directory mount points must be created in the zones on the
user's system. For NFS-mounted home directories to work correctly, the conventional
location for directories, <filename class="directory">/export/home</filename>,
must be used. The automounter has been modified to handle home directories
in every zone, that is, at every label. For details, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-19">Changes to the Automounter in Trusted Extensions</olink>.</para>
<para>Home directories are created when users are created. In Trusted Extensions,
the Solaris Management Console is used to create users, so the Solaris Management Console creates the home directories.
However, the console creates the home directories in the global zone of the
home directory server. On that server, the directories are mounted by LOFS.
Home directories are automatically created by the automounter if they are
specified as LOFS mounts. However, the automounter cannot automatically create
home directories on remote NFS servers. Either the user must first log in
to the NFS server or administrative intervention is required. To create home
directories for users, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7314" targetptr="txconf-56">
<citetitle remap="section">Enable Users to Access Their Home Directories</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="managefiles-19">
<title>Changes to the Automounter in Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, each label requires a separate home directory mount.
The <command>automount</command> command has been modified to handle these
labeled automounts. For each zone, <command>autofs</command> mounts an <literal>auto_home_</literal>
<replaceable>zone-name</replaceable> file. For example, the following
is the entry for the global zone in the <filename>auto_home_global</filename> file:</para>
<screen>+auto_home_global
*       -fstype=lofs    :/export/home/&amp;</screen>
<para>When a zone is booted that permits lower-level zones to be mounted,
the following occurs. The home directories of lower-level zones are mounted
read-only under <filename>/zone/&lt;</filename>
<replaceable>zonename</replaceable>
<filename>&gt;/export/home</filename>. The <filename>auto_home_&lt;</filename>
<replaceable>zonename</replaceable>
<filename>&gt;
</filename> map specifies the <filename>/zone</filename> path
as the source directory for an <filename>lofs</filename> remount onto <filename>/zone/&lt;</filename>
<replaceable>zonename</replaceable>
<filename>&gt;/home/&lt;</filename>
<replaceable>username</replaceable>
<filename>&gt;
</filename>.</para>
<para>For example, the following is an <filename>auto_home_public</filename> entry
in an <filename>auto_home_</filename>
<replaceable>zone-at-higher-label</replaceable> map
that is generated from a higher level zone:</para>
<screen>+auto_home_public
*       -fstype=lofs    :/zone/public/export/home/&amp;</screen>
<para>The corresponding entry in the public zone is:</para>
<screen>auto_home_public
*       -fstype=lofs    :/export/home/&amp;</screen>
<para>When a home directory is referenced and the name does not match any
entries in the <filename>auto_home_&lt;</filename>
<replaceable>zonename</replaceable>
<filename>&gt;
</filename> map, the map tries to match this loopback mount specification.
The software creates the home directory when two conditions are met.</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>When the map finds the match of the loopback mount specification</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When the home directory name matches a valid user whose home
directory does not yet exist in <replaceable>zonename</replaceable>
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>For details on changes to the automounter, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="automount-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>automount</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managefiles-26">
<title>Trusted Extensions Software and NFS Protocols</title>
<para>Trusted Extensions software recognizes the NFS protocols that the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS)
supports: NFS Version 2 (V2), NFS Version 3 (V3), and NFS Version 4 (V4).</para>
<para>Trusted Extensions software recognizes labels on NFS Version 4 (V4) only.
Therefore, any file system that is being mounted from a NFS server that is
running Trusted Extensions software must be mounted with <replaceable>vers=4</replaceable> and <replaceable>proto=tcp</replaceable> mount options.</para>
<para>A host that is configured with Trusted Extensions can also share its own
file systems with unlabeled hosts. A file or directory that is exported to
an unlabeled host is <emphasis>writable</emphasis> if its label equals the
label that is associated with the remote host in its trusted networking database
entries. A file or directory that is exported to an unlabeled host is <emphasis>readable</emphasis> only if its label is dominated by the label that is associated
with the remote host.</para>
<para>Communications with computers that are running a release of Trusted Solaris software
is possible only at a single label. The Trusted Extensions system and the Trusted Solaris system
must assign to the other system a template with the unlabeled host type. The
unlabeled host types must specify the same single label. As an unlabled NFS
client of a Trusted Solaris server, the label of the client cannot be <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>.</para>
<para>The NFS protocol that is used is independent of the type of the local
file system. Rather, the protocol depends on the type of the sharing computer's
operating system. The file system type that is specified to the <filename>mount</filename> command
or in the <filename>vfstab</filename> for remote file systems is always NFS.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managefiles-6">
<title>Managing Files and File Systems (Tasks)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-557">
<primary>Managing Files and File Systems (Tasks)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-558">
<primary>tasks and task maps</primary>
<secondary>Managing Files and File Systems (Tasks)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The following table describes common tasks that are performed when managing files
and file systems and the procedures associated with the tasks.</para>
<informaltable frame="all" pgwide="1">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Back up files</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Protect your data by backing it up.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-13">How to Back Up Files</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Restore data</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Retrieve data from a backup.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-14">How to Restore Files</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Share the contents of a directory</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Allow the contents of a directory to be shared among users.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txconf-43">How to Share File Systems</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Mount the contents of a directory</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Allow the contents of a directory to be mounted.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txconf-41">How to Mount File Systems</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create home directory mount points</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Create mount points for every user at every label. This enables users
to access their home directory on a system that is not the NFS home directory
server.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7314" targetptr="txconf-56">
<citetitle remap="section">Enable Users to Access Their Home Directories</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle>
</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Hide lower-level information from a user who is working at a higher
label</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Prevent the viewing of lower-level information from a higher-level window.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="managezones-3">How to Disable the Mounting of Lower-Level
Files</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Troubleshoot file system mounting problems</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Resolve problems with mounting a file system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="managefiles-20">How to Troubleshoot Mount Failures</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managefiles-13">

<title>How to Back Up Files</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-559">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>backing up</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-560">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>backing up files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Assume the Operator role.</para>
<para>This role includes the Media
Backup rights profile.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Use one of the following backup methods:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>/usr/lib/fs/ufs/ufsdump</command> for major backups</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>/usr/sbin/tar cT</command> for small backups</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A script calling either of the above commands</para>
<para>For
example, the <application>Budtool</application> backup application calls the <filename>ufsdump</filename> command. For details on the <option role="nodash">T</option> option
to the <command>tar</command> command, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="tar-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>tar</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managefiles-14">

<title>How to Restore Files</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-561">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>restoring</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-562">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>restoring files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Assume the System Administrator role.</para>
<para>This role includes
the Media Restore rights profile.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Use one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>/usr/lib/fs/ufs/ufsrestore</command> for major restores</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>/usr/sbin/tar xT</command> for small restores</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A script calling either of the above commands</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For details on the <option role="nodash">T</option> option to the <command>tar</command> command, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="tar-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>tar</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<caution>

<para>Only these commands preserve labels.</para>
</caution>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="txconf-43">

<title>How to Share File Systems</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-563">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>sharing file systems</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-564">
<primary>files and file systems</primary>
<secondary>mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-565">
<primary>mounting</primary>
<secondary>file systems</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-566">
<primary>directories</primary>
<secondary>mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-567">
<primary>directories</primary>
<secondary>sharing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-568">
<primary>files and file systems</primary>
<secondary>sharing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>As in the Solaris OS, the Mounts and Shares tool in the Solaris Management Console cannot be
used to mount or share file systems in labeled zones. Use the <filename>dfstab</filename> file
in the labeled zone, and the <command>shareall</command> and <command>mount</command> commands
to export and mount file systems in labeled zones.</para>
<caution>

<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-569">
<primary>protecting</primary>
<secondary>file systems by using non-proprietary names</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-570">
<primary>files and file systems</primary>
<secondary>naming</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-571">
<primary>names of file systems</primary>
</indexterm>Do not use proprietary names for shared file systems. The names
of shared file systems are visible to every user.</para>
</caution>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be on the file server, in the zone at the label of the files
that you want to share. You must be the superuser, or in the System Administrator
role.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Create a workspace at the label of the file system that is going
to be shared.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create a new <filename>dfstab</filename> file in that zone.</para>
<para>Each zone shares its exported directories at the label of the zone.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Go to the zone's <filename class="directory">/etc/dfs</filename> directory.</para>
<screen># cd <filename class="directory">/zone/<replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>/etc/dfs</filename>
</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Open the Admin Editor.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type the full pathname of the <filename>dfstab</filename> file
into the editor.</para>
<screen># /zone/<replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>/etc/dfs/dfstab</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Add an entry to share the exported directory.</para>
<para>For
example, the following entry shares an application's files at the label of
the containing zone.</para>
<screen>share -F nfs -o ro /<replaceable>viewdir</replaceable>/<replaceable>viewfiles</replaceable>
</screen>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Repeat the preceding steps for every zone that is going to share
a directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the global zone, run the <command>shareall</command> command.</para>
<para>The actual sharing occurs when each zone is brought into the <literal>ready</literal> or <literal>running</literal> state.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Display the status of the labeled zones.</para>
<screen># zoneadm list -v</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>For each zone, share the directories.</para>
<para>As root in the
global zone, run one of the following commands for each zone. Each zone can
share its directories in any of these ways.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If the zone is not in the running state and you do not want users
to log in to the server at the label of the zone, set the zone state to <literal>ready</literal>.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zonename</replaceable> ready</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>If the zone is not in the running state and users are allowed
to log in to the server at the label of the zone, boot the zone.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zonename</replaceable> boot</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>If the zone is already running, reboot the zone.</para>
<screen># zoneadm -z <replaceable>zonename</replaceable> reboot</screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step>
<para>To enable the client to mount the exported files, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txconf-41">How to Mount File Systems</olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="txconf-41">

<title>How to Mount File Systems</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-572">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>mounting file systems</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-573">
<primary>zones</primary>
<secondary>
<constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>Unlabeled and labeled hosts can be mounted on a Solaris Trusted Extensions labeled host.
The assigned label of the remote host must be identical to the zone in which
the file system is being mounted.</para>
<para>As in the Solaris OS, the Mounts and Shares tool in the Solaris Management Console cannot be
used to mount or share file systems in labeled zones. Use the <filename>dfstab</filename> file
in the labeled zone, and the <command>shareall</command> and <command>mount</command> commands
to export and mount file systems in labeled zones.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be on the client system, in the zone at the label of the files
that you want to mount. You must be the superuser, or in the System Administrator
role. The zone must be configured with the <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> privilege.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Create a workspace at the label of the file system that is going
to be mounted.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In that workspace, run the <command>mount</command> command.</para>
<para>You can also modify the local <filename>vfstab</filename> file to mount
the file system across reboots.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managefiles-10">

<title>How to Share Files for User Access at a Higher
Label</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-574">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>sharing file systems for access at higher label</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-575">
<primary>files</primary>
<secondary>sharing lower-level</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-576">
<primary>sharing</primary>
<secondary>lower-level files</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure role="single-step">
<step>
<para>Follow the procedure, <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="txconf-41">How to Mount
File Systems</olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="managefiles-20">

<title>How to Troubleshoot Mount Failures</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-577">
<primary>mounting</primary>
<secondary>troubleshooting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-578">
<primary>troubleshooting</primary>
<secondary>mounted file systems</secondary>
</indexterm>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in the zone at the label of the files that you want to mount.
You must be the superuser, or in the System Administrator role.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Check the security attributes of the NFS server.</para>
<para>Use
the Security Templates tool in the Solaris Management Console, at the appropriate scope.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Check that the IP address of the NFS server is an assigned host
in one of the security templates.</para>
<para>The address might be directly
assigned, or be assigned indirectly through a wildcard mechanism. The address
can be in a labeled template, or in an unlabeled template.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Check the label that the template assigns to the NFS server.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Check that the label is consistent with the label at which you
are trying to mount the files.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>To mount file systems from an NFS server that is running earlier
versions of Trusted Solaris software, do the following:</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>For a Trusted Solaris 1 NFS server, use the <literal>vers=2</literal> and <literal>proto=udp</literal> options to the <command>mount</command> command.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>For a Trusted Solaris 2.5.1 NFS server, use the <literal>vers=2</literal> and <literal>proto=udp</literal> options to the <command>mount</command> command.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>For a Trusted Solaris 8 NFS server, use the <literal>vers=3</literal> and <literal>proto=udp</literal> options to the <command>mount</command> command.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
<para>To mount file systems from any of these servers, the server must be
assigned to an unlabeled template.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
