<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="gdhbj">



<title>Upgrading When Solaris Zones Are Installed
on a System (Planning)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter provides an overview of  how Solaris Zones partitioning
technology relates to upgrading the Solaris OS when non-global zones are configured.</para>
<para>This chapter contains the following sections:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="gavhc">Solaris Zones (Overview)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="gdkbx">Upgrading With Non-Global Zones</olink>l</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="gcdfn">Disk Space Requirements for Non-Global
Zones</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="gavhc">
<title>Solaris Zones (Overview)</title>
<para>For complete information on overview, planning, creating and configuring
zones,  see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="zones.intro-1">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Introduction to Solaris Zones,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Solaris Zones partitioning technology is used to virtualize operating
system services and provide an isolated and secure environment for running
applications. A non-global zone is a virtualized operating system environment
created within a single instance of the Solaris OS. When you create a non-global
zone, you produce an application execution environment in which processes
are isolated from the rest of the system. This isolation prevents processes
that are running in one non-global zone from monitoring or affecting processes
that are running in other non-global zones. Even a process running with superuser
credentials cannot view or affect activity in other zones.  A non-global zone
also provides an abstract layer that separates applications from the physical
attributes of the machine on which they are deployed. Examples of these attributes
include physical device paths.</para>
<para>Every Solaris system contains a global zone. The global zone has a dual
function. The global zone is both the default zone for the system and the
zone used for system-wide administrative control. All processes run in the
global zone if no non-global zones are created by the global administrator.
 The global zone is the only zone from which a non-global zone can be configured,
installed, managed, or uninstalled. Only the global zone is bootable from
the system hardware. Administration of the system infrastructure, such as
physical devices, routing, or dynamic reconfiguration (DR), is only possible
in the global zone. Appropriately privileged processes running in the global
zone can access objects associated with the non-global zones. </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gdkbx">
<title>Upgrading With Non-Global Zones</title>
<para>When you are upgrading the Solaris OS, you cannot upgrade a system  that has
non-global zones installed. The behavior of the upgrade depends on the program
you are using.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>With the Solaris interactive installation program, you are
not given the option to upgrade the OS. This occurs because the upgrade software
 displays a list of all disk partitions that contain a Solaris OS that  can
be upgraded. If a partition contains the Solaris OS and has non-global  zones
installed, that OS is not included in the list. See the upgrade installation
log for error messages. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>With the custom JumpStart installation program, the upgrade
fails. See the upgrade    installation log for error messages.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>With Solaris Live Upgrade, you can create a boot environment
with the <command>lucreate</command> command, but when you are using the <command>luupgrade</command> command, the upgrade fails. An error message is displayed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-71">
<primary>Solaris Zones partitioning technology</primary>
<secondary>installing with a Solaris Flash archive</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-72">
<primary>non-global zone</primary>
<secondary>installing with a Solaris Flash archive</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-73">
<primary>archives</primary>
<secondary>installing with a Solaris Flash archive</secondary>
</indexterm>A Solaris Flash archive cannot be properly created when a
non-global zone is installed. The Solaris Flash feature is not compatible
 with Solaris Zones partitioning technology. If you create a Solaris Flash
archive, the resulting  archive is not installed properly when the archive
is deployed under these conditions:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The archive is created in a non-global zone</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The archive is created in a global zone that has non-global
zones installed</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="gdhbs">
<title>Backing Up Your System Before Performing an Upgrade
With Zones</title>
<para>You should back up the global and non-global zones on your Solaris system
before you perform the upgrade. For information about backing up a system
with zones installed, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="z.admin.ov-1">Chapter 26, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Zones Administration (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gcdfn">
<title>Disk Space Requirements for Non-Global Zones</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-74">
<primary>Solaris Zones partitioning technology</primary>
<secondary>disk space requirements</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-75">
<primary>non-global zone</primary>
<secondary>disk space requirements</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-76">
<primary>disk space</primary>
<secondary>planning for non-global zones</secondary>
</indexterm>When installing the global zone, be sure to  reserve enough disk
space for all of the zones you might create. Each non-global zone might have
unique disk space requirements. </para>
<para>No limits are placed on how much disk space can be consumed by a zone.
 The global zone administrator is responsible for space restriction.  Even
a small uniprocessor system can support a number of zones running simultaneously.
 The characteristics of the packages installed in the global zone affect the
space requirements of the non-global zones that are created.  The number of
packages and space requirements are factors.</para>
<para>For complete planning requirements and recommendations, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="z.conf.start-1">Chapter 18, <citetitle remap="chapter">Planning and Configuring Non-Global Zones (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
