<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="jumpstartoverview-4">



<title>Custom JumpStart (Overview)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter provides an introduction and overview to the custom JumpStart
installation process.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="jumpstartoverview-1">Custom JumpStart Introduction</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="preparecustom-3">How the JumpStart Program
Installs Solaris Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="jumpstartoverview-1">
<title>Custom JumpStart Introduction</title>
<para>The custom JumpStart installation method is a command–line interface
that enables you to automatically install or upgrade several systems, based
on profiles that you create. The profiles define specific software installation
requirements. You can also incorporate shell scripts to include preinstallation
and postinstallation tasks. You choose which profile and scripts to use for
installation or upgrade. The custom JumpStart installation method installs
or upgrades the system, based on the profile and scripts that you select.
Also, you can use a <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file to specify configuration
information so that the custom JumpStart installation is completely hands-off.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="fxjww">
<title>Custom JumpStart Example Scenario</title>
<para>The custom JumpStart process can be described by using an example scenario.
In this example scenario, the systems need to be set up with the following
parameters:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Install Solaris on 100 new systems.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Seventy of the systems are SPARC based systems that are owned
by the engineering group and need to be installed as standalone systems with
the Solaris OS software group for developers.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The remaining 30 systems are x86 based, owned by the marketing
group and need to be installed as standalone systems with the Solaris OS software
group for end users.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>First, the system administrator must create a <filename>rules</filename> file
and a profile for each group of systems. The <filename>rules</filename> file
is a text file that contains a rule for each group of systems or single systems
on which you want to install the Solaris software. Each rule distinguishes
a group of systems that are based on one or more system attributes. Each rule
also links each group to a profile.</para>
<para>A profile is a text file that defines how the Solaris software is to
be installed on each system in the group. Both the <filename>rules</filename> file
and profile must be located in a JumpStart directory.</para>
<para>For the example scenario, the system administrator creates a <filename>rules</filename> file that contains two different rules, one for the engineering
group and another for the marketing group. For each rule, the system's network
number is used to distinguish the engineering group from the marketing group.</para>
<para>Each rule also contains a link to an appropriate profile. For example,
in the rule for the engineering group, a link is added to the profile, <filename>eng_profile</filename>, which was created for the engineering group. In the
rule for the marketing group, a link is added to the profile, <literal>market_profile</literal>, which was created for the marketing group.</para>
<para>You can save the <filename>rules</filename> file and the profiles on
a diskette or on a server. </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A profile diskette is required when you want to perform custom
JumpStart installations on nonnetworked, standalone systems.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A profile server is used when you want to perform custom JumpStart
installations on networked systems that have access to a server.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>After creating the <filename>rules</filename> file and profiles, validate
the files with the <command>check</command> script. If the <command>check</command> script
runs successfully, the <filename>rules.ok</filename> file is created. The <filename>rules.ok</filename> is a generated version of the <filename>rules</filename> file
that the JumpStart program uses to install the Solaris software.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="preparecustom-3">
<title>How the JumpStart Program Installs Solaris
Software</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix256">
<primary>standalone systems</primary>
<secondary>custom JumpStart installation example</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix257">
<primary>custom JumpStart installation</primary>
<secondary>examples</secondary>
<tertiary>nonnetworked</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix258">
<primary>custom JumpStart installation</primary>
<secondary>examples</secondary>
<tertiary>standalone system</tertiary>
</indexterm>After you validate the <filename>rules</filename> file and the
profiles, you can begin a custom JumpStart installation. The JumpStart program
reads the <filename>rules.ok</filename> file. Then, the JumpStart program
searches for the first rule with defined system attributes that match the
system on which the JumpStart program is attempting to install the Solaris
software. If a match occurs, the JumpStart program uses the profile that is
specified in the rule to install the Solaris software on the system.</para>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="preparecustom-fig-2">Figure 2–1</olink> illustrates
how a custom JumpStart installation works on a standalone, nonnetworked system.
The system administrator initiates the custom JumpStart installation on Pete's
system. The JumpStart program accesses the rules files on the diskette in
the system's diskette drive. The JumpStart program matches <filename>rule
2</filename> to the system. <filename>rule 2</filename> specifies that the
JumpStart program use <filename>Pete's profile</filename> to install the Solaris
software. The JumpStart program reads <filename>Pete's profile</filename> and
installs the Solaris software, based on the instructions that the system administrator
specified in <filename>Pete's profile</filename>. </para>
<figure xml:id="preparecustom-fig-2">

<title xml:id="preparecustom-59497">How a Custom
JumpStart Installation Works: nonnetworked Example</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/prepare_custom.fig169.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>The context describes the illustration.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix259">
<primary>custom JumpStart installation</primary>
<secondary>examples</secondary>
<tertiary>networked</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix260">
<primary>network installation</primary>
<secondary>custom JumpStart installation, example</secondary>
</indexterm>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="preparecustom-fig-3">Figure 2–2</olink> illustrates
how a custom JumpStart installation works with more than one system on a network.
 Previously, the system administrator set up different profiles and saved
the profiles on a single server. The system administrator initiates the custom
JumpStart installation on one of the engineering systems. The JumpStart program
accesses the rules files in the <filename>JumpStart/</filename> directory
on the server. The JumpStart program matches the engineering system to <filename>rule 1</filename>. <filename>rule 1</filename> specifies that the JumpStart
program use <filename>Engineering Group's Profile</filename> to install the
Solaris software. The JumpStart program reads <filename>Engineering Group's
Profile</filename> and installs the Solaris software, based on the instructions
that the system administrator specified in <filename>Engineering Group's Profile</filename>. </para>
<figure xml:id="preparecustom-fig-3">

<title xml:id="preparecustom-38900">How a Custom
JumpStart Installation Works: Networked Example</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/prepare_custom.fig168.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>The context describes the illustration.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix255">
<primary>custom JumpStart installation</primary>
<secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix238">
<primary>custom JumpStart installation</primary>
<secondary>preparing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix239">
<primary>custom JumpStart installation</primary>
<secondary>description</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix240">
<primary>preparing for installation, with custom JumpStart</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix241">
<primary>root (<filename>/</filename>) file systems</primary>
<secondary>profile example</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix242">
<primary>hard disks</primary>
<secondary>swap space</secondary>
<tertiary>profile examples</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix243">
<primary>size</primary>
<secondary>swap space</secondary>
<tertiary>profile examples</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="preparecustom-ix244">
<primary>swap file systems</primary>
<secondary>profile examples</secondary>
</indexterm>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="preparecustom-fig-1">Figure 2–3</olink> describes
the order in which the JumpStart program searches for custom JumpStart files. </para>
<figure xml:id="preparecustom-fig-1">

<title xml:id="preparecustom-99104">What Happens
During a Custom JumpStart Installation</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/prepare_custom.fig167.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>The flow diagram shows the order in which the custom
JumpStart program searches for files.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect1>
</chapter>
