<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="tasks-basics-2">



<title>Registering Your Solaris Express
3/06 or 10/05 Software (Tasks)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter describes how to register a system that is running either the Solaris Express
3/06 or the Solaris
Express 10/05 software. If you are running at least the
Solaris Express 8/06 release, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkma">Chapter 17, Registering Your Solaris Software (Tasks)</olink>, for instructions. By registering your system, you can use Sun Update Connection
services to manage updates for your Solaris system. Registration is free,
and it involves sending only your basic system specifications to Sun. The
registration process is initiated when you reboot your Solaris system.</para>
<para>Starting with the  Solaris
Express 10/05 release, you can use the Solaris Registration GUI or the CLI to
register your Solaris system. The steps to register your Solaris software
vary depending on your Solaris OS version.</para>
<note>

<para>Any information in this chapter that pertains to a specific Solaris
release only, or was introduced in a specific Solaris release, is labeled accordingly.</para>
</note>
<itemizedlist>
<para>For Solaris Express 3/06 software,
the following methods of registration are available:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration wizard in your Solaris software. The wizard is available
upon system reboot. For information about registering your system, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxkr">Registering Your Solaris Software With the Registration Wizard</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration CLI. Starting
with the Solaris
Express 3/06 release, a registration CLI is available in the software.
See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> for
the steps to register your system.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration wizard in the Sun Update Manager application.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<para>For Solaris Express 10/05 software,
the following methods of registration are available:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration wizard in the Solaris software. The wizard is available
upon system reboot. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink> or <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galip">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink> for the steps to register your system.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration CLI. In Solaris Express
10/05 software, a registration CLI is available in the software. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> for
the steps to register your system.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Registration wizard in the Sun Update Manager application. For information
about registering by using the Sun Update Manager application, see the Sun Update Connection documentation on
docs.sun.com.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<para>If you are not running at least Solaris Express
10/05 software, the following methods of registration are available:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Update Manager application.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Registration CLI. The CLI is available in the following patches:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>SPARC – At least 120776-02</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>x86 – At
least 120777-02</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For information about registering using the CLI, print the README file
located in the update before installing the update. Information about registering using
the CLI is also available at <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> and in the Solaris OS Man Pages Collection.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>This is a list of the overview information in this chapter.</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gawoh">Solaris Software Registration (Overview)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fxblr">Solaris Software Registration (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwp">What Is a Sun Online Account?</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxyc">What Is a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number?</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxkr">Registering Your Solaris Software With the Registration Wizard</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gawin">Registering Your Solaris Software Later</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gateq">Disabling the Solaris Registration </olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note arch="x86">

<para>If the keyboard's Num Lock is on, the Tab and Backspace
keys on the keyboard might not work. To activate the Tab and Backspace keys,
turn off Num Lock.</para>
</note>
<para>For a complete listing of new Solaris software features and a description of
Solaris releases, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2183">
<citetitle remap="book">What’s New in Solaris
Express</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="gawoh">
<title>Solaris Software Registration (Overview)</title>
<para>When you register your Solaris software
and provide a service plan number (also called a <emphasis>subscription key</emphasis>),
you can use <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaykv" type="custom-text">Sun Update Connection</olink> client
services to manage your Solaris software updates.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>The following registration options are available:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Register the Solaris software and receive software updates.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Register later.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Never register.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The Solaris Registration
wizard does not appear after your system is registered or after you select
the Never Register option. If you choose the Never Register option, you can
still register your system from the Update Manager application or from the
CLI.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>When you register your system, you choose how the updates are delivered
and how they are applied. The following options are available:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Receive updates from Sun Update Connection, System Edition services.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Receive updates from a local source, such as a local proxy
server.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Manage updates remotely by using the Sun Update Connection
application, henceforth referred to as <emphasis>Update Connection</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Manage updates manually by using the <command>smpatch add</command> and
the <command>smpatch remove</command> commands.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="gaykv">
<title>What Is Sun Update Connection, System Edition?</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-309">
<primary>patches</primary>
<seealso>
updates</seealso>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-310">
<primary>Sun Update Connection services</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-311">
<primary>updates</primary>
<secondary>applying with Sun Update Connection</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-312">
<primary>Sun Update Manager</primary>
</indexterm>
<itemizedlist>
<para>Sun Update Connection, System Edition System
Edition (also called <emphasis>Sun Update Connection</emphasis>)
services are designed to compare an individual system configuration and status
to a database of configuration data and business rules. The following tools
are available with Sun Update Connection, System Edition:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Update Manager – An application that assesses your system
status and recommends system-specific updates. You are notified when new updates
are available for your system. Update Manager enables you to manage updates
on your system, including identifying update dependencies and determining
installation order for each system. You can use Update Manager to view a list
of applied updates, to apply new updates to your system, and to remove updates from
your system.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Update Connection – A web application hosted at Sun
that enables you to remotely manage updates on one or more systems. You can
view and install updates for systems that are registered with Update Manager.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Update Connection Proxy – A system on your intranet that provides
updates to eligible systems. The Update Connection Proxy is similar to a local update server, but updates are sent over
the Internet from Sun to the Update Connection Proxy. The Update Connection Proxy transfers
the updates to your systems within your intranet. The Update Connection Proxy system must
obtain updates either from a local collection of updates or from the Sun update
server. .</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<para>Sun Update Connection, System Edition is available with the following service subscriptions:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris 10 OS service plan</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<trademark class="service">SunSpectrum</trademark> service
plan</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Preventive Services</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about Sun Update Connection, System Edition, see the documentation on docs.sun.com.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="fxblr">
<title>Solaris Software Registration (Task Map)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-313">
<primary>Solaris Express 3/06 or 10/05 software, registration wizard (Task Map)</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The following task map identifies the procedures that you might need
to perform to register your Solaris system.</para>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="110.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="167.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="119.00*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Obtain a Sun Online Account.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Registered assets are associated with a Sun Online Account. A Sun Online
Account is required to register your Solaris system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gcfkc">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxxs">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Purchase a subscription key (also called a  <emphasis>service plan
number</emphasis>).</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Use aservice plan number to register for additional Solaris updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcom">How to Purchase a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system with Update Manager to automatically manage your
updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Register your system with Update Manager if your system obtains update
data from the Sun update server or if you want to remotely manage updates.</para>
<para>Use the Update Manager GUI to automatically manage updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsh">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Specify a local source for updates for your system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>To obtain updates either from a Sun Update Connection Proxy or from
a collection of updates on a local system, specify a local source.</para>
<para>By default, your system obtains updates from Sun. If your system is
not connected to the Internet, you must provide a local update source. You
can use a network proxy to connect to the Internet. </para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsh">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Specify the network proxy to use.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If your system is connected to the Internet through a network proxy,
specify the network proxy information.</para>
<para>By default, no network proxy is specified.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsh">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system with Update Manager to manually manage your updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If your system obtains update data from the Sun update server, register
your system with Update Manager. </para>
<para>To manage updates manually, download updates from the Sun update server.
You must manually apply and remove the updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsx">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galip">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system without choosing an update option.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>You can register your Solaris software without selecting an update option
at registration. After you have successfully registered your Solaris software,
you can use the CLI or the Update Manager GUI to add an update option.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galnp">How to Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing an Update Option: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system as part of a noninteractive Solaris software installation.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>As a superuser, you can register a system and create a registration
profile.  The profile enables you to use Solaris JumpStart software, Solaris
Flash software, WAN boot, or a diskless client to register your other
systems.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create an automatic registration profile and ID.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>To autoregister,
you need a registration profile and registration ID. The profile and ID are
automatically generated when you register a system and select Enable Auto
Registration. </para>
<para>You must be a superuser to create an automatic registration profile.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbiem">How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If you want to register your Solaris software with the CLI, you must first create
a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File. This file is not the same file that is used for  the automatic
registration profile.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbts">How to Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register a system by using a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Use a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file to register your
other systems.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software by using the CLI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software by using the registration CLI instead
of the registration GUI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbgit">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gaxwp">
<title>What Is a Sun Online Account?</title>
<para>A <emphasis>Sun Online Account</emphasis> is a global Sun account that
enables you to access many Sun web applications and portals. You can move
between sites and portals in a single browser session without having to log
in multiple times.</para>
<note>

<para>If you can access Sun online services, such as the SunSolve web
site or the Sun Online Support Center, you already have a Sun Online Account.
You do not need to create a new account.</para>
</note>
<para>To create a Sun Online Account, your system must be connected to the
Internet. The information that you specify is saved locally and sent to Sun.
Use English characters for the information you supply.</para>
<para>You can create a Sun Online Account from most Sun applications and web
sites, including the Update Manager application and the Sun Update Connection
web application.</para>
<para>If you are running 
the Solaris Express 3/06 software, release, go to  <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gcfkc">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</olink> for the steps
to create a Sun Online Account. If you are the running Solaris Express
10/05 software, go to  <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxxs">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 10/05</olink> for the steps
to create a Sun Online Account.</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gcfkc">

<title>How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-314">
<primary>Sun Online Account, creating</primary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your Solaris system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration  screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Create a Sun Online Account.</para>
<para>The Create Sun
Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the required fields.</para>
<para>A Sun Online Account
user name must contain at least six valid characters: a-z, 0-9, @, - (dash),
_ (underscore), . (period).  The username is not case sensitive. The password
must contain at least six standard ASCII characters and is case sensitive.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Next. The data is validated to confirm the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The user name is not already assigned.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The required fields are completed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The entered data matches field validation logic.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the fields and select your Country/Territory. Click Terms
and Conditions to read the  Sun Terms of Use. If the terms are acceptable,
Click Next to agree to the Terms and Conditions and complete the creation
of your Sun Online Account.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gaxxs">

<title>How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express
10/05</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-315">
<primary>Sun Online Account, creating</primary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your Solaris system. Become superuser or assume an equivalent
role.</para>
<para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged commands. For
more information about roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task
Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security
Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration  screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Register the Solaris software and Receive software updates
and click Next.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Register to Manage Updates or click Next.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Create a Sun Online Account.</para>
<para>The Create Sun
Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the required fields.</para>
<para>Your account creation
will fail if any required fields are left blank.</para>
<para>A Sun Online
Account user name must contain at least six valid characters: a-z, 0-9, @,
- (dash), _ (underscore), . (period).  The username is not case sensitive.
The password must contain at least six standard ASCII characters and is case
sensitive.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Next.</para>
<para>The data is validated to confirm the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The user name is not already assigned.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The required fields are completed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The entered data matches field validation logic.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Continue.</para>
<para>The Terms of Use and Software License
window displays.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Continue Without a Subscription Key or Enter One Later.
If you do not have a key, you will still have access to limited updates by
using the Sun Update Manager.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Read the Sun Terms of Use. If the terms are acceptable, Click
I have read the agreement and I Accept.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Finish to complete the creation of your Sun Online Account.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gaxyc">
<title>What Is a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number?</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-316">
<primary>subscription key</primary>
<secondary>definition</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-317">
<primary>service plan</primary>
<secondary>definition</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>A subscription key or service plan number is associated with your Sun
support contract and enables you to access additional services.  When you provide a valid subscription
key, you can use Sun Update Manager to help you manage your updates. If
you do not specify a subscription key during registration,  you can later
add a subscription key by using the Update Manager application or <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwy" type="custom-text">by
reregistering your system using the CLI</olink>.</para>
<note>

<para>If you have a Sun support contract that includes software support,
your subscription key might be known as your service plan number, contract
ID, support agreement number, or entitlement token.</para>
</note>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbcom">

<title>How to Purchase a Subscription Key or Service Plan
Number</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-318">
<primary>subscription key</primary>
<secondary>purchasing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-319">
<primary>service plan</primary>
<secondary>purchasing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>To
purchase a plan, go to General Solaris OS Support Plans at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/service/support/software/solaris/">http://www.sun.com/service/support/software/solaris/</link>.</para>
<para>If you have questions on available plans, contact your
Sun representative.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Follow the directions on the web site.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gaxkr">
<title>Registering Your Solaris Software With the Registration
Wizard</title>
<para>Registering your
system enables you to use the Sun Update Manager. Update Manager is
designed to recommend updates that are based on your specific system information.
When you register your system, you choose how the updates are delivered and
how they are applied. You can manage the updates automatically or manually.
After you determine how the updates are managed, you can use the Update Connection application
or the Update Connection Proxy to deliver updates.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>The steps to register your software depend on your Solaris software
release. The following registration options are covered in this section:</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsh">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsx">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galnp">How to Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing an Update Option: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galip">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Each registered system is linked to a Sun Online Account. During system
registration, system specifications are gathered. This information is analyzed
at Sun, enabling Sun to send you an appropriate list of available updates.</para>
<para>System registration requires superuser access to your system. To successfully
register your system by using the registration wizard, your system must be
a desktop system with a monitor, keyboard, and graphics card. If you do not
have a desktop system, see the steps in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> to complete your system registration.</para>
<para>Your system must also have an Internet connection to send basic system
information to Sun, including the packages and patches installed on your system.
The system information is used to determine recommended updates. You can view
the information that is collected before you complete the registration. Information
is not sent to Sun until you complete the registration.</para>
<para>You can create a Sun Online Account and purchase a service plan during
the registration process. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwp">What Is a Sun Online Account?</olink> and <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxyc">What Is a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number?</olink> for more information.</para>
<para>To make changes to your registration, use the CLI or the Update Manager
application. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> or the <citetitle>Sun Update Manager 1.0 Administration
Guide</citetitle>.</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbbsh">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically
Manage Updates: Solaris Express 3/06</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>You can configure Update Manager to automatically manage updates on
your system. To manually download the updates from Sun and for the commands to manage
the updates, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsx">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Express 3/06</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>To successfully register, your system to be registered must be a desktop
system with a monitor, keyboard,
and graphics card. If your system has  an Internet
connection, 
basic system information, installed packages, and installed updates data is sent to
Sun. The system information is used to determine recommended updates. If your system does not have an Internet
connection, you can receive updates by specifying a network proxy or local
source.</para>
<para>You must have a Sun Online Account. If you do not
have a Sun Online Account, you can create an account during the registration
process.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your
system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser
or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles contain authorizations and
privileged commands. For more information about roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring
RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration
Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration
screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Sun Online
Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify
how your system will receive updates .</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>If your system does not connect to the Internet, determine
if you want to use a local source or a network proxy for updates. To specify
a network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbepq">Step 5</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If your system is connected to the Internet or you do not
want to specify a network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcwv" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbepq">
<para>To specify the network proxy that your system uses to
connect to the Internet, click Configure Network Proxy Settings.</para>
<para>If
your system is directly connected to the Internet, you do not need to specify
network proxy information and can proceed to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcwv" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>At the Network Proxy Settings screen, select Enable Network Proxy.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para> In the Proxy Host Name field, type your proxy host name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Port field, type your proxy port number.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your proxy requires authentication,  select Use Proxy Authentication. In the Proxy User Name field,
type the proxy user name  and in the Proxy Password field, type
the proxy password .</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To set these
network proxy values and close the dialog box, click OK.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbcwv">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password, then click Next.</para>
<para>The
Activation of Services screen appears.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password,
click Forgot Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve your
Sun Online Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gcfkc">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</olink> for the steps to create
an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbddv">
<para>Activate
Sun Update Manager.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To use the Sun Update Connection to manage your updates, select
Use Sun Update Manager and Sun Update Connection to manage updates, then click
Next.  The Select Service Level screen appears. Go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcwv" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To use a local update source to manage your updates, select Use
Sun Update Manager using a local update source, such as Sun Connection Proxy.
 The Apply Updates Using a Local Source screen appears. Go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcwv" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbcwk">
<para>Decide if you want access to all updates, or only security
and hardware support updates.</para>
<para>You can specify a service plan number
at any time to use the Sun Update Manager to manage your Solaris software updates.
See the <citetitle>Sun Update Manager 1.0 Administration Guide</citetitle> for
the steps to specify a service plan number in the Update Manager application.
To specify a service plan number by using the CLI, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwy">How to Reregister Your Solaris Software and Add a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number</olink>. </para>
<note>

<para>You can access all updates without a service plan number. If you register
with a service plan number, you can use the Sun Update Manager to help you
manage and apply your updates.</para>
</note>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To use the
Sun Update Manager to access updates, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gdjzq" type="auto-generated">Step 9</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To manually access and
manage  updates, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gdjzy" type="auto-generated">Step 10</olink>.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdjzq">
<para>To
use the Sun Update Manager to access all updates, perform the following steps:</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Select Enter a Service Plan Number, and then provide a valid service
plan number.</para>
<para>Your service plan number might be your support contract
number or subscription key. For more information about service plan numbers
and how to purchase a service plan, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxyc">What Is a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number?</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Read the Software License Agreement. If the terms are acceptable,
click the check box to accept the agreement, and then click Next.</para>
<para>The
Remote Software Updates Service screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>At the System Name field, type your host name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To view the system information to be sent to Sun, click What gets
sent.</para>
<para>A dialog box appears with the system information. Click
OK to close the box.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register
your other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<note>

<para>To successfully complete an autoregistration profile, you must
be logged in as superuser.</para>
</note>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink> or click Learn More or to get more
information.</para>
<para>Your registration options are saved in a <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.
To use the file to register other systems, place the file in the<filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system, reboot the system, and log in as superuser.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, click Yes, Sun
may contact me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Finish to complete your system registration and send your
system information to Sun.</para>
<para>To successfully complete the registration
process, basic system information must be sent to Sun. The information to
be sent is provided on the screen. The Registration Confirmation screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close.</para>
<para>Your system is registered. You can use
the Update Connection portal at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/mysunconnection/">
</link> to access updates and support according to the support
contract level that you used to register the system.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdjzy">
<para>To manually manage your updates and not register
with the Sun Update Connection, perform the following steps:</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Click Continue without providing a Service Plan Number.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Read the Software License Agreement. If the terms are acceptable,
click the check box to accept the agreement, then click Next.</para>
<para>The
System Registration screen appears. To successfully complete the registration
process, basic system information must be sent to Sun. The information to
be sent is displayed on the screen.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register
your other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink> or click Learn More for more information.</para>
<para>Your registration options are saved in a <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.
To use the file to register other systems, place the file in the<filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system, reboot the system, and log in as superuser.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, click Yes, Sun
may contact me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To complete your system registration and send your system information
to Sun, click Finish.</para>
<para>The Registration Confirmation screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close.</para>
<para>Your system is registered.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbbsx">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually
Manage Updates: Express 3/06</title>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>To successfully register, your system to be registered must be a desktop
system with a monitor,
keyboard, and graphics card.  If your
system has an Internet connection, basic system information, installed packages, and installed updates data to Sun. The system
information is used to determine recommended updates. If your system does not have an Internet
connection, you can receive updates by specifying a network proxy.</para>
<para>You must
have a Sun Online Account. If you do not have a Sun Online Account, you can
create an account during the registration process.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system. Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information
about roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Sun
Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your system does not connect to the Internet, determine if
you want to use a local source or a network proxy for updates. If your system
is connected to the Internet or you do not want to specify a network proxy,
go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbeui" type="auto-generated">Step 5</olink>.</para>
<para>To specify a network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbevx">Step 4</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbevx">
<para>To specify the network proxy your system uses to connect
to the Internet, click Configure Network Proxy Settings.</para>
<para>If your
system is directly connected to the Internet, you do not need to specify network
proxy information and you can go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbeui" type="auto-generated">Step 5</olink>.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>At the Network Proxy Settings screen, click Enable Network Proxy.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Host Name field, type your proxy host name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Port field, type your proxy port number.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your proxy requires authentication, click Use Proxy Authentication. In
the Proxy User Name field,
type the proxy user name and  in the Proxy Password
field, type the proxy
password.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To set these
network proxy values and close the dialog box, click OK.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbeui">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Activation of Services
screen appears.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password, then click Forgot
Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve your Sun Online
Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gcfkc">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</olink> for the steps to create
an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbeug">
<para>Click Use Sun Update Manager using a local update source,
such as Sun Connection Proxy,
then click Next.</para>
<para>The Apply Updates Using a Local Source screen
appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type the URL for your local server, then click Next.</para>
<para>The System Registration
screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To successfully complete the registration process, basic system
information must be sent to Sun. The information to be sent is displayed
on the screen.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register your
other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink> or click Learn More or for more information.</para>
<para>Your registration options are saved in a <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.
To use the file to register other systems, place the file in the<filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system, reboot the system, and log in as superuser.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, click Yes, Sun may contact
me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Finish to complete your system registration and send your
system information to Sun.</para>
<para>The Registration Confirmation screen
appears.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close.</para>
<para>Your system is registered. You can use
the Update Connection portal at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/mysunconnection/">
</link> to access updates and support according to the support
contract level that you used to register the system.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="galnp">

<title>How to
Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing an Update Option: Solaris Express 3/06</title>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>To successfully register, your system to be registered must be a desktop
system with a monitor, keyboard,
and graphics card. If you have an Internet connection. The Internet connection is used to send
basic system information, installed packages, and installed patches to Sun.
The system information is used to determine recommended updates. If your system does not have an Internet
connection, you can receive updates by specifying a network proxy or local
source.</para>
<para>You must have a Sun Online Account. If you do not
have a Sun Online Account, you can create an account during the registration
process.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system. Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information
about roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Sun
Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbewn">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password.
Click Next.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password,
click Forgot Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve your
Sun Online Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gcfkc">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</olink> for the steps to create
an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
<para>The Activation of Services screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbewj">
<para>Click Register the Solaris software without choosing
an update option, then click Next.</para>
<para>The System Registration screen appears. </para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To successfully complete the registration process, basic system
information must be sent to Sun. The information to be sent is displayed
on the screen.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register your
other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink> or click Learn More or to get more information.</para>
<para>Your registration options are saved in a <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.
To use the file to register other systems, place the file in the<filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system, reboot the system, and log in as superuser.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, click Yes, Sun may contact
me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To complete your system registration and send your system information
to Sun, click Finish.</para>
<para>The Registration Confirmation screen appears.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close.</para>
<para>To make changes to your registration,
use the CLI or the Update Manager application. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> or the <citetitle>Sun Update Manager
1.0 Administration Guide</citetitle>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="fwcch">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically
Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-320">
<primary>updates</primary>
<secondary>managing automatically</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>You can configure Update Manager to automatically manage updates on
your system. To manually download the updates from Sun, and the commands to
manage the updates, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galip">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your Solaris system. Become superuser or assume an equivalent
role.</para>
<para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged commands. For
more information about roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task
Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security
Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Register and Receive Software Updates, and click Next.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Register to Manage Updates to use the Update Manager GUI
to manage updates automatically.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your system does not connect to the Internet, determine if
you want to use a local source or a network proxy for updates. If your system
is connected to the Internet and you do not want to specify a local source
or network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcbh">Step 7</olink>.</para>
<para>To specify a local source for updates, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcbo">Step 5</olink>.</para>
<para>To specify a network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcbv">Step 6</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbcbo">
<para>If your system is not directly connected to the Internet
and you want to retrieve updates from a local source, enable the Update Connection
Proxy.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Click Configure the System to Retrieve Updates From a Local Source.</para>
<para>The Use a Local Source of Updates screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Patch Source URL field, type the URL to the local update
source.</para>
<para>The Update Connection Proxy URL has this form:</para>
<para>http://<replaceable>server-name</replaceable>:3816/solaris</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Finish to set these update source values, and to return
to the Sun Online Account screen.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbcbv">
<para>If your system is not directly connected to the Internet
and you use a network proxy, enable the network proxy feature.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Click Configure Network Proxy Settings.</para>
<para>The Network
Proxy Settings screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Enable Network Proxy.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Host Name field, type the host name for the proxy.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Port field, type the port number for the proxy.</para>
</step>
<step performance="optional">

<para>If a user name and password are needed
for proxy authentication, click Enable Network Proxy.</para>
<para>In the Proxy
User Name field, type
the proxy user name.</para>
<para>In the Proxy
Password field, type
the proxy user password.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To set these network proxy values and close the dialog box, click OK.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbcbh">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password, then click Next.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password,
click Forgot Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve your
Sun Online Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account. See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxxs">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 10/05</olink> for the steps to create
an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
<para>The Terms of Use and Software License screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Decide whether you want access to all updates, or only security
and hardware support updates.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To access all updates, select Enter Sun Subscription Key and type
your subscription key in the Key field.</para>
<para>Your subscription key might be your
support contract number. If you do not have a subscription key, sign up for
a Solaris OS support
plan. For information about general Solaris OS support plans, go to <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/service/support/software/solaris/">.</link>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To access only security and hardware support updates, click Continue
Without a Subscription Key or Enter One Later.</para>
<para>You can specify
a subscription key at any time to gain access to all Solaris software updates. See <citetitle>Sun Update Manager 1.0 Administration Guide</citetitle> for the steps to specify
a subscription key in the Update Manager GUI.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Read the Terms of Use and Software License Agreement. If the terms
are acceptable, click the check box to accept the agreement.</para>
<para>You
cannot use the Update Manager software unless you agree to the terms of use
and the software license.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Next.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you supplied a subscription key, the Remote Software Updates
Service screen appears. Go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbdcv">Step 9</olink>.
From this screen, you can view demonstrations (demos) of Update Connection
and Update Manager.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you did not supply a subscription key, the System Registration
screen appears. Go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxlp">Step 11</olink>.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gbdcv">
<para>Decide whether to manage updates on your systems remotely
or locally.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To manage updates remotely, click Activate Remote Update Management
Using the Sun Update Connection.</para>
<para>If you choose to manage updates
remotely, you can still use Update Manager to manage updates locally on your
system.</para>
<para>To view your system information that is sent to Sun, click
What Gets Sent.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To manage updates locally, click Activate Local Update Management.</para>
<para>To view your system information that is sent to Sun, click What Gets
Sent.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step>
<para>To complete your system registration, click Finish.</para>
<para>System
information is sent to Sun. The Registration Confirmation screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gaxlp">
<para>Click Close to close the registration wizard.</para>
<para>The Checking dialog box shows the progress of update analysis on your
system. Your system is registered. To view available updates, go to the Update
Connection application.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="galip">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually
Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-321">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>using the registration wizard</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>To use the Update Manager GUI to manage updates automatically, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your Solaris system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Registration Wizard appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Register and Receive Software Updates, and click Next.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Apply Updates Manually.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Finish to exit the Registration Wizard.</para>
<para>You
are ready to manually manage updates on your system by using the <command>smpatch add</command> and <command>smpatch remove</command> commands.<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-322">
<primary>smpatch commands</primary>
</indexterm>
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<taskrelated role="see-also">

<para>For information about using the <command>smpatch add</command> command
and the <command>smpatch remove</command> command to manage updates, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="smpatch-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>smpatch</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</taskrelated>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gbicw">
<title>Registering Your Solaris
Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-323">
<primary>registration</primary>
<secondary>autoregistration profile</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-324">
<primary>autoregistration profile</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-325">
<primary>autoregistering</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>When you register a Solaris system, you can create an autoregistration profile and
an Auto Registration ID that you can use to register your other Solaris systems.
Your Auto Registration ID is associated with your Sun Online Account and is
valid for one year. You can display, renew, or invalidate your Auto Registration
ID on the Support / Services page on My Sun Connection at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/mysunconnection/">
</link>. For information
about how to perform administration tasks for your Auto Registration ID, see
the FAQ on the My Sun Connection Support / Services page.</para>
<para>You can use the registration profile and ID to register other systems
by using one of the following installation methods:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicx" type="custom-text">Solaris JumpStart</olink> software —
Automate the installation or upgrade of multiple systems based on profiles
that you create.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbidu" type="custom-text">Solaris Flash</olink> software —
Replicate the same software and configuration on multiple systems.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicy" type="custom-text">WAN boot</olink> —
Install systems over a wide area network (WAN) or the Internet.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbidv" type="custom-text">Diskless client</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>

<para>The steps to install using the above methods are not detailed
in this document. For detailed instructions about how to use the above installation
methods, see the Solaris Software Release and Installation Collection documentation
on docs.sun.com.</para>
</note>
<para>The registration ID is valid for one year. You can reissue or invalidate
your registration ID on the Sun Connection portal at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/mysunconnection/">
</link>.</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbiem">

<title>How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-326">
<primary>
<filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>To use the Autoregistration feature, become a superuser,  use the Solaris Registration Wizard to register a Solaris
system, and select the Enable Auto Registration option during registration.
When you complete your registration, a <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file
is created in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Determine the registration options and the Solaris software version
that you want to use for your profile.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gawoh">Solaris Software Registration (Overview)</olink> for the registration options.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Register a Solaris system with the configuration options that
you want.</para>
<para>Register your system by using one of the following procedures. Be sure to click the
Enable Auto Registration checkbox before you click Finish to complete
your system registration.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsh">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbsx">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galnp">How to Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing an Update Option: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="fwcch">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="galip">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Your registration options are saved in the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file
in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Choose from one
of the following installation methods to use the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicx">How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris JumpStart Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbidu">How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris Flash Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicy">How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris WAN Boot Installation Method</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbidv">How to Auto Register by Using a Diskless Client</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbicx">

<title>How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris JumpStart
Software</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>Solaris JumpStart software is a CLI that enables you to automatically
install or upgrade several systems, based on profiles that you create. The
profiles define specific software installation requirements. You can also
incorporate shell scripts to include pre-installation and postinstallation tasks. You
choose which profile and scripts to use for installation or upgrade.  To automate your Solaris software installation or update, specify
your configuration information in the <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file. For detailed
instructions on  using Solaris JumpStart software to install your Solaris OS, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2396">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation
Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Register a Solaris system to create an automatic registration
profile.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbiem">How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</olink> for the steps to create a profile.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Determine your system groups and prepare your Solaris JumpStart
software profile and scripts, as described in the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2396">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation
Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Copy the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file
from the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system
you registered and save it in your JumpStart directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the steps to prepare for and execute a JumpStart installation,
as described in the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2396">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris
Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbidu">

<title>How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris Flash Software</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>The Solaris Flash software enables you to create a single reference
installation of the Solaris OS on a system, which is called the <emphasis>master
system</emphasis>. You can replicate the master system installation on a number
of systems, which are called clone systems. See the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2397">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation
Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle>
</olink>   for detailed instructions on using a Solaris Flash
archive.</para>
<note>

<para>You cannot use the Solaris Flash software installation to upgrade a system
that is already running Solaris software. You can only use the Solaris Flash software to perform an
initial installation.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Prepare the systems at your site from which and on which you intend
to install the Solaris software.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Register the master system to create an automatic registration
profile.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbiem">How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</olink> for the steps to create a profile.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create a Solaris Flash archive that contains the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.</para>
<para>See the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2397">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris
Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle>
</olink>  for detailed instructions on creating a Solaris
Flash archive.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Install the Solaris Flash archive on clone systems. </para>
<para>When you install the Solaris Flash
archive on a system, all of the files in the archive are copied to that system.
The newly installed system (clone system) has the same installation configuration
as the original master system.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbicy">

<title>How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris WAN Boot
Installation Method</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>The WAN boot installation method enables you to boot and install software
over a wide area network (WAN) by using HTTP. By using WAN boot, you can install
the Solaris OS on SPARC based systems that are located in geographically remote
areas or over a large public network where the network infrastructure might
be untrustworthy. You might want to use WAN boot to install remote servers
or clients that are accessible only over a public network.  If you want to
install systems that are located on your local area network (LAN), the WAN
boot installation method might require more configuration and administration
than necessary.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Register a Solaris system to create a registration profile.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbiem">How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</olink> for
the steps to create a profile.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create an installation server, create a boot server (if necessary),
and set up the systems to be installed from the network.</para>
<para>See the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2394">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation
Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle>
</olink> to get detailed instructions
about performing a secure WAN boot installation.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create a Solaris Flash archive that contains the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.</para>
<para>See the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2397">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris
Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle>
</olink> to
get detailed instructions about creating a Solaris Flash archive.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Install the Solaris Flash archive on clone systems. When you install
the Solaris Flash archive on a system, all of the files in the archive are
copied to that system. The newly installed system (clone system) has the same
installation configuration as the original master system.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbidv">

<title>How to Auto Register by Using a Diskless Client</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>For information about preparing for managing diskless clients and the
procedures to add diskless clients, go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="clientsetup-1">Chapter 7, Managing Diskless Clients (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Register a Solaris system to create a registration profile.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbiem">How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</olink> for
the steps to create a profile.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Change to the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system that you just registered
and copy the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Add your diskless client.</para>
<para>Go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="fxcpp">How to Add a Diskless Client in the Solaris 10 OS</olink> or <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-7.xml" targetptr="clientsetup-4">
How to Add a Diskless Client in the GRUB Based Boot Environment</olink> for the steps to add a diskless client.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create a <filename>/export/root/<replaceable>client-name</replaceable>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system that you want to register, and save the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in that directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Reboot the system to be registered, and log in as superuser.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gawin">
<title>Registering Your Solaris Software Later</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-327">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>later</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>If you choose to register later, the registration wizard appears the
next time you log in to your system as superuser.</para>
<para>In the Solaris Express 3/06 release, if you choose to register later,
a registration icon is displayed on your desktop.</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbbvj">

<title>How to Use the Registration GUI to Register Later</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>The Solaris Registration Wizard
appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the Register Later option.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If
you are running at least the Solaris Express
3/06 release, click Next and then click Register Later. If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running at least the Solaris Express
3/06 release, click Submit.</para>
<para>The Solaris Registration Wizard closes. To register
later, follow the steps in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxkr" type="auto-generated">Registering Your Solaris Software With the Registration Wizard</olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gbgit">
<title>Registering Your Solaris Software With the
CLI (Task Map)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-328">
<primary>Solaris software, registration CLI (Task Map)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-329">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The following task map identifies the procedures that you might need
to perform to register your Solaris system by using the CLI.</para>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="110.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="167.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="119.00*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Obtain a Sun Online Account.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Registered assets are associated with a Sun Online Account. A Sun Online
Account is required to register your Solaris system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gcfkc">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 3/06</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxxs">How to Create a Sun Online Account: Solaris Express 10/05</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Purchase a subscription key or service plan number.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Use a subscription key or service plan number to register for additional
Solaris updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcom">How to Purchase a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If you register your Solaris software with the CLI, you must first create
a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbts">How to Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Run the CLI registration command using the subcommand options.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Describes the subcommand options that are available with the CLI registration
command.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="regsub">Solaris Software CLI Registration Subcommand Options</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software by using the CLI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software by using the registration CLI instead
of the registration GUI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwr" type="auto-generated">How to Register Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Change the user name and password associated with your Solaris software
registration.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>To change the user that is registered with the software, reregister
your software.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxzd">How to Reregister Your Solaris Software With a Different User</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Add a subscription key or service plan number to your Solaris software
registration.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If you did not add a subscription key or service plan number when you
first registered, or if you have a new subscription key or service plan number,
you can reregister your system to update your system's entitlement level.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwy" type="auto-generated">How to Reregister Your Solaris Software and Add a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Add Update Connection services to your Solaris software registration.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If your system obtains update data from the Sun update server, register
your system with Update Manager.</para>
<para>To manage updates manually, download updates from the Sun update server.
You must manually apply and remove the updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxzc">How to Reregister Your Solaris Software to Enable Access to All of the Update Connection Services</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software in fail-safe mode.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If your registration did not collect all system information, use this
option to register the software.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwz">How to Register Your Solaris Software in Fail-Safe Mode</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gatmi">
<title>Registering Your Solaris
Software With the CLI</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-330">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>using the CLI</secondary>
</indexterm>
<itemizedlist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-331">
<primary>
<filename>registrationprofile.properties</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm>To register by using the CLI, you need to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbts" type="custom-text">create a registration profile</olink>. Use the profile to
register your systems. Information about using the CLI is also available in
the following Solaris man pages:</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="sconadm-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>sconadm</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2251" targetptr="registration-profile-4">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>registration_profile</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
4
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2252" targetptr="attributes-5">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>attributes</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
5
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2252" targetptr="privileges-5">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>privileges</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
5
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbbts">

<title>How to Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Go to the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Copy the  <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file and save
it in your <filename>/tmp</filename> directory.</para>
<para>
<filename>/tmp/RegistrationProfile</filename>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Open the <filename>/tmp/RegistrationProfile</filename> file in
a text editor.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> properties,
as needed, to meet your requirements.</para>
<para>The following properties
are in the <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>userName</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Online Account user name. Systems registered with this
profile are identified with this Sun Online Account.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>password</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Online Account password.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>hostName</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Portal host name (Portal Common Name).</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>subscriptionKey</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>(Optional) Sun support contract ID. A valid subscription key
or service plan number is required to enable access to all Sun Update Connection services.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>portalEnabled</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Determines if the local client is managed using the Sun hosted
Update Connection service. <computeroutput>True</computeroutput> enables the Sun Update Connection
service. <computeroutput>False</computeroutput> disables the Sun Update Connection.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>proxyHostName</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>(Optional) Proxy host name,  if your system is connected to
a network proxy.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>proxyPort</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>(Optional) Proxy port number of the network proxy, if your
system connects to the Internet through a network proxy.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>proxyUserName</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>(Optional) Network proxy user name.  Network proxy user name.
The user name is only needed if your network proxy requires authentication.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<property>proxyPassword</property>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>(Optional) Network proxy password. The proxy password is only
needed if your network proxy requires authentication.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<note>

<para>If your network proxy requires authentication, store the network
proxy password in a <filename>registrationprofile.properties</filename> file.
By storing the password in a file, you prevent the proxy password from becoming
exposed as part of a process listing by other system users.</para>
</note>
</step>
<step>
<para>Save your changes.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="gbbtf">

<title>
<filename>RegistrationProfile.properties</filename> File</title>
<para>The following is an example of a completed <filename>RegistrationProfile.properties</filename> file:</para>
<informaltable> <tgroup Remap="SimpleList" cols="1">
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>userName=</property>
<literal>soa-username1</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>password=</property>
<literal>SOA-password1</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>hostName=</property>
<literal>evita</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>subscriptionKey=</property>
<literal>abc12345678</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>portalEnabled=</property>
<literal>false</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>proxyHostName=</property>
<literal>webcache.mycompany.com</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>proxyPort=</property>
<literal>8080</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>proxyUserName=</property>
<literal>user123</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<property>proxyPassword=</property>
<literal>abc123</literal>
</para>
</entry> </row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="regsub">
<title>Solaris Software CLI Registration Subcommand Options</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-332">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>CLI subcommand options</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The Solaris software CLI registration uses the following command-line options:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
a</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Accepts the Terms of Use and the Binary Code License. If you
do not use the <option>
a</option> option, you do not accept the Terms of Use
and the Binary Code License
and the registration fails.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
e</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Enables software updates with the Sun Update Connection services.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
E</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Disables software updates with the Update Connection services.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
h</option> <replaceable>portal-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the portal host name (Portal Common Name) of the
system to be registered. If a name is not provided, the default is the UNIX
host name.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
l</option> <replaceable>logfile</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the location of the log file.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
N</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Removes the registration options from your system.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option> <replaceable>proxy-host:[proxy port]</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the proxy host name and optional proxy port number
of your network proxy, if your system connects to the Internet thorough a
network proxy.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
r</option> <replaceable>registration-profile</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the full path, or relative path, to the registration
profile.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
s</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Operates the registration in fail-safe mode. For normal operation,
do not use the <option>
s</option> option. If you are running at least the Express 3/06 software, the fail-safe mode is not
available.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
u</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the Sun Online Account user name.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
x</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies your network proxy user name. The user name is only
needed if you use a network proxy, and the proxy requires authentication.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The <option>
u</option>, <option>
h</option>, <option>
e</option>, <option>
E</option>, <option>
p</option>, <option>
x</option> options override the values that are specified
in the registration profile.  If a property is not specified in the profile
or on the command line, it is not used.</para>
<note>

<para>To successfully register your Solaris software with the CLI, you
must always use the <option>
a</option> option to accept the Terms of Use and
the Binary Code License.</para>
</note>
<example>

<title>CLI Command to Register Your Solaris Software Using Your Default
Options</title>
<para>To register a system using the properties defined in your <filename>/tmp/registrationprofile.properties</filename> file, type the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r /tmp/registrationprofile.properties</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example>

<title>CLI Command to Register Your Solaris Software Using a Registration
Subcommand Option to Override a Default Option</title>
<para>To register your Solaris software with a username that is not defined
in your <filename>/tmp/registrationprofile.properties</filename> file, type
the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r  /tmp
/registrationprofile.properties -u <replaceable>username</replaceable>
</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="gbbtl">

<title>CLI Command to Register Your Solaris Software Using
a Network Proxy Subcommand Option to Override a Default Option</title>
<para>If you define the <property>proxyHostName</property> property in the
registration profile as <literal>webcache.mycompany.com</literal>,  run the
following command to change the <property>proxyHostName</property> to <literal>newcache.mycompany.com:</literal>
</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm proxy -a -r /tmp
/registrationprofile.properties -p newcache.mycompany.com</userinput>
</screen>
<para>All proxy settings will use the <option>
p</option> value of <literal>newcache.mycompany.com</literal>.</para>
</example>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gaxwr">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software With the CLI</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-333">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>using the CLI</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbts" type="custom-text">Create a <filename>registrationprofile.properties</filename> file</olink> in the  <filename>/tmp</filename> directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Run the following command to register your Solaris software:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r /tmp/registrationprofile.properties</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gaxzd">

<title>How to Reregister Your Solaris Software With a Different
User</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-334">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>reregistering to change the user</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>The software registration
is associated with the Sun Online Account used during registration. You
can create a new registration profile with a new user and reregister the Solaris software to associate it with a new Sun
Online Account. You might want to reregister if a user has
moved to a different department or left the company.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbts" type="custom-text">Create a new registration
profile</olink> in the <filename>/tmp</filename> directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To reregister your Solaris software, run the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r /tmp/registrationprofile.properties</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gaxwy">

<title>How to Reregister Your Solaris Software and Add a
Subscription Key or Service Plan Number</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-335">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>adding a subscription key (CLI)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>You can add a subscription key (also called a <emphasis>service plan
number</emphasis>) to an existing registration profile.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Open the <filename>/tmp/registrationprofile.properties</filename> file
in a text editor. </para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type your subscription key or service plan number in the subscriptionKey
property and save your changes.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type the following command to register your Solaris software with
the subscription key or service plan number:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r /tmp/registrationprofile.properties</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gaxzc">

<title>How to Reregister Your Solaris Software to Enable
Access to All of the Update Connection Services</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-336">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>editing the <filename>registrationprofile.properties</filename> file</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Open the <filename>/tmp/registrationprofile.properties</filename> file.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Change the <property>portalEnabled</property> property to true.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Run the following command to access all Update Connection services:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r /tmp
/registrationprofile.properties -e softwareUpdate</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gaxwz">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software in Fail-Safe
Mode</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-337">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>using fail-safe mode (CLI)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>If the software registration did not collect all system information,
use this option to register the software in fail-safe mode.</para>
<note>

<para>Fail-safe mode is not available after the Solaris Express 10/05 release.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create a <filename>registrationprofile.properties</filename> file
in the  <filename>/tmp</filename> directory.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Run the following command in fail-safe mode:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -a -r /tmp/registrationprofile.properties -s</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gbgig">
<title>Disabling the Solaris Registration (Task Map)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-338">
<primary>Solaris software, disabling the registration Wizard</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The following task map identifies the procedures to disable the Basic
Registration tool.</para>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="110.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="167.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="119.00*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Disable Basic Registration from the GUI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Select the Never Register option to disable the registration wizard.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbcop" type="auto-generated">How to Disable Solaris Registration From the GUI</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Disable Basic Registration from the CLI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Run the CLI registration command with the Never Register option.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbwj">How to Disable Solaris Registration From the CLI</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gateq">
<title>Disabling the Solaris Registration </title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-339">
<primary>registering your system</primary>
<secondary>never</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Once you register your system, the registration wizard does not appear. If
you choose to disable the Solaris Registration Wizard
by selecting never register, the registration wizard will not appear. You
can still register your software
with the Sun Update Manager application. For more
information, see the Sun Update Connection documentation on docs.sun.com..</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbcop">

<title>How to Disable Solaris Registration From the GUI</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system to launch the registration wizard.</para>
<para>The Solaris Registration Wizard appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the Never Register option.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Submit.</para>
<para>The Solaris Registration Wizard closes.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gbbwj">

<title>How to Disable Solaris Registration From the CLI</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Launch a terminal window.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/sconadm register -N</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
