<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="gdkma">



<title>Registering Your Solaris Software (Tasks)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter describes how to register systems that are running at least
the Solaris Express 8/06 software. If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running
at least the Solaris Express 8/06 software, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="tasks-basics-2">Chapter 18, Registering Your Solaris Express 3/06 or 10/05 Software (Tasks)</olink> for instructions.</para>
<para>The following information is discussed in this chapter:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdklx">Solaris Software Registration (Overview)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdktb">What Is Sun Update Connection?</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfj">Solaris Software Registration (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkvt">Before You Get Started</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfy">Register Your Software With the Solaris Registration Wizard</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For a complete listing of new Solaris software features and a description
of Solaris releases, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2183">
<citetitle remap="book">What’s New in Solaris
Express</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="gdklx">
<title>Solaris Software Registration (Overview)</title>
<para>When you register your Solaris software and accept the Software License
Agreement, you have access to Solaris software updates. If you provide a Sun
service plan number during registration, you can use Sun Update Connection
client services to remotely manage updates for one or more of your Solaris
systems.</para>
<para>The following methods of registration are available:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration Wizard. The wizard is initiated upon
system reboot. For information, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfy">Register Your Software With the Solaris Registration Wizard</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris autoregistration profile. When you register a system,
you can create a profile that can be used to register your other systems.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris Registration command-line interface (CLI). For more
information, go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbgit">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Registration wizard in the Sun Update Manager application.
For information, view the Sun Update Connection documentation located on docs.sun.com.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>When you register your system, you choose how the updates are delivered
and how they are applied. The following options are available:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Receive updates from Sun Update Connection client services.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Receive updates from a local source, such as a local proxy
server.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Manage updates remotely by using the Sun Update Connection
application.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Manage updates manually by using the <command>smpatch add</command> and
the <command>smpatch remove</command> commands.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note arch="x86">

<para>If the keyboard's Num Lock is on, the Tab and Backspace
keys on the keyboard might not work. To activate the Tab and Backspace keys,
turn off Num Lock.</para>
</note>
<para>The Solaris Registration Wizard gives you the option of registering
later, or never registering. If you select Register Later, a registration
icon is displayed on your desktop. If you select Never Register, you can still
register your system from the CLI or from the Sun Update Manager application.
You can also use the CLI or Sun Update Manager to make changes to an existing
registration. For more information, go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> or the <citetitle>Sun Update Manager
Administration Guide</citetitle> located on docs.sun.com.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gdktb">
<title>What Is Sun Update Connection?</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-302">
<primary>Sun Update Connection services</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-303">
<primary>updates</primary>
<secondary>applying with Sun Update Connection</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Sun Update Connection services are designed to compare an individual
system configuration and status to a database of configuration data and business
rules. When you register your Solaris system, you can also register with Sun
Update Connection services by supplying a service plan number. The following
tools are available with Sun Update Connection services:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Update Manager – A graphical user interface and
a fully-scriptable <command>smpatch</command> command-line interface that
assesses your system status and recommends system-specific updates. You are
notified when new updates are available for your system. You can use Sun Update
Manager to view a list of applied updates, to apply new updates to your system,
and to remove updates from your system. Sun Update Manager enables you to
manage updates on your system, including identifying update dependencies and
determining installation order for each system.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Update Connection-Hosted – A web application hosted
at Sun that enables you to remotely manage updates on up to 10 systems through
a standard web browser. You can view and install updates for systems that
are registered with Sun Update Manager.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Update Connection Proxy – A system located within your intranet
that provides updates to eligible systems. The Sun Update Connection Proxy
is similar to a local update server, but updates are sent over the Internet
from Sun to the Sun Update Connection Proxy. The Sun Update Connection Proxy transfers
the updates to the systems that are inside your enterprise security domain.
The Sun Update Connection Proxy system must be connected to the Internet or to another
Proxy which can access the Internet.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Sun Update Connection is available with the following service subscriptions:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Solaris 10 OS service plan</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<trademark class="service">SunSpectrum</trademark> service
plan</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Sun Preventive Services</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about Sun Update Connection and how to use the
Sun Update Connection Proxy, go to the Sun Update Connection documentation
on docs.sun.com.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gdkfj">
<title>Solaris Software Registration (Task Map)</title>
<para>The following task map identifies the procedures that you might need
to perform to register your Solaris system.</para>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="110.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="167.00*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="119.00*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Obtain a Sun Online Account.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Registered systems are associated with a Sun Online Account. A Sun Online
Account is required to register your Solaris system.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkwe">How to Create a Sun Online Account in the Solaris Registration Wizard</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Purchase Sun service plan.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Use a service plan number to register for additional Solaris updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkvm">How to Purchase a Sun Service Plan</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system with Sun Update Manager to automatically manage
your updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Register your system with Sun Update Manager if your system obtains
update data from the Sun update server or if you want to remotely manage updates.</para>
<para>When you register, you have the following options:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Specify a local source for updates for your system. To obtain
updates either from a Sun Update Connection Proxy or from a collection of
updates on a local system, specify a local source. By default, your system
obtains updates from Sun. If your system is not connected to the Internet,
you must provide a local update source. You can use a network proxy to connect
to the Internet.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Specify the network proxy to use. If your system is connected
to the Internet through a network proxy, specify the network proxy information.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfb">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system with Sun Update Manager to manually manage your
updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If your system obtains update data from the Sun update server, register
your system with Sun Update Manager. </para>
<para>To manage updates manually, download updates from the Sun update server.
You must manually apply and remove the updates.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgy">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system without choosing an update option.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>You can register your Solaris software without selecting an update option
at registration. After you have successfully registered your Solaris software,
you can use the CLI or the Sun Update Manager application to add an update
option.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgu">How to Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing an Update Option</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your system as part of a noninteractive Solaris software installation.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>You can register a system and create a registration profile. The profile enables you to use Solaris <trademark>JumpStart</trademark> software, Solaris Flash software, WAN boot, or a diskless client
to register your other systems.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicx">How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris JumpStart Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbidu">How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris Flash Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicy">How to Autoregister by Using the Solaris WAN Boot Installation Method</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbidv">How to Auto Register by Using a Diskless Client</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create an automatic registration profile and ID.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>To autoregister, you need a registration profile and registration ID.
The profile and ID are automatically generated when you register a system
and select Enable Auto Registration. </para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbiem">How to Create an Autoregistration Profile</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> file.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>If you want to register your Solaris software with the CLI, you must
first create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File. This file is
not the same file that is used for the automatic registration profile.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbbts">How to Create a <filename>RegistrationProfile</filename> File</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software by using the CLI.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Register your Solaris software by running the registration command from
a terminal window.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwr">How to Register Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gdkvt">
<title>Before You Get Started</title>
<para>System registration requires superuser access to your system. Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbactask-15">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>. </para>
<para>To register your system with the Solaris Registration Wizard, the system
to be registered must be a desktop system with a monitor, keyboard, and graphics
card. If the system to be registered is not a desktop system, you can use
the CLI or autoregistration to register the system.</para>
<note>

<para>You can register a system and use that system registration as
a template to register your other systems. When you select Enable Auto Registration
during registration, your registration options are saved in the <filename>autoRegistrationProfile.xml</filename> file in the <filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory.
To use the file to register other systems, place the file in the<filename>/usr/lib/breg/data/</filename> directory on the system, reboot the system, and log in as superuser.
For more information about autoregistration, go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink>.</para>
</note>
<para>If your system has an Internet connection, basic system information
is sent to Sun, including the packages and updates installed on your system.
The system information is used to determine recommended updates. You can view
the information that is collected before you complete the registration. Information
is not sent to Sun until you complete the registration. If your system does
not have an Internet connection, you can receive updates by specifying a network
proxy or local source.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="gdkvf">
<title>Sun Online Account</title>
<para>To register a system, you must have a Sun Online Account. If you do
not have a Sun Online Account, you can create an account during the registration
process. A <emphasis>Sun Online Account</emphasis> is a global Sun account
that enables you to access many Sun web applications and portals. You can
move between sites and portals in a single browser session without having
to log in multiple times.</para>
<note>

<para>If you can access Sun online services, such as the SunSolve web
site or the Sun Online Support Center, you already have a Sun Online Account.
You do not need to create a new account.</para>
</note>
<para>When you register your Solaris software, the software is associated
with the Sun Online Account in Sun Update Connection services. To change the
Sun Online Account associated with the Solaris software, reregister the software
as described in <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxzd">How to Reregister Your Solaris Software With a Different User</olink>.</para>
<para>To create a Sun Online Account, your system must be connected to the
Internet. The information that you specify is saved locally and sent to Sun.
Use English characters for the information you supply.</para>
<para>You can create a Sun Online Account from most Sun applications and web
sites, including the Sun Update Manager application and the Sun Update Connection
web application, or you can create a Sun Online Account from the Solaris Registration
Wizard.</para>
<task xml:id="gdkwe">
<title>How to Create a Sun Online Account in the Solaris
Registration Wizard</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your Solaris system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>The
Registration screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Create a Sun Online Account.</para>
<para>The Create Sun
Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the required fields.</para>
<para>A Sun Online Account
user name must contain at least six valid characters: a-z, 0-9, @, - (dash),
_ (underscore), . (period).  The username is not case sensitive. The password
must contain at least six standard ASCII characters and is case sensitive.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Next. The data is validated to confirm the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The user name is not already assigned.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The required fields are completed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The entered data matches field validation logic.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the fields and select your Country/Territory. Click Terms
and Conditions to read the  Sun Terms of Use. If the terms are acceptable,
Click Next to agree to the Terms and Conditions and complete the creation
of your Sun Online Account.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="gdkuy">
<title>Sun Service Plan</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-305">
<primary>service plan</primary>
<secondary>definition</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>A Sun service plan number is associated with your Sun support contract
and enables you to access additional services. If you specify a valid service
plan number when you register your system, you can use the Sun Update Manager
to help manage your updates. If you do not specify a service plan number during
registration, you can reregister your software and add a service plan number
at any time. For information on reregistering, go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gaxwy">How to Reregister Your Solaris Software and Add a Subscription Key or Service Plan Number</olink>.</para>
<note>

<para>If you have a Sun support contract that includes software support,
your service plan number might be known as your, subscription key, contract
ID, support agreement number, or entitlement token.</para>
</note>
<task xml:id="gdkvm">
<title>How to Purchase a Sun Service Plan</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>To purchase a plan, go to General Solaris OS Support Plans at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/service/support/software/solaris/">http://www.sun.com/service/support/software/solaris/</link>.</para>
<para>If you have questions on available plans, contact your
Sun representative.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Follow the directions on the web site.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gdkfy">
<title>Register Your Software With the Solaris Registration
Wizard</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-307">
<primary>Solaris software, registration wizard (Task Map)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-308">
<primary>Registration wizard</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>Registering your system enables you to use Sun Update Manager, which
is designed to recommend updates that are based on your specific system information.
When you register your system, you choose how the updates are delivered and
how they are applied. You can manage the updates automatically or manually.
After you determine how the updates are managed, you can use the Sun Update Connection application
or the Sun Update Connection Proxy to deliver updates.</para>
<para>The following registration options are covered in this section:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfb">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgy">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually Manage Updates</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgu">How to Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing an Update Option</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For instructions on registering your system without using the Solaris
Registration Wizard, go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gatmi">Registering Your Solaris Software With the CLI</olink> or <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink>.</para>
<para>Each registered system is linked to a Sun Online Account. During system
registration, system specifications are gathered. This information is analyzed
at Sun, enabling Sun to send you an appropriate list of available updates.</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gdkfb">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically
Manage Updates</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>You can configure Sun Update Manager to automatically manage updates
on your system.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>The
Solaris Registration Wizard appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration, then click Next.</para>
<para>The
Sun Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Determine how your system will receive updates.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To specify a network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfr">Step 5</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To specify a local source, or if your system has a direct Internet
connection, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgn" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>
</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkfr">
<para>To specify the network proxy that your system uses
to connect to the Internet, click Configure Network Proxy Settings.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>At the Network Proxy Settings screen, select Enable Network Proxy.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Host Name field, type your proxy host name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Port field, type your proxy port number.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your proxy requires authentication,  select Use Proxy Authentication.
In the Proxy User Name field, type the proxy user name  and in the Proxy Password
field, type the proxy password .</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To set these network proxy values and close the dialog box, click
OK.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkgn">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password,
then click Next.</para>
<para>The Activation of Services screen appears.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password,
click Forgot Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve your
Sun Online Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkfi">
<para>Select Use Sun Update Manager and Sun Update Connection
to manage updates, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Select Service Level screen
appears</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkgr">
<para>Select Enter a Service Plan Number, and then provide
a valid service plan number. Read the Software License Agreement. If the terms
are acceptable, click the check box to accept the agreement, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Remote Software Updates Service screen appears.</para>
<note>

<para>Your service plan number might be your support contract number
or subscription key. For more information, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkuy">Sun Service Plan</olink>.</para>
</note>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkgi">
<para>Select Activate remote update management. In the System
Name field, type your host name.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To view the system information that will be sent to
Sun, click What Gets Sent.</para>
<para>To successfully complete the registration
process, basic system information is sent to Sun. The information to be sent
is provided on the System Data screen.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register
your other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink> or click Learn More or to get more information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, select Yes,
Sun may contact me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To complete your registration and send your system information
to Sun, click Finish.</para>
<para>The Registration Confirmation screen appears.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close</para>
<para>Your system is registered and the Sun
Update Manager application is launched.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gdkgy">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software to Manually
Manage Updates</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>You can manually manage the updates on your system.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>The
Solaris Registration Wizard appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration, then click Next.</para>
<para>The
Sun Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your system does not connect to the Internet, determine if
you want to use a local source or a network proxy for updates. If your system
is connected to the Internet or you do not want to specify a network proxy,
go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgl" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>.</para>
<para>To specify a network proxy, go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkfb">How to Register Your Solaris Software to Automatically Manage Updates</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkfp">
<para>To specify the network proxy your system uses to connect
to the Internet, click Configure Network Proxy Settings.</para>
<para>If your
system is directly connected to the Internet, you do not need to specify network
proxy information and you can go to <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-17.xml" targetptr="gdkgl" type="auto-generated">Step 6</olink>.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>At the Network Proxy Settings screen, click Enable Network Proxy.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Host Name field, type your proxy host name.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Proxy Port field, type your proxy port number.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If your proxy requires authentication, click Use Proxy Authentication.
In the Proxy User Name field, type the proxy user name and  in the Proxy Password
field, type the proxy password.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To set these network proxy values and close the dialog box, click
OK.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkgl">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password,
then click Next.</para>
<para>The Activation of Services screen appears.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password,
then click Forgot Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve
your Sun Online Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkgo">
<para>Select Use Sun Update Manager using a local update
source, such as Sun Connection Proxy, then click Next.</para>
<para>The Apply
Updates Using a Local Source screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>In the Local Source URL, type the URL for your local server, then
click Next.</para>
<para>The System Registration screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To successfully complete the registration process, basic system
information is sent to Sun. The information to be sent is displayed on the
screen. To complete your system registration and send your system information
to Sun, click Finish.</para>
<para>The Registration Confirmation screen appears.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register
your other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<para>See <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink> or click Learn More or for more information.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, click Yes, Sun
may contact me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close.</para>
<para>Your system is registered.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="gdkgu">

<title>How to Register Your Solaris Software Without Choosing
an Update Option</title>
<tasksummary>
<para>You can register your Solaris software without choosing an update option.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Reboot your system. </para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
<para>The
Solaris Registration Wizard appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Continue with Registration, then click Next.</para>
<para>The
Sun Online Account screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkgg">
<para>Type your Sun Online Account user name and password.
Click Next.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>If you have a Sun Online Account, but cannot remember the password,
click Forgot Your User Name or Password.</para>
<para>After you retrieve your
Sun Online Account information, restart the registration process.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>If you do not have a Sun Online Account, click Create a Sun Online
Account to register for an account.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
<para>The Activation of Services screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="gdkex">
<para>Click Register the Solaris software without configuring
the Sun Update Connection, then click Next.</para>
<para>The System Registration
screen appears. </para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To successfully complete the registration process, basic system
information is sent to Sun. To complete your system registration and send
your system information to Sun, click Close.</para>
<para>The Registration
Confirmation screen appears.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To use this system's registration as a profile to register
your other systems, click Enable Auto Registration.</para>
<para>To get more
information, click Learn More or go to <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-18.xml" targetptr="gbicw">Registering Your Solaris Software by Using an Automatic Registration Profile</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>(Optional) To receive other information from Sun, click Yes, Sun
may contact me with product and service information.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Click Close.</para>
<para>Your system is registered.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
