<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="softmgt-1">



<title>Software Management in Trusted Extensions</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1003">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>third-party software</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1004">
<primary>software</primary>
<secondary>administering third-party</secondary>
</indexterm>
<toc>
<para>This chapter contains information about ensuring that third-party software
runs in a trustworthy manner on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions.</para>
<itemizedlist remap="jumplist">
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-19.xml" targetptr="addsoft-12">Adding Software to Trusted Extensions</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-19.xml" targetptr="addsoft-17">Trusted Processes in the Window
System</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-19.xml" targetptr="addsoft-41">Managing Software (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="addsoft-12">
<title>Adding Software to Trusted Extensions</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1005">
<primary>importing</primary>
<secondary>software</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1006">
<primary>software</primary>
<secondary>importing</secondary>
</indexterm>Any software that can be added to a Solaris system can be
added to a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions. Additionally, programs
that use Trusted Extensions APIs can be added. Adding software to a Trusted Extensions system
is similar to adding software to a Solaris system that is running non-global
zones.</para>
<para>For example, packaging issues affect systems that have installed non-global
zones. Package parameters define the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The zone scope of the package. The scope determines the type
of zone in which an individual package can be installed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The visibility of the package. Visibility determines whether
a package is required to be installed on all zones, and be identical in all
zones.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The limitation of the package. One limitation is whether a
package must be installed in the current zone only.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>In Trusted Extensions, programs are typically installed in the global zone
for use by ordinary users in labeled zones. For details on installing packages
in zones, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="z.pkginst.ov-1">Chapter 24, <citetitle remap="chapter">About Packages and Patches on a Solaris System With Zones Installed (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink> and
the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="pkgadd-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>pkgadd</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<para>At a Trusted Extensions site, the system administrator and the security
administrator work together to install software. The security administrator
evaluates software additions for adherence to security policy. When the software
requires privileges or authorizations to succeed, the Security Administrator
role assigns an appropriate rights profile to the users of that software.</para>
<para>To import software from removable media requires authorization. An account
with the device allocation authorization can import or export data from removable
media. Data includes programs. An ordinary user can only import data at a
label within that user's clearance.</para>
<para>The System Administrator role is responsible for adding the programs
that the security administrator approves.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="addsoft-53">
<title>Solaris Security Mechanisms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1007">
<primary>security mechanisms</primary>
<secondary>Solaris</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Trusted Extensions uses the same security mechanisms as the Solaris OS. The
mechanisms include the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Authorizations –</emphasis> Users
of a program can be required to have a particular authorization. For information
on authorizations, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbac-29">
<citetitle remap="section">Solaris RBAC Elements and Basic Concepts</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.
Also, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2251" targetptr="auth-attr-4">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>auth_attr</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
4
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> and
the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2246" targetptr="getauthattr-3secdb">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>getauthattr</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
3SECDB
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man pages.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Privileges –</emphasis> Programs
and processes can be assigned privileges. For information on privileges, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="prbac-1">Chapter 7, <citetitle remap="chapter">Using Roles and Privileges (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>. Also, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2252" targetptr="privileges-5">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>privileges</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
5
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
<para>The <command>ppriv</command> command provides a debugging utility. For
details, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="ppriv-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>ppriv</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page. For using this utility with programs that work in non-global zones,
see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="z.admin.task-2">
<citetitle remap="section">Using the ppriv Utility</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Right Profiles –</emphasis> Rights
profiles collect security attributes in one place for assignment to users
or roles. For information on rights profiles, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="rbac-33">
<citetitle remap="section">RBAC Rights Profiles</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>. Trusted Extensions adds
CDE actions to the type of executables that can be given security attributes.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Trusted libraries –</emphasis> Dynamically-shared
libraries that are used by setuid, setgid, and privileged programs can be
loaded only from trusted directories. As in the Solaris OS, the <command>crle</command> command
is used to add a privileged program's shared library directories to the list
of trusted directories. For details, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="crle-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>crle</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="addsoft-45">
<title>Evaluating Software for Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1008">
<primary>trusted programs</primary>
<secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1009">
<primary>applications</primary>
<secondary>trusted and trustworthy</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1010">
<primary>trustworthy programs</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1011">
<primary>evaluating programs for security</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>When software has been assigned privileges or when the software runs
with an alternate UID or GID, the software becomes <emphasis>trusted</emphasis>.
Trusted software can bypass aspects of the Trusted Extensions security policy.
Be aware that you can make software trusted even though it might not be worthy
of trust. The Security Administrator role should not give any privileges to
software until careful scrutiny has revealed that the software uses the privileges
in a trustworthy manner. </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Programs that require no security
attributes –</emphasis> Some programs run at a single level and require
no privileges. These programs can be installed in a public directory, such
as <filename>/usr/local</filename>. For access, assign the programs as commands
in the rights profiles of users and roles.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1012">
<primary>real UID of root</primary>
<secondary>required for applications</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1013">
<primary>root UID</primary>
<secondary>required for applications</secondary>
</indexterm>
<emphasis role="strong">Programs that run as root –</emphasis> Some
programs execute with <command>setuid 0</command>. Such programs can be assigned
an effective UID of root in a rights profile. The Security Administrator role
then assigns the profile to an administrative role.</para>
<para>If the application
can use privileges in a trustworthy manner, assign the needed privileges to
the application, and do not execute the program as root.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1014">
<primary>
<filename class="devicefile">/dev/kmem</filename> kernel image file</primary>
<secondary>security violation</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1015">
<primary>privileges</primary>
<secondary>non-obvious reasons for requiring</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1016">
<primary>
<filename class="devicefile">kmem</filename> kernel image file</primary>
</indexterm>
<emphasis role="strong">Programs that require privileges –</emphasis> Some
programs might need privileges for reasons that are not obvious. Even if a
program is not performing any function that seems to violate system security
policy, the program might be doing something internally that violates security.
For example, the program could be using a shared log file, or the program
could be reading from <filename>/dev/kmem</filename>. For security concerns,
see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2254" targetptr="mem-7d">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>mem</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
7D
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<para>Sometimes an internal policy override is not particularly
important to the application's correct operation. Rather, the override provides
a convenient feature for users. If your organization has access to the source
code, check if you can remove the operations that require policy overrides
without affecting the performance of the application.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect3 xml:id="addsoft-59">
<title>Developer Responsibilities When Creating
Trusted Programs</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1017">
<primary>trusted programs</primary>
<secondary>adding</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Even though a program's developer can manipulate privilege sets in the
program's source code, if the Security Administrator role does not assign
the required privileges, the program will fail. The developer and security
administrator cooperate when creating trusted programs.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1018">
<primary>developers responsibilities</primary>
</indexterm>A developer who writes a trusted program must do the following:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Understand where the program requires privileges to do its
work.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Know and follow techniques, such as privilege bracketing,
for safely using privileges in programs.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Be aware of the security implications when assigning privileges
to a program. Make sure that the program does not violate security policy.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Compile the program by using shared libraries that are linked
to the program from a trusted directory.</para>
<para>For additional information,
see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2145">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris Security for Developers Guide</citetitle>
</olink>. For examples of code for Trusted Extensions,
see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7312">
<citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Developer’s Guide</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 xml:id="addsoft-23">
<title>Security Administrator Responsibilities for
Trusted Programs</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1019">
<primary>applications</primary>
<secondary>evaluating for security</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1020">
<primary>commercial applications</primary>
<secondary>evaluating</secondary>
</indexterm>The security administrator is responsible for testing and evaluating
new software. After determining that the software is trustworthy, the Security
Administrator role configures rights profiles and other security-relevant
attributes for the program.</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Make sure the programmer and the program distribution process
is trusted.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>From one of these sources, find out which privileges are required
by the program:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Ask the programmer.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Search the source code for any privileges that the program
expects to use.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Search the source code for any authorizations that the program
requires of its users.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Use the debugging options to the <command>ppriv</command> command
to search for use of privilege. For examples, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="ppriv-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>ppriv</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Examine the source code to make sure that the code behaves
in a trustworthy manner when using the privileges that the program needs to
operate.</para>
<para>If the program fails to use privilege in a trustworthy
manner, and you can modify the program's source code, then modify the code.
A security consultant or programmer who is knowledgeable about security can
modify the code. Modifications might include privilege bracketing or checking
for authorizations.</para>
<para>The assignment of privileges should not be
automatic. A program that fails due to lack of privilege can be assigned privileges.
Alternatively, the Security Administrator role might decide to assign an effective
UID or GID to make the privilege unnecessary.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="addsoft-17">
<title>Trusted Processes in the Window System</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1021">
<primary>trusted processes</primary>
<secondary>in the window system</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1022">
<primary>window system</primary>
<secondary>trusted processes</secondary>
</indexterm>
<itemizedlist>
<para>In Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE), the following window system processes are trusted:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Front Panel</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Subpanels of the Front Panel</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Workspace Menu</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>File Manager</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Application Manager</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1023">
<primary>administrative actions</primary>
<secondary>trusted</secondary>
</indexterm>The window system's trusted processes are available to everyone,
but access to administrative actions is restricted to roles in the global
zone.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1024">
<primary>icon visibility</primary>
<secondary>in the Workspace Menu</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1025">
<primary>icon visibility</primary>
<secondary>in the File Manager</secondary>
</indexterm>In the File Manager, if an action is not in one of the account's
profiles, the icon for the action is not visible. In the Workspace Menu, if
an action is not in one of the account's profiles, the action is visible,
but an error displays if the action is invoked.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1026">
<primary>window manager</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1027">
<primary>
<filename>Xtsolusersession</filename> script</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1028">
<primary>
<command>dtwm</command> command</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1029">
<primary>rights profiles</primary>
<secondary>controlling the use of actions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1030">
<primary>actions</primary>
<secondary>restricted by rights profiles</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1031">
<primary>restricting</primary>
<secondary>actions by rights profiles</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1032">
<primary>trusted processes</primary>
<secondary>launching actions</secondary>
</indexterm>In CDE, the window manager, <command>dtwm</command>, calls the <command>Xtsolusersession</command> script. This script works with the window manager
to invoke actions that are launched from the window system. The <command>Xtsolusersession</command> script consults the account's rights profiles when the account
attempts to launch an action. In either case, if the action is in an assigned
rights profile, the action is run with the security attributes that are specified
in the profile.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="addsoft-47">
<title>Adding Trusted CDE Actions</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1033">
<primary>actions</primary>
<secondary>adding new Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) actions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The process of creating and using CDE actions is similar in Trusted Extensions to
the process in the Solaris OS. Adding actions is described in the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="806-7492" targetptr="configappmanager-18247">Chapter 4, <citetitle remap="chapter">Adding and Administering  Applications,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Common Desktop Environment: Advanced User’s and System Administrator’s Guide</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>As in the Solaris OS, the use of actions can be controlled by the rights
profile mechanism. In Trusted Extensions, a number of actions have been assigned
security attributes in the rights profiles of administrative roles. The Security
Administrator role can also use the Rights tool to assign security attributes
to new actions.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1034">
<primary>actions</primary>
<secondary>use differences between CDE and Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE)</secondary>
</indexterm>The following table summarizes the main differences that are encountered
in creating and using actions in the Solaris Trusted Extensions system.</para>
<table frame="topbot" xml:id="addsoft-24" pgwide="1">

<title>Constraints on CDE
Actions in Solaris Trusted Extensions</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colnum="1" colwidth="3.93*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colnum="2" colwidth="9.07*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="column1" rowsep="1">
<para>Solaris CDE Actions</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="column2" rowsep="1">
<para>Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) Actions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="left" colname="column1" morerows="1" valign="top">
<para>New actions can be created by anyone within the originator's home directory.</para>
<para>A new action is automatically usable by its creator.</para>
</entry>
<entry align="left" colname="column2" valign="top">
<para>An action is usable only if the action is a rights profile that is assigned
to the user. The search path for actions has been changed. Actions in any
individual's home directory are processed last instead of first. Therefore,
no one can customize existing actions.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" colname="column2" valign="top">
<para>Users can create a new action in their home directory, but the action
might not be usable.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" colname="column1" valign="top">
</entry>
<entry align="left" colname="column2" valign="top">
<para>Users with the All profile can use an action that they create. Otherwise,
the Security Administrator role must add the name of the new action to one
of the account's rights profiles.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="1" valign="top">
</entry>
<entry align="left" colname="column2" rowsep="1" valign="top">
<para>To launch the action, the user uses the File Manager. The System Administrator
role can place actions in public directories.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="column1" rowsep="1">
<para>Actions can be dragged and dropped to the Front Panel.</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="column2" rowsep="1">
<para>The Front Panel is part of the trusted path. The window manager recognizes
only the administratively-added actions that are located in the <filename>/usr/dt</filename> and <filename>/etc/dt</filename> subdirectories. Even with the
All profile, a user cannot drag a new action to the Front Panel. Action from
a user's home directory are not recognized by the window manager. The manager
only looks in the public directories.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="1" valign="top">
<para>Actions can do privileged operations if they are run by root.</para>
</entry>
<entry align="left" colname="column2" rowsep="1" valign="top">
<para>Actions can do privileged operation if the actions have been assigned
privileges in a rights profile that has been assigned to a user.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="column1">
<para>Actions are not managed by the Solaris Management Console.</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="column2">
<para>Actions are assigned to rights profiles in the Rights tool of the Solaris Management Console.
If new actions are added, the Security Administrator role can make the new
actions available.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="addsoft-41">
<title>Managing Software (Tasks)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1035">
<primary>applications</primary>
<secondary>installing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1036">
<primary>Managing Software (Tasks)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1037">
<primary>tasks and task maps</primary>
<secondary>Managing Software (Tasks)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Managing software in Trusted Extensions is similar to managing software
on a Solaris system that has non-global zones installed. For details
about zones, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2450" targetptr="zone">Part II, <citetitle remap="chapter">Zones,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="addsoft-40">

<title>How to Add a Software Package</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1038">
<primary>removable media</primary>
<secondary>mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1039">
<primary>packages</primary>
<secondary>accessing the media</secondary>
</indexterm>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>You must be in a role that can allocate a device.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Start from the appropriate workspace.</para>
<stepalternatives>
<step>
<para>To install a software package in the global zone, stay in the
global zone.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>To install a software package in a labeled zone, create a workspace
at that label.</para>
<para>For details, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="commontasks-40">How
to Work at a Different Label</olink>.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
<step>
<para>Allocate the CD-ROM device.</para>
<para>For details, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7313" targetptr="ugelem-27">
<citetitle remap="section">How to Allocate a Device</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions User’s Guide</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Install the software.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Deallocate the device when you are finished.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="addsoft-54">

<title>How to Install a Java Jar File</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1040">
<primary>Java jar files</primary>
<secondary>installing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-1041">
<primary>software</primary>
<secondary>installing Java programs</secondary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>This procedure downloads a Java jar file to the global zone. From the
global zone, the administrator can make it available to ordinary users.</para>
</tasksummary>
<taskprerequisites>

<para>The security administrator has verified that the source of the Java
program is trustworthy, that the method of delivery is secure, and that the
program can run in a trustworthy manner.</para>
<para>You are in the System Administrator role in the global zone.</para>
</taskprerequisites>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Download the Java jar file to the <filename class="directory">/tmp</filename> directory.</para>
<para>For example, if you are selecting software from the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="text" xlink:href="http://www.sunfreeware.com">http://www.sunfreeware.com</link>,
download the link that is described with Web Start Wizard form of <replaceable>application</replaceable>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Open a File Manager to the <filename class="directory">/tmp</filename> directory.</para>
<para>The Software Installation profile includes the Open action for
Java code.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Double-click the downloaded file.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Answer the questions in the dialog boxes to install the software.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Read the installation log.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="addsoft-14">

<title>Downloading a Java Jar File to a User Label</title>
<para>To limit the security risk, the system administrator downloads the software
to a single label within an ordinary user's accreditation range. Then, the
security administrator tests the jar file at that label. The administrator
then downgrades the label to <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>, and installs
it on an NFS server to make it available to all users.</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>In the System Administrator role, create a workspace at a
user label.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In that workspace, download the Java jar file.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In that workspace, test the file.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Then, change the label of the file to <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The System Administrator role then copies the file to an NFS
server whose label is <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
