<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">



<title>Devices in Trusted Extensions</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-804">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm>
<toc>
<para>This chapter describes device protection in Trusted Extensions.</para>
<itemizedlist remap="jumplist">
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-16.xml" targetptr="managedev-52">Device Protection With Trusted
Extensions Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-16.xml" targetptr="managedev-50">Device Allocation Manager
GUI</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-16.xml" targetptr="managedev-25">Enforcement of Device Security</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-16.xml" targetptr="managedev-40">Devices in Trusted Extensions
(Reference)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="managedev-52">
<title>Device Protection With Trusted Extensions Software</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-805">
<primary>users</primary>
<secondary>accessing devices</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-806">
<primary>accessing</primary>
<secondary>devices</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-807">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>allocating</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-808">
<primary>device allocation</primary>
<secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-809">
<primary>protecting</primary>
<secondary>devices</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-810">
<primary>restricting</primary>
<secondary>access to devices</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>On a Solaris system, devices can be protected by allocation and
by authorization. By default, devices are available to ordinary users without
an authorization. A system that is configured with Trusted Extensions software
uses the device protection mechanisms of the Solaris OS.</para>
<para>However, Trusted Extensions requires that a device be allocated for use,
and by default, requires that the user be authorized to use the device. In
addition, devices are protected by labels. Trusted Extensions provides a graphical
user interface for administrators to manage devices. The same interface is
used by users to allocate devices.</para>
<para>For information on device protection in the Solaris OS, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="devtask-1">Chapter 4, <citetitle remap="chapter">Controlling Access to Devices (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>. This chapter covers the extensions
to device protection that Trusted Extensions provides.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<para>On a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions, two roles protect
devices.</para>
<listitem>
<para>The system administrator controls access to peripheral devices.</para>
<para>The System Administrator role makes a device allocatable. Devices that
the system administrator makes nonallocatable cannot be used by anyone. Allocatable
devices can be allocated only by authorized users.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The Security Administrator role restricts the labels at which
a device can be accessed and sets device policy. The security administrator
decides who is authorized to allocate a device.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<para>The following are the main features of device control with Trusted Extensions software:</para>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-811">
<primary>Allocate Device authorization</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-812">
<primary>authorizations</primary>
<secondary>Allocate Device</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-813">
<primary>diskettes</primary>
<secondary>accessing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-814">
<primary>CD-ROM devices</primary>
<secondary>accessing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-815">
<primary>tape devices</primary>
<secondary>accessing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-816">
<primary>users</primary>
<secondary>accessing devices</secondary>
</indexterm>An unauthorized user on a default Trusted Extensions system cannot
allocate devices such as tape drives, CD-ROM drives, or diskette drives.</para>
<para>An ordinary user with the Allocate Device authorization can import or
export information at the label at which the user allocates the device.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Users invoke the Device Allocation Manager to allocate devices
when logged in directly. To allocate a device remotely, you must
be able to the global zone. Typically, only roles can log in to the global
zone.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The label range of each device can be restricted by the security
administrator. Ordinary users are limited to accessing devices whose label
range includes the labels at which the users are allowed to work. The default
label range is <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> to <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Label ranges can be restricted for both allocatable and nonallocatable
devices. Nonallocatable devices are devices such as framebuffers and printers.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="managedev-11">
<title>Device Label Ranges</title>
<para>To prevent users from copying sensitive information, each allocatable
device has a label range. To use an allocatable device, the user must be currently
operating at a label within the device's label range. If the user is not,
allocation is denied. The user's current label is applied to data imported
or exported while the device is allocated to the user. The label of exported
data is displayed when the device is deallocated. The user should physically
label the medium that contains the exported data.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="managedev-32">
<title>Effects of Label Range on a Device</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-817">
<primary>label ranges</primary>
<secondary>setting on frame buffers</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-818">
<primary>restricting</primary>
<secondary>access to computer based on label</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-819">
<primary>computer access</primary>
<secondary>restricting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-820">
<primary>label ranges</primary>
<secondary>setting on printers</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-821">
<primary>nonallocatable devices</primary>
<secondary>setting label range</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-822">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>setting label range for nonallocatable</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-823">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>setting label range</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To restrict direct login access through the console, the Security Administrator
role can set a restricted label range on the framebuffer.</para>
<para>For example, a restricted label range might be specified to limit access
to a publicly accessible computer. The label range enables users to access
the computer only at a label within the framebuffer's label range.</para>
<para>When a host has a local printer, a restricted label range on the printer
limits the jobs that can be printed on the printer.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="managedev-39">
<title>Device Access Policies</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-824">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>access policy</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-825">
<primary>access policy</primary>
<secondary>devices</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-826">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>setting policy</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-827">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>policy defaults</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Trusted Extensions follows the same device policy as the Solaris OS.
The Security Administrator role can change default policies and define new
policies. The <command>getdevpolicy</command> command retrieves information
about device policy, and the <command>update_drv</command> command changes
device policy. For more information, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="devtask-10">
<citetitle remap="section">Configuring Device Policy (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>. See also the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="getdevpolicy-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>getdevpolicy</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="update-drv-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>update_drv</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man pages.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="managedev-30">
<title>Device-Clean Scripts</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-828">
<primary>
<command>device-clean</command> scripts</primary>
<secondary>requirements</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>A device-clean script is run when a device is allocated or deallocated.
The Solaris OS provides scripts for tape, CD-ROM, and diskette drives. If your
site adds allocatable device types to the system, the added devices might
need scripts. To see existing scripts, go to the <filename class="directory">/etc/security/lib</filename> directory. For more information, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="devtask-38">
<citetitle remap="section">Device-Clean Scripts</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>For Trusted Extensions software, device-clean scripts must satisfy certain
requirements. The requirements are described on the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2252" targetptr="device-clean-5">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>device_clean</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
5
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managedev-50">
<title>Device Allocation Manager GUI</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-829">
<primary>actions</primary>
<secondary>Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-830">
<primary>devices</primary>
<secondary>accessing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-831">
<primary>Front Panel</primary>
<secondary>Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-832">
<primary>Tools subpanel</primary>
<secondary>Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-833">
<primary>Device Allocation Manager</primary>
<secondary>description</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-834">
<primary>allocating</primary>
<secondary>using Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/DevAlloc.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Shows the Device Allocation icon.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The Device Allocation Manager is used by administrators to administer
allocatable and nonallocatable devices. The Device Allocation Manager is also
used by ordinary users to allocate and deallocate devices. The users must
have the Allocate Device authorization. In a Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) workspace, the Device
Allocation Manager is launched from the Front Panel. The following figure
shows a Device Allocation Manager that was opened by a user who can allocate
the <literal>audio</literal> device.</para>
<figure>

<title>Device Allocation Manager Opened by a User</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/devmgr.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Dialog box titled Device Allocation Manager shows the
user name, and the devices that are available to that user.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>Users see an empty list when the users are not authorized to allocate
devices. Or, an empty list might mean that the allocatable devices are currently
allocated by another user or are in an error state. If a user cannot see a
device in the Available Devices list, the user needs to contact the responsible
administrator.</para>
<para>The Device Administration feature is available to roles that have either
one or both of the authorizations that are needed to administer devices. The
administration authorizations are Configure Device Attributes, and Revoke
or Reclaim Device. The following figure shows a Device Allocation Administration
dialog box.</para>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/devadmin.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Dialog box titled Device Allocation Administration shows
a list of devices and status. Shows the Revoke, Reclaim, New, and Configure
buttons.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managedev-25">
<title>Enforcement of Device Security</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-835">
<primary>users</primary>
<secondary>security training</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-836">
<primary>security policy</primary>
<secondary>users and devices</secondary>
</indexterm>
<itemizedlist>
<para>The security administrator decides who can allocate devices. The security
administrator should make sure that any user who is authorized to use devices
is trained. The user is trusted to do the following:</para>
<listitem>
<para>Properly label and handle any media containing exported sensitive
information so that the information does not become available to anyone who
should not see it.</para>
<para>For example, if information at a label of <constant>NEED TO KNOW ENGINEERING</constant> is stored on a diskette, the person
who exports the information must physically label the disk with the <constant>NEED
TO KNOW ENGINEERING</constant> label. The diskette must be stored where it
is accessible only to members of the engineering group with a need to know.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Ensure that labels are properly maintained on any information
being imported (read) from media on these devices.</para>
<para>An authorized
user should allocate the device at the label that matches the label of the
information being imported. For example, if a user allocates a diskette drive
at <constant>PUBLIC</constant>, the user should only import information labeled <constant>PUBLIC</constant>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-837">
<primary>Security Administrator role</primary>
<secondary>enforcing security</secondary>
</indexterm>The Security Administrator role also is responsible for enforcing
proper compliance with security requirements.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managedev-40">
<title>Devices in Trusted Extensions (Reference)</title>
<para>Trusted Extensions device protection uses Solaris interfaces and Trusted Extensions interfaces.</para>
<para>For Solaris command line interfaces, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="devtask-16">
<citetitle remap="section">Device Protection (Reference)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<note>

<para>In Trusted Extensions, users cannot use the <command>allocate</command> and <command>deallocate</command> commands. Users must use the Device Allocation Manager.</para>
</note>
<para>Administrators who do not have access to the Device Allocation Manager
can administer allocatable devices by using the command line. The <command>allocate</command> and <command>deallocate</command> commands have administrative
options. For examples, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="devtask-13">
<citetitle remap="section">Forcibly Allocating a Device</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink> and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-3321" targetptr="devtask-31">
<citetitle remap="section">Forcibly Deallocating a Device</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle>
</olink>.</para>
<para>For Trusted Extensions command line interfaces, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7307" targetptr="add-allocatable-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>add_allocatable</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> and <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-7307" targetptr="remove-allocatable-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>remove_allocatable</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man pages.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
