<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="hbsysboot-76719">



<title>The Boot Process
(Reference)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter describes the firmware used for booting SPARC based and x86 based
systems. This chapter also provides an overview of the boot process on each platform.</para>
<para>In this release, GRUB based booting has been implemented
on x86 based systems. For reference information that pertains to GRUB based booting,
see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="fwamf">
The GRUB Based Boot Process (Reference)</olink>.</para>
<note>

<para>GRUB based booting is not available on SPARC based systems in this Solaris release.</para>
</note>
<para>This is a list of the reference information in this chapter.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-13.xml" targetptr="hbsysboot-19570">
The Boot PROM</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-13.xml" targetptr="hbsysboot-41054">
The Boot Process</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-13.xml" targetptr="hbsysboot-82010">
The System BIOS</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-13.xml" targetptr="hbsysboot-36626">
Boot Process</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For step-by-step instructions on booting an x86 based system, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-10.xml" targetptr="hbsparcboot-79782">Chapter 10, Booting a System (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</toc>
<sect1 arch="sparc" xml:id="hbsysboot-19570">
<title>
The Boot PROM</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="hbsysboot-ix1038">
<primary>monitor (PROM)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="hbsysboot-ix1039">
<primary>PROM</primary>
<secondary>monitor</secondary>
</indexterm>Each SPARC based system has a programmable read-only memory (PROM) chip
with a program called the <emphasis>monitor</emphasis>. The monitor controls the operation
of the system before the Solaris kernel is available. When a system is turned on,
the monitor runs a quick self-test procedure to check the hardware and memory on the
system. If no errors are found, the system begins the automatic boot process.</para>
<note>

<para>Some older systems might require PROM upgrades before they will work with
the Solaris system software. Contact your local service provider for more information.</para>
</note>
</sect1>
<sect1 arch="sparc" xml:id="hbsysboot-41054">
<title>
The Boot Process</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="hbsysboot-ix1040">
<primary>boot process</primary>
<secondary>description (SPARC)</secondary>
</indexterm>The following table describes the boot process on SPARC based systems. </para>
<table arch="sparc" frame="topbot" xml:id="hbsysboot-31272">

<title>
Description of the
Boot Process</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="91*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colwidth="305*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Boot Phase</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Boot PROM</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>1. The PROM displays system identification information and then runs self-test
diagnostics to verify the system's hardware and memory.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>2. The PROM loads the primary boot program, <command>bootblk</command>. This
program's purpose is to load the secondary boot program (that is located in the UFS
file system) from the default boot device.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Boot programs</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>3. The <command>bootblk</command> program finds and executes the secondary boot
program, <command>ufsboot</command>, and loads it into memory.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>4. After the <filename>ufsboot</filename> program is loaded, the <command>ufsboot</command> program loads the kernel.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Kernel initialization</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>5. The kernel initializes itself and begins loading modules by using <command>ufsboot</command> to read the files. When the kernel has loaded enough modules to
mount the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system, the kernel unmaps the <command>ufsboot</command> program and continues, using its own resources.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>6.  The kernel creates a user process and starts the <command>/sbin/init</command> process.
This process starts other processes by reading the <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> file.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<command>init</command>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>7. In this Solaris release, the <command>/sbin/init</command> process starts <command>/lib/svc/bin/svc.startd</command>, which starts system services that do the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Check and mount file systems</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Configure network and devices</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Start various processes and perform system maintenance tasks</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>In addition, <command>svc.startd</command> executes the run control (<command>rc</command>) scripts for compatibility.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-82010">
<title>
The System BIOS</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="hbsysboot-ix1041">
<primary>booting</primary>
<secondary>and PC BIOS</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="hbsysboot-ix1042">
<primary>PC BIOS (and booting)</primary>
</indexterm>Before the kernel is started, the system is controlled by the read-only-memory
(ROM) Basic Input/Output System (BIOS), which is the firmware interface on a non-SPARC
based system.</para>
<para>Hardware adapters can have an on-board BIOS that displays the physical characteristics
of the device and can be used to access the device.</para>
<para>During the startup sequence, the system BIOS checks for the presence of any
adapter BIOS, and if found, loads and executes each adapter BIOS. Each individual
adapter's BIOS runs self-test diagnostics and displays device information.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-14119">
<title>
Boot Subsystems</title>
<para>During the boot process, the boot subsystem menus allow you to customize boot
choices. If the system receives no response during the timeout periods, it continues
to boot automatically using the default selections. You can stop the boot process
when each boot subsystem menu is displayed. Or, you can let the boot process continue
automatically.</para>
<para>At three points during the Solaris boot process, you can make the following
choices about a booting system:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Primary Boot Subsystem (Partition Boot Menu)</emphasis> – This first menu appears if multiple operating systems exist on
the disk. The menu enables you to boot any of the operating systems installed. By
default, the operating system that is designed as <emphasis>active</emphasis> is booted.</para>
<para>Note that if you choose to boot a system other than the Solaris Operating System,
you cannot reach the next two menus.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Interrupt the Autoboot Process</emphasis> –
If the autoboot process is interrupted, you can access the Device Configuration Assistant
menu.</para>
<para>The Solaris Device Configuration Assistant enables you to boot the
Solaris system from a different boot device, configure new or misconfigured hardware,
or perform other device-related or boot-related tasks.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Current Boot Parameters menu</emphasis> –
Two forms of this menu exist, one menu for a normal Solaris boot and one menu for
a Solaris installation boot:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The normal Current Boot Parameters menu enables you to boot the Solaris
system with options, or enter the boot interpreter. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The install Current Boot Parameters menu enables you to select the
type of installation to be performed or to customize the boot process.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The following table summarizes the purpose of the primary x86 based system
boot interfaces. See the sections that follow for a detailed description and example
of each boot interface.</para>
<table arch="x86" frame="topbot" xml:id="hbsysboot-31167">

<title>
Boot Subsystems</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="132*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colwidth="264*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Boot Subsystem</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Purpose</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Primary Boot Subsystem (Partition Boot menu)</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>This menu appears if the disk you are booting from contains multiple operating
systems, including the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS).</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Secondary Boot Subsystem</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>This menu appears each time you boot the Solaris release. The Solaris release
is booted automatically unless you choose to run the Solaris Device Configuration
Assistant by interrupting the autoboot process.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Solaris Device Configuration Assistant/Boot Diskette</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>There are two ways to access the Device Configuration Assistant menus: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Use the Device Configuration Assistant boot diskette or the Solaris
Software 1 CD (on systems that can boot from the CD-ROM drive) to boot the system.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Interrupt the autoboot process when you boot the  Solaris software
from an installed disk.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Current Boot Parameters menu</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>This menu appears when you boot the Solaris release from the disk, CD-ROM, or
the network. The menu presents a list of boot options.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<note>

<para>If you need to create the Solaris Device Configuration Assistant boot
diskette, go to <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="url" xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl/drivers/dca_diskettes/">http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl/drivers/dca_diskettes/</link>.</para>
</note>
<sect2 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-1">
<title>
Booting the Solaris Release</title>
<para>In this release, if you are booting an x86 based system with the Solaris Software
1 CD, DVD, or performing a PXE network boot, the system will boot automatically. To
use the Device Configuration Assistant, you must interrupt the boot process by pressing
Esc when prompted by the system.</para>
<para>During the device identification phase, the Device Configuration Assistant does
the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Scans for devices that are installed on the system</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Displays the identified devices</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Enables you to perform optional tasks such as selecting a keyboard
type or editing devices and their resources</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>During the boot phase, the Device Configuration Assistant does the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Displays a list of devices from which to boot. The device marked with
an asterisk (*) is the default boot device.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Enables you to perform optional tasks, such as editing autoboot settings
and property settings, and choosing the network configuration strategy.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The following section provides examples of menus that appear during the device
identification phase. The device output varies based on your system configuration.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-5">
<title>
Screens Displayed During the Device Identification
Phase</title>
<para>Several screens are displayed as the Device Configuration Assistant attempts
to identify devices on the system. This section provides examples of the following
boot subsystem screens:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Device Configuration Assistant screen</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Bus Enumeration screen</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Scanning Devices screen</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Identified Devices screen</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect3 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-2">
<title>
Device Configuration Assistant Screen</title>
<note>

<para>In the current Solaris release, the Device Configuration Assistant Screen has
been replaced with the GRUB menu on x86 based systems. For more information, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-11.xml" targetptr="hbx86boot-68676">Chapter 11, GRUB Based Booting (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</note>
<para>In the Solaris 10 initial release, the autoboot process bypasses the Device
Configuration Assistant menus, unless you press Esc when prompted by the system during
the boot phase. If you choose to use the Device Configuration Assistant, the following
screen is displayed.</para>
<screen width="100">Solaris Device Configuration Assistant
                                             
The Solaris(TM)Device Configuration Assistant
scans to identify system hardware, lists identified devices, and can
boot the Solaris software from a specified device. This program must be
used to install the Solaris operating environment, add a driver,
or change the hardware on the system. 

&gt; To perform a full scan to identify all system hardware, choose Continue. 
&gt; To diagnose possible full scan failures, choose Specific Scan.
&gt; To add new or updated device drivers, choose Add Driver. 

About navigation...  
	- The mouse cannot be used. 
	- If the keyboard does not have function keys or they do not respond,
	  press ESC. The legend at the bottom of the screen will change to
	  show the ESC keys to use for navigation. 
	- The F2 key performs the default action.

F2_Continue		F3_Specific Scan		F4_Add Driver		F6_Help</screen>
</sect3>
<sect3 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-7">
<title>
Bus Enumeration Screen</title>
<para>The Bus Enumeration screen appears briefly while the Device Configuration Assistant
gathers hardware configuration data for devices that can be detected automatically. </para>
<screen>Bus Enumeration

Determining bus types and gathering hardware configuration data ...

Please wait ...</screen>
</sect3>
<sect3 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-4">
<title>
Scanning Devices Screen</title>
<para>The Scanning Devices screen appears while the Device Configuration Assistant
manually scans for devices that can only be detected with special drivers. </para>
<screen>Scanning Devices

The system is being scanned to identify system hardware.

If the scanning stalls, press the system's reset button. When the
system reboots, choose Specific Scan or Help.


Scanning: Floppy disk controller

#######################
|      |        |         |         |         |
0	 		 20       40        60	       80       100

Please wait ...</screen>
</sect3>
<sect3 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-3">
<title>
Identified Devices Screen</title>
<para>The Identified Devices screen displays which devices have been identified on
the system. From here, you can continue to the Boot Solaris menu. Or, you can perform
the following optional device tasks:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Setting a keyboard configuration</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Viewing and editing devices</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Setting up a serial console</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Saving and deleting configurations</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<screen>Identified Devices

The following devices have been identified on this system. To identify
devices not on this list or to modify device characteristics, such as
keyboard configuration, choose Device Tasks. Platform types may be
included in this list.

ISA: Floppy disk controller
	ISA: Motherboard
	ISA: PnP bios: 16550-compatible serial controller
	ISA: PnP bios: 16550-compatible serial controller
	ISA: PnP bios: Mouse controller
	ISA: PnP bios: Parallel port
	ISA: System keyboard (US-English)
	PCI: Bus Mastering IDE controller
	PCI: Universal Serial Bus
	PCI: VGA compatible display adapter

F2_Continue   F3_Back   F4_Device Tasks   F6_Help</screen>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-13">
<title>
Menus Displayed During the Boot Phase</title>
<para>During this phase, you can determine the way in which the system is booted.
The following menus are displayed during the boot phase:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Boot Solaris menu</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Current Boot Parameters menu</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect3 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-14">
<title>
Boot Solaris Menu</title>
<para>The Boot Solaris menu allows you to select the device from which to boot the
Solaris release. You can also perform optional tasks, such as viewing and editing
autoboot and property settings. Once you select a boot device and you choose Continue,
the Solaris kernel begins to boot.</para>
<screen>Boot Solaris
Select one of the identified devices to boot the Solaris kernel and
choose Continue.

To perform optional features, such as modifying the autoboot and property
settings, choose Boot Tasks.

An asterisk (*) indicates the current default boot device.

&gt; To make a selection use the arrow keys, and press Enter to mark it [X].

[<userinput>X</userinput>]  DISK: (*) Target 0:QUANTUM  FIREBALL1280A
on Bus Mastering IDE controller on Board PCI at Dev 7, Func 1
[ ]  DISK: Target 1:ST5660A
on Bus Mastering IDE controller on Board PCI at Dev 7, Func 1
[ ]  DISK: Target 0:Maxtor 9 0680D4
	on Bus Mastering IDE controller on Board PCI at Dev 7, Func 1
[ ]  CD  : Target 1:TOSHIBA  CD-ROM XM-5602B  1546
	on Bus Mastering IDE controller on Board PCI at Dev 7, Func 1

F2_Continue   F3_Back   F4_Boot Tasks   F6_Help</screen>
</sect3>
<sect3 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-6">
<title>
Current Boot Parameters Menu</title>
<para>This menu appears each time you boot the Solaris release from the local disk.
Let the five-second timeout elapse if you want to boot the default Solaris kernel.
If you want to boot with different options, select an appropriate option before the
timeout period elapses. </para>
<screen>                     &lt;&lt;&lt; Current Boot Parameters &gt;&gt;&gt;
Boot path: /pci@0,0/pci-ide@7,1/ide@0/cmdk@0,0:a
Boot args: 
Type    b [file-name] [boot-flags] &lt;ENTER&gt;       to boot with options
or      i &lt;ENTER&gt;                                to enter boot interpreter
or      &lt;ENTER&gt;                                  to boot with defaults
 
 
                     &lt;&lt;&lt; timeout in 5 seconds &gt;&gt;&gt;
 
Select (b)oot or (i)nterpreter: </screen>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 arch="x86" xml:id="hbsysboot-36626">
<title>
Boot Process</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="hbsysboot-ix1050">
<primary>boot process</primary>
<secondary>x86</secondary>
</indexterm>The following table describes the boot process on x86 based systems. </para>
<table arch="x86" frame="topbot" xml:id="hbsysboot-30637">

<title>
Description of the Boot
Process</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="91*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colwidth="305*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Boot Phase</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>BIOS</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>1. When the system is turned on, the BIOS runs self-test diagnostics to verify
the system's hardware and memory. The system begins to boot automatically if no errors
are found. If errors are found, error messages are displayed that describe recovery
options.</para>
<para>The BIOS of additional hardware devices are run at this time.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>2. The BIOS boot program tries to read the first disk sector from the boot device.
This first disk sector on the boot device contains the master boot record <literal>mboot</literal>, which is loaded and executed. If no <literal>mboot</literal> file
is found, an error message is displayed.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Boot Programs</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>3. The master boot record, <command>mboot</command>, contains disk information
needed to find the active partition and the location of the Solaris boot program, <literal>pboot</literal>, loads and executes <literal>pboot</literal>, <literal>mboot</literal>.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>4.  The Solaris boot program, <command>pboot</command>, loads <command>bootblk</command>, the primary boot program. The purpose of <command>bootblk</command> is
to load the secondary boot program, which is located in the UFS file system.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>5. If there is more than one bootable partition, <command>bootblk</command> reads
the <literal>fdisk</literal> table to locate the default boot partition, and builds
and displays a menu of available partitions. You have a 30 seconds to select an alternate
partition from which to boot. This step occurs only if there is more than one bootable
partition present on the system.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>6. <command>bootblk</command> finds and executes the secondary boot program, <command>boot.bin</command> or <literal>ufsboot</literal>, in the root  (<filename>/</filename>)
file system. You have five seconds to interrupt the autoboot to start the Solaris
Device Configuration Assistant.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>7. The secondary boot program, <command>boot.bin</command> or <command>ufsboot</command>, starts a command interpreter that executes the <filename>/etc/bootrc</filename> script.
This script provides a menu of choices for booting the system. The default action
is to load and execute the kernel. You have a 5–second interval to specify a
boot option or to start the boot interpreter.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Kernel initialization</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>8. The kernel initializes itself and begins loading modules by using the secondary
boot program (<command>boot.bin</command> or <command>ufsboot</command>) to read the
files. When the kernel has loaded enough modules to mount the root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system, the kernel unmaps the secondary boot program and continues, using its
own resources.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>9. The kernel creates a user process and starts the <command>/sbin/init</command> process,
which starts other processes by reading the <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> file.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<command>init</command>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>10. In this Solaris release, the <command>/sbin/init</command> process starts <command>/lib/svc/bin/svc.startd</command>, which starts system services that do the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Check and mount file systems</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Configure network and devices</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Start various processes and perform system maintenance tasks</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>In addition, <command>svc.startd</command> executes the run control (<command>rc</command>) scripts for compatibility.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 arch="x86" xml:id="hbrunlevels-8">
<title>
Boot Files</title>
<para>In addition to the run control scripts and boot files, there are additional
boot files that are associated with booting x86 based systems.</para>
<table arch="x86" frame="topbot" xml:id="hbrunlevels-9">

<title>
Boot Files</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="160.80*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colwidth="235.20*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>File</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/etc/bootrc</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Contains menus and options for booting the Solaris release.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Contains files and directories needed to boot the system.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/mdboot</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>DOS executable that loads the first-level bootstrap program (<filename>strap.com</filename>) into memory from disk.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/mdbootbp</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>DOS executable that loads the first-level bootstrap program (<filename>strap.com</filename>) into memory from diskette.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/rc.d</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Directory that contains install scripts. Do not modify the contents of this
directory.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Directory that contains items for the boot subsystem.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/boot.bin</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Loads the Solaris kernel or stand-alone <command>kmdb</command>. In addition,
this executable provides some boot firmware services.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/boot.rc</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Prints the Solaris Operating System on an x86 system and runs the Device Configuration
Assistant in DOS-emulation mode.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/bootconf.exe</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>DOS executable for the Device Configuration Assistant.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/bootconf.txt</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para> Text file that contains internationalized messages for Device Configuration
Assistant (<filename>bootconf.exe</filename>).</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/bootenv.rc</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Stores <command>eeprom</command> variables that are used to set up the boot
environment. </para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/devicedb</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Directory that contains the <filename>master</filename> file, a database of
all possible devices supported with realmode drivers.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/drivers</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Directory that contains realmode drivers.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/itup2.exe</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>DOS executable run during install time update (ITU) process. </para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/machines</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Obsolete directory.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/nbp</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>File associated with network booting.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/solaris/strap.rc</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>File that contains instructions on what load module to load and where in memory
it should be loaded.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<filename>/boot/strap.com</filename>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>DOS executable that loads the second-level bootstrap program into memory.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
</chapter>
