<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="printforms-12319">



<title>Managing Character Sets, Filters,
Forms, and Fonts (Tasks)</title>
<toc>
<para>This chapter provides overview information and step-by-step instructions for
setting up and administering character sets, print filters, forms, and fonts.</para>
<para>For information on the step-by-step procedures associated with managing character
sets, filters, forms, and fonts, see the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="embzi">Managing Character Sets (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="eojcq">Managing Print Filters (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="eojco">Managing Forms (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="eojct">Managing Fonts (Task Map)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about printing, see the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-1.xml" targetptr="printconcept-76595">Chapter 1, Managing Printing Services (Overview)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="printconcept-76596">Chapter 2, Planning Printers on Your Network (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-3.xml" targetptr="printsetup-33230">Chapter 3, Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-15883">Chapter 4, Administering Printers (Tasks)</olink>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</toc>
<sect1 xml:id="embzi">
<title>Managing Character Sets (Task Map)</title>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Define a print wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Define a print wheel or font cartridge that can be used with a printer.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-83223">How to Set an Alert to Mount a Print Wheel or Font Cartridge</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Unmount and mount a print wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Delete a current print wheel or font cartridge from the print server's configuration
file. Adds a new print wheel or font cartridge to the print server's configuration
file.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-29773">How to Unmount and Mount a Print Wheel or Font Cartridge</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Set up alerts to mount a print wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Set up email alerts for print requests.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-83223">How to Set an Alert to Mount a Print Wheel or Font Cartridge</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Set up an alias for a selectable character set.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Set up aliases when <literal>terminfo</literal> names for the selectable character
sets are inadequate.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-36731">How to Set Up an Alias for a Selectable Character Set</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printforms-1">
<title>Managing Character Sets</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix491">
<primary>managing</primary>
<secondary>character sets</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix492">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>styles</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix493">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>PostScript</secondary>
<tertiary>treatment of text</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix494">
<primary>PostScript printers</primary>
</indexterm>Printers differ in the method that they use to print text in various font
styles. For example, PostScript printers treat text as graphics. These printers can
generate text in different fonts. They can also place the text in any position, size,
or orientation on the page. Other types of printers support a more limited number
of font styles and sizes. These printers use either print wheels, font cartridges,
or preprogrammed selectable character sets. Usually, only one printing method applies
to a given printer type.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix495">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>print wheels</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix496">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>font cartridges</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix498">
<primary>character set</primary>
<secondary>hardware</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix499">
<primary>character set</primary>
<secondary>software</secondary>
</indexterm>From the perspective of the LP print service, print wheels and font cartridges
are similar. In both cases, someone must intervene and mount the hardware on the printer,
when needed. Character sets that require you to physically mount a print wheel or
font cartridge are referred to as <emphasis>hardware character sets</emphasis>. Character
sets that do not require hardware mounting, come preprogrammed with the printer. These
character sets can be selected by a print request. They are referred to as <emphasis>software character sets</emphasis>.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix500">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>non-PostScript</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix501">
<primary>non-PostScript printers</primary>
</indexterm>When you set up a non-PostScript printer, you need to tell the LP print
service which print wheels or selectable character sets are available to users. When
users submit print requests, the <command>lp -S</command> command enables them to
specify a print wheel or selectable character set to use for the print job. Users
do not have to know which type of character set applies. They just refer to the font
style by the name you have defined. For example, you can define a print wheel as <literal>gothic</literal>. To request the <literal>gothic</literal> print wheel, the user would
use the following command: </para>
<screen>% <userinput>lp -S gothic</userinput> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
</screen>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-15091">
<title>Selectable Character Sets</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix502">
<primary>selectable character sets</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix503">
<primary>
<filename>terminfo</filename> entry</primary>
<secondary>selectable character sets in</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix504">
<primary>character sets</primary>
<secondary>selectable</secondary>
</indexterm>The selectable character sets supported by a printer are listed in the <filename>terminfo</filename> entry for that printer. For example, the entry for the <literal>ln03</literal> printer is <filename>/usr/share/lib/terminfo/l/ln03</filename>. You
can find the names of selectable character sets for any printer type in the <filename>terminfo</filename> database by using the <command>tput</command> command. The syntax
for the <command>tput</command> command is as follows:</para>
<screen>tput -T <replaceable>printer-type</replaceable> cs<replaceable>n</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix505">
<primary>character sets</primary>
<secondary>number</secondary>
</indexterm>The <command>cs</command>
<replaceable>n</replaceable> option is an abbreviation
for character set number. The number starts with 0, which is always the default character
set number after the printer is initialized. To display the names of the other character
sets, you can repeat the command by using <option>
1</option>, <option>
2</option>, <option>
3</option>, and so on, in place of the <option>
0</option>. For each selectable character
set, a <command>terminfo</command> name, for example, <literal>usascii</literal>, <literal>english</literal>, <literal>finnish</literal>, and so forth, is returned.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix506">
<primary>
<filename>terminfo</filename> database</primary>
<secondary>character set names</secondary>
</indexterm>In general, the <filename>terminfo</filename> character set names should
closely match the character set names that are used in the manufacturer's documentation
for the printer. Because all manufacturers do not use the same character set names,
the <filename>terminfo</filename> character set names can differ from one printer
type to the next printer type. </para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix507">
<primary>alias for selectable character set</primary>
</indexterm>You do not have to register the selectable character set names with the
LP print service. However, you can give them more meaningful names or aliases.</para>
<note>

<para>If you do not specify the selectable character sets that can be used with
a printer, the LP print service assumes that the printer can accept any character
set name, such as <literal>cs0</literal>, <literal>cs1</literal>, or <literal>cs2</literal>, or the <filename>terminfo</filename> name known for the printer.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix508">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>PostScript</secondary>
<tertiary>character sets for</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix509">
<primary>PostScript printers</primary>
<secondary>character sets for</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix510">
<primary>character sets</primary>
<secondary>selectable</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix511">
<primary>selectable character sets</primary>
</indexterm>Character sets for PostScript printers are not listed when you use the <command>lpstat -p -l</command> command. The PostScript fonts are controlled by PostScript
filters, not by entries in the <filename>terminfo</filename> database. For information
about how to administer PostScript fonts, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-26075">Managing Fonts</olink>.</para>
</note>
<para>Users can use the <command>lpstat -p -l</command> command to display the names
of the selectable character sets that you have defined for each printer on a print
server.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-42551">
<title>Hardware Character Sets</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix512">
<primary>character sets</primary>
<secondary>hardware</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix513">
<primary>print wheels</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix514">
<primary>font cartridges</primary>
</indexterm>Another method to obtain alternative character sets is to use removable
print wheels or font cartridges that you physically attach, or mount, in a printer. </para>
<para>To administer hardware-mounted character sets, you inform the LP print service
of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The names you want to use for the available print wheels</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>How you want to be alerted when a printer needs a different print
wheel</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Then, when a user requests a particular character set by using the <command>lp -S</command> command, the print scheduler sends an alert to mount the print wheel.
In addition, the print request is placed in the print queue. When you mount the correct
print wheel and tell the LP print service that the print wheel is mounted, the job
is printed. For more information, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-29773">How to Unmount and Mount a Print Wheel or Font Cartridge</olink>.</para>
<para>If you do not specify multiple print wheels or font cartridges for a printer,
the LP print service assumes that the printer has a single, fixed print wheel or font
cartridge. As such, users cannot specify a special print wheel or font cartridge when
using that printer.</para>
<para>Unlike selectable character sets, the names you use for print wheels or font
cartridges are not tied to entries in the <filename>terminfo</filename> database.
Print wheel names or font cartridge names are used only for the purpose of communicating
with the LP print service and its users. <indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix515">
<primary>print wheels</primary>
<secondary>naming</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix516">
<primary>font cartridges</primary>
<secondary>naming</secondary>
</indexterm>
</para>
<para>However, the names you choose for print wheels or font cartridges should have
meaning to the users. The names should refer to font styles. In addition, the names
should be the same across printers that have similar print wheels, font cartridges,
or selectable character sets. That way, users can specify a font style (character
set), without regard to which printer will be used, or whether a print wheel, font
cartridges, or a selectable character set will be used.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix517">
<primary>character sets</primary>
<secondary>hardware</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix518">
<primary>non-PostScript printers</primary>
</indexterm>You and the printer users should agree on the meanings of print wheel
names or font cartridge names. Otherwise, what a user asks for and what you mount
might not be the same character set.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-44">
<title>Tracking Print Wheels</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printref-ix214">
<primary>print wheels</primary>
<secondary>tracking</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printref-ix215">
<primary>LP print service</primary>
<secondary>tracking print wheels</secondary>
</indexterm>The procedure for tracking print wheels is similar to the procedure for
tracking forms. Some printers, usually letter-quality printers, have removable print
heads that provide a particular font or character set. Removable print heads include
print wheels and print cartridges. A user can request a named character set. If that
character set is not available, the LP print service notifies <literal>root</literal> of
the request. The job is stored in the print queue until the print wheel is changed.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-37412">
<title>Alerts for Mounting Print Wheels or Font Cartridges</title>
<para>You request alerts for mounting print wheels or font cartridges in the same
way that you request other alerts from the LP print service. For general information
about alerts, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printplan-23">Setting Up Printer Fault Alerts</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-65132">

<title>How to Define a Print Wheel or Font Cartridge</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-65">
<primary>print wheels</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-66">
<primary>font cartridges</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-67">
<primary>defining</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-68">
<primary>defining</primary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>These procedure shows how to define a print wheel or font cartridge that can
be used with the printer.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-3">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-4">
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix527">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>defining print wheels with</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix528">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>defining font cartridges with</secondary>
</indexterm>Define a print wheel or font cartridge.</para>
<screen># <replaceable>print-server</replaceable> <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-S</userinput> <replaceable>hard-charset1</replaceable>[<userinput>,</userinput>
<replaceable>hard-charset2</replaceable>...]</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the printer for which you are defining a print
wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
s</option> <replaceable>hard-charset</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the hardware character set name of the print wheel or font
cartridge.</para>
<para>You can specify multiple hardware character sets with this command. Use commas
or spaces to separate character set names. If you use spaces, enclose the list of
character set names in quotation marks.</para>
<para>Define names that are meaningful to users. Inform the users of these names.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The print wheel or font cartridge definition is specified in the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-5">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on a print client of the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-6">
<para>Define the same print wheel or font cartridge for
the print client.</para>
<screen># <replaceable>print-client</replaceable> <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-S</userinput> <replaceable>hard-charset1, hard-charset2...</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>In this command, the variables are the same as the variables in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-4">Step 2</olink>.</para>
<para>The print wheel or font cartridge definition is added
to the print client's <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-7">
<para>Repeat <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-5">Step 3</olink> and <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-6">Step 4</olink> for each print
client that might need to use the print wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-111">
<para>Verify that the print wheel or font cartridge
is defined.</para>
<para>You should see the name of the character set and the notation <literal>(mounted)</literal>.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpstat -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgj">

<title>Defining a Print Wheel</title>
<para>The following example shows how to define the <literal>pica</literal> print
wheel on the printer <literal>luna</literal>. The print client is named <literal>asteroid</literal>.</para>
<screen>asteroid# <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -S pica</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-29773">

<title>How to Unmount and Mount a Print Wheel or Font
Cartridge</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-69">
<primary>unmounting and mounting</primary>
<secondary>print wheel or font cartridge</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-70">
<primary>mounting and unmounting</primary>
<secondary>print wheel or font cartridge</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-71">
<primary>print wheels</primary>
<secondary>unmounting and mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-72">
<primary>font cartridges</primary>
<secondary>unmounting and mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-11">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-12">
<para>Unmount the print wheel or font cartridge that
is mounted in the printer.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-M -S none</userinput>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the printer on which you are unmounting a print wheel or
font cartridge.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<command>
<option>
M</option> <option>
S</option> none</command>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Indicates that you want to unmount the current print wheel or font
cartridge.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpadmin-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpadmin</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<para>The current print wheel or font cartridge is deleted from the print
server's <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-13">
<para>Remove the print wheel or font cartridge from
the printer.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-14">
<para>Put the new print wheel or font cartridge in the
printer.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-15">
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix541">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>mounting print wheel with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix542">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>mounting font cartridge with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>Mount the new print wheel or font cartridge.  </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-M -S</userinput> <replaceable>hard-charset...</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the printer on which you are mounting a print wheel or font
cartridge.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
M</option> <option>
S</option> <replaceable>hard-charset</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the hardware character set name of the print wheel or font
cartridge you want to mount.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The print wheel or font cartridge is added to the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file. The mounted print wheel or font cartridge remains active until it
is unmounted or until a new print wheel or font cartridge is mounted. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-118">
<para>Check the information under the <literal>Print
wheels</literal> or <literal>Character set</literal> heading in the output of the
following command. </para>
<para>You should see the name of the print wheel or character
set and the notation <literal>(mounted)</literal>.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpstat -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgm">

<title>Unmounting and Mounting a Print Wheel</title>
<para>The following example shows how to unmount the current print wheel on the printer <literal>luna</literal> and mount the <literal>pica</literal> print wheel.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -M -S none</userinput>
# <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -M -S pica</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-83223">

<title>How to Set an Alert to Mount a Print Wheel or Font
Cartridge</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-73">
<primary>setting</primary>
<secondary>printer alerts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-74">
<primary>alerts</primary>
<secondary>setting for printers</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-75">
<primary>print wheels</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-76">
<primary>font cartridges</primary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-19">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-20">
<para>Set an alert to mount a print wheel or font cartridge.<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix553">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>setting alerts to mount print wheels with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -S</userinput> <replaceable>hard-charset</replaceable> -A <replaceable>alert</replaceable> [<userinput>-Q</userinput> <replaceable>requests</replaceable>] [<userinput>-W</userinput> <replaceable>minutes</replaceable>]</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
S</option> <replaceable>hard-charset</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the hardware character set name of the print wheel or font
cartridge for which you want to set an alert. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
A</option> <replaceable>alert</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies what kind of alert will occur when a print wheel or font
cartridge is requested. For detailed information about the valid values for <replaceable>alert</replaceable>, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-97091">Table 4–3</olink>.
Some valid values are <literal>mail</literal>, <literal>write</literal>, and <literal>quiet</literal>. </para>
<para>If you specify <literal>mail</literal> or <literal>write</literal>, a predefined
alert message says to mount the specified print wheel or font cartridge. The message
includes the names of one or more printers that have been set up to use such a print
wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
Q</option> <replaceable>requests</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the number of print requests that require the print wheel
or font cartridge that must be in the queue before an alert occurs. If you don't specify
this option, only one print request in the queue triggers an alert.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
W</option> <replaceable>minutes</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies how often (in minutes) the alert occurs If you don't specify
this option, the alert is sent one time.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpadmin-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpadmin</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<para>The alert is added to the print server's  <filename>/etc/lp/pwheels/</filename>
<replaceable>charset-name</replaceable>
<filename>/alert.sh</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-113">
<para>Verify that the alert has been added for the
print wheel or font cartridge by checking the output of the following command.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -S</userinput> <replaceable>hard-charset</replaceable> <userinput>-A list</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Alternately, if you have set a low number of print requests to trigger the alert,
submit enough print requests to meet the minimum requirements. Ensure that you receive
an alert to mount the print wheel or font cartridge.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgl">

<title>Setting an Alert to Mount a Print Wheel</title>
<para>The following example shows how to set email alerts to occur every 5 minutes
for the <literal>elite</literal> print wheel when the print queue contains 10 print
requests for the <literal>elite</literal>.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -S elite -A mail -Q 10 -W 5</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embzl">

<title>Setting an Alert to Mount a Font Cartridge</title>
<para>The following example shows how to set email alerts to occur every minute for
the <literal>finnish</literal> font cartridge when the print queue contains 5 print
requests for the <literal>finnish</literal>.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -S finnish -A mail -Q 5 -W 1</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embzd">

<title>Setting Up No Alerts for a Print Wheel</title>
<para>The following example shows how to set up no alerts for the <literal>elite</literal> print
wheel.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -S elite -A none</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-36731">

<title>How to Set Up an Alias for a Selectable Character
Set</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-77">
<primary>alias for selectable character set</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-78">
<primary>selectable character sets</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-79">
<primary>setting</primary>
</indexterm>
<tasksummary>
<para>You do not need to perform this procedure if the <filename>terminfo</filename> names
for the selectable character sets are adequate.  For more information on using the <filename>terminfo</filename> database, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-6.xml" targetptr="printcust-11157">Adding a <literal>terminfo</literal> Entry for an Unsupported Printer</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-24">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-25">
<para>Display the names of the selectable character
sets for the specified printer type.</para>
<screen># <userinput>tput -T</userinput> <replaceable>printer-type</replaceable> <userinput>cs</userinput>
<replaceable>n</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
T</option> <replaceable>printer-type</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the printer type found in the <filename>terminfo</filename> database.
 For information on entries in the <filename>terminfo</filename> database, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="printplan-15">Printer Type</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<replaceable>n</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the number (0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and so on) that represents
a selectable character set for the specified printer type. The system displays the
selectable character set name followed by the prompt symbol. For example, <literal>cs1</literal> could cause the system to display <literal>english#</literal>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="tput-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>tput</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-26">
<para>Set up an alias for a selectable character set.</para>
<screen width="100"># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-S</userinput> <replaceable>select-charset1=alias1,select-charset2=alias2...</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the printer on which you are setting up aliases for selectable
character sets.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
S</option>
<replaceable>select-charset</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the electable character set name. The name can be found
in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-25">Step 2</olink>. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<replaceable>alias</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Is the alias for the specified selectable character set. This alias
can be used in addition to the selectable character set name.</para>
<para>You can set up more than one alias with this command. Use commas or spaces to
separate the aliases. If you use spaces, enclose the list of aliases in quotation
marks.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The alias is added to the print server's  <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-27">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on a system that is a print client of the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-28">
<para>Set up an alias for the selectable character set.</para>
<screen width="100"># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-S</userinput> <replaceable>select-charset1=alias1,select-charset2=alias2...</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>In this command, the variables are the same as the variables in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-26">Step 3</olink>.</para>
<para>The alias is added to the print client's  <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-29">
<para>Repeat <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-27">Step 4</olink> and <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-28">Step 5</olink> for
each print client that might need to use the alias.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-120">
<para>On the print server and print clients, verify
that the selectable character set alias is listed in the output of the following command.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpstat -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Alternately, submit a print request that uses the alias for the selectable character
set and check for output.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgk">

<title>Setting Up an Alias for a Selectable Character Set</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix559">
<primary>setting up</primary>
<secondary>character sets (example of)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix560">
<primary>alias for selectable character set</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix561">
<primary>setting</primary>
<secondary>alias for selectable character set (example of)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix562">
<primary>selectable character sets</primary>
</indexterm>The following example shows how to display the names of selectable character
sets for the <literal>usascii</literal> selectable character set on the printer <literal>luna</literal>. The printer <literal>luna</literal> is a <literal>ln03</literal> printer
type. This example also shows how to specify text as an alias for the <literal>usascii</literal> selectable character set.</para>
<screen># <userinput>tput -T ln03 cs0</userinput>
usascii# <userinput>tput -T ln03 cs1</userinput>
english# <userinput>tput -T ln03 csn2</userinput>
finnish# <userinput>tput -T ln03 csn3</userinput>
japanese# <userinput>tput -T ln03 cs4</userinput>
norwegian#
# <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -S usascii=text</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="eojcq">
<title>Managing Print Filters (Task Map)</title>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Add a print filter.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Add information about print filters, which are programs that convert the content
type of a file to a content type that is acceptable to the destination printer.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-96887">How to Add a Print Filter</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Delete a print filter.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Delete information about print filters, which are programs that convert the
content type of a file to a content type that is acceptable to the destination printer.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-76250">How to Delete a Print Filter</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>View information about a print filter.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Delete information about print filters, which are programs that convert the
content type of a file to a content type that is acceptable to the destination printer.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-97732">How to View Information About a Print Filter</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printforms-88247">
<title>Managing Print Filters</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix567">
<primary>managing</primary>
<secondary>print filters (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix568">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>definition</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix569">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>managing (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix574">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>converting file content type</secondary>
</indexterm>Print filters are programs that convert the content type of a file to
a content type that is acceptable to the destination printer. The LP print service
uses filters to complete the following tasks:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Convert a file from one data format to another format so that it can
be printed properly on a specific type of printer</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Handle the special modes of printing, such as two-sided printing,
landscape printing, draft-quality, and letter-quality printing</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Detect printer faults and notify the LP print service, so that the
print service can alert users and system administrators</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Not every print filter can perform all these tasks. Because each task is printer-specific,
the tasks can be implemented separately.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix575">
<primary>
<filename>/usr/lib/lp/postscript</filename> directory</primary>
</indexterm>The LP print service provides the PostScript filters listed in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-63029">Table 5–1</olink>. The filter programs are located
in the <filename>/usr/lib/lp/postscript</filename> directory. For PostScript printing,
you usually only need to install the filter programs when setting up a print server.
Solaris Print Manager automatically enables the supplied filters. However, if you
administer other printers, you might need to administer print filters for them. </para>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-32">
<title>Creating Print Filters</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix576">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>creating (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To create a new print filter, you must write a print filter program and create
a print filter definition. Filters contain input types, output types, and complex
options that provide a language to process command-line arguments within the filter.
For more information and step-by-step instructions, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-6.xml" targetptr="printcust-45830">Creating a New Print Filter</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-33">
<title>Adding, Changing, Deleting, and Restoring Print Filters</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix577">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>adding (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix578">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>changing (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix579">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>removing (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix580">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>restoring (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>Print filters are added, changed, deleted, or restored on the print server only.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix581">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/filter.table</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix583">
<primary>
<command>lpfilter</command> command</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix584">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/fd</filename> directory</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix585">
<primary>
<filename>/usr/lib/lp</filename> directory</primary>
</indexterm>You can use the <command>lpfilter</command> command to manage the list
of available filters. System information about filters is stored in the <filename>/etc/lp/filter.table</filename> file. The <command>lpfilter</command> command gets
the information about filters to write to the table from filter descriptor files.
The filter descriptor files that are supplied (PostScript only) are located in the <filename>/etc/lp/fd</filename> directory. The actual filter programs are located in the <filename>/usr/lib/lp</filename> directory.    </para>
<para>The LP print service imposes no fixed limit on the number of print filters you
can define. You can remove filters that are no longer used to avoid extra processing
by the LP print service. (LP examines all filters to find a filter that works for
a specific print request.) If in doubt, do not remove a filter. </para>
<para>As you add, change, or delete filters, you can overwrite or remove some of the
original filters provided by the LP print service. You can restore the original set
of filters, if necessary. You can also remove any filters you have added.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix588">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>PostScript</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix589">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>TranScript</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix590">
<primary>TranScript filters</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix591">
<primary>PostScript printers</primary>
<secondary>default print filters</secondary>
</indexterm>SunOS software provides a default set of PostScript filters. Solaris Print
Manager automatically adds these filters to a print server. Some of the TranScript
filters used with <command>lpd</command>-based print services have SunOS equivalents,
but other TranScript filters do not. The following table lists the default PostScript
filters and identifies the equivalent TranScript filters, where applicable. </para>
<table frame="topbot" xml:id="printforms-63029">

<title>Default PostScript Filters</title>
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="column1" colwidth="89*"/>
<colspec colname="column2" colwidth="162*"/>
<colspec colname="column3" colwidth="108*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>PostScript Filter</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Action</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>TranScript Equivalent</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>download</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Used to download fonts</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>dpost</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes <literal>ditroff</literal> to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>psdit</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postdaisy</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes <literal>daisy</literal> to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postdmd</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes <literal>dmd</literal> to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postio</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Used for serial interface for PostScript printer</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>pscomm</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postior</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Used to communicate with printer</para>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postmd</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes matrix gray scales to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postplot</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes <literal>plot</literal> to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>psplot</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postprint</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes <literal>simple</literal> to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>enscript</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>postreverse</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Used to reverse or select pages</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>psrev</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>posttek</literal>
</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Changes <literal>TEK4014</literal> to PostScript</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<literal>ps4014</literal>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>The SunOS software does <emphasis>not</emphasis> provide the following filters: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>TEX</literal>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<literal>oscat</literal> (NeWSprint <literal>opost</literal>)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Enscript</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The <literal>postreverse</literal>, <literal>postprint</literal>, <literal>postio</literal>, and <literal>dpost</literal> filters are provided in place of Enscript.</para>
<para>Solaris Print Manager adds the default PostScript filters to a print server.
If you have printing needs that are not met by these filters, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-6.xml" targetptr="printcust-53777">How to Create a New Print Filter</olink>. This section provides information about
writing a custom print filter.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-96887">

<title>How to Add a Print Filter</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-80">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>adding (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-81">
<primary>adding</primary>
<secondary>print filters (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-35">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-36">
<para>Add a print filter that is based on a print filter
definition.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f</userinput> <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable> <userinput>-F</userinput> <replaceable>filter-definition</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option> <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name you choose for the print filter.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
F</option> <replaceable>filter-definition</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the print filter definition.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpfilter-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpfilter</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix593">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/filter.table</filename> file</primary>
<secondary>filter added to</secondary>
</indexterm>The print filter is added in the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/filter.table</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-115">
<para>Verify that the print filter was added.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f</userinput> <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgv">

<title>Adding a Print Filter</title>
<para>The following example shows how to add the <literal>daisytroff</literal> print
filter that has the <literal>daisytroff.fd</literal> print filter definition.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f daisytroff -F /etc/lp/fd/daisytroff.fd</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-76250">

<title>How to Delete a Print Filter</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-82">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>deleting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-83">
<primary>deleting</primary>
<secondary>print filters</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-40">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-41">
<para>Delete the print filter.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f</userinput> <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable> <userinput>-x</userinput>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<term>
<replaceable>filter-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the print filter to be deleted.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
x</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Deletes the specified filter.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="frcdo">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/filter.table</filename> file</primary>
<secondary>filter deleted from</secondary>
</indexterm>The print filter is deleted from the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/filter.table</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-116">
<para>Verify that the filter was deleted.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f</userinput> <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
<para>You should receive an error indicating that no filter by the specified name
exists.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgu">

<title>Deleting a Print Filter</title>
<para>The following example shows how to delete the <literal>daisytroff</literal> print
filter.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f daisytroff -x</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-97732">

<title>How to View Information About a Print Filter</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-84">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>viewing information about</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-45">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-46">
<para>Request information about a print filter. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f</userinput> <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the print filter for which you want to view information.
Specify <literal>all</literal> for <replaceable>filter-name</replaceable> to view
information about all available print filters.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
l</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Displays information about the specified filter.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>Information about the specified print filter or filters is displayed.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgn">

<title>Viewing Information About a Print Filter</title>
<para>This example shows how to request information for the <literal>postdaisy</literal> print
filter. Sample command output follows.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f postdaisy -l</userinput>
Input types: daisy
Output types: postscript
Printer types: any
Printers: any
Filter type: slow
Command: /usr/lib/lp/postscript/postdaisy
Options: PAGES * = -o*
Options: COPIES * = -c*
Options: MODES group = -n2
Options: MODES group\=\([2-9]\) = -n\1
Options: MODES portrait = -pp
Options: MODES landscape = -pl
Options: MODES x\=\(\-*[\.0-9]*\) = -x\1
Options: MODES y\=\(\-*[\.0-9]*\) = -y\1
Options: MODES magnify\=\([\.0-9]*\) = -m\1</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embzg">

<title>Viewing Information About All Print Filters on a System</title>
<para>This example shows how to display all the print filters that have been added
to the system. Sample command output follows.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f all -l | grep Filter</userinput>
(Filter "download")
Filter type: fast
(Filter "postio")
Filter type: fast
(Filter "postior")
Filter type: fast
(Filter "postreverse")
Filter type: slow</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embzp">

<title>Redirecting Information About a Print Filter</title>
<para>This example shows how to redirect information about the <literal>daisytroff</literal> filter to a file. This task is useful if a filter definition is removed
unintentionally.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpfilter -f daisytroff -l &gt; daisytroff.fd</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="eojco">
<title>Managing Forms (Task Map)</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-85">
<primary>managing forms</primary>
<secondary>task map</secondary>
</indexterm>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colwidth="33.27*"/>
<colspec colwidth="32.87*"/>
<colspec colwidth="32.87*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Limit user access to a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Control user access to printers and forms that are available on the network.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12946">How to Limit User Access to a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Add a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Add the definition of a form to the list of available forms, so that the LP
print service can recognize the form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-70477">How to Add a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Delete a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Remove the definition of a form from the list of available forms that are recognized
by the LP print service.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-98930">How to Delete a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Mount a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Use the <command>mount</command> command to notify the LP print service to accept
print requests for a form with a specific definition.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-31385">How to Unmount and Mount a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Set an alert to mount a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Set alerts for forms that are mounted to a printer.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-44360">How to Set an Alert to Mount a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>View information about a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>View form names and other form information by listing the contents of the <filename>/etc/lp/forms</filename> directory.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-40098">How to View Information About a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>View the current status of a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Use the <command>lpforms</command> command to display the current status of
a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-67212">How to View the Current Status of a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Limit printer access to a form.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Control what forms printers have access to.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12033">How to Limit Printer Access to a Form</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printforms-48">
<title>Managing Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix602">
<primary>managing</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>A <emphasis>form</emphasis> is a sheet of paper on which information is printed
in a predetermined format. Unlike plain paper stock, forms usually have text or graphics
preprinted on them. Common examples of forms are company letterhead, invoices, blank
checks, receipts, and labels.</para>
<para>The term <emphasis>form</emphasis> has two meanings: the physical medium (the
paper) and the software that defines a form to the LP print service.</para>
<para>The LP print service allows you to control the use of forms. This section provides
information about adding, changing, deleting, mounting, and limiting access to forms.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-70392">
<title>Adding, Changing, or Deleting Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix603">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>adding (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix604">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>changing (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix605">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>deleting (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>When you add a form, you tell the LP print service to include the form in its
list of available forms. You also have to supply the information required to describe
or define the form. Although you can specify such definitions when you add the form,
it helps to create the definitions first and save them in files. You can then change
the form definition by editing the file.</para>
<note>

<para>No form definitions are supplied with the LP print service.</para>
</note>
<para>To change a form, you must re-add the form with a different definition.</para>
<para>The LP print service imposes no limit on the number of forms you can define.
However, you should delete forms that are no longer appropriate. Obsolete forms can
result in unnecessary processing by the print service.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-70477">

<title>How to Add a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-86">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>adding</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-87">
<primary>adding</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-50">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-51">
<para>Add a form that is based on a form definition.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-F /etc/lp/forms/</userinput>
<replaceable>form</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name you choose for the form</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
F</option> <filename>/etc/lp/forms/</filename> <replaceable>form</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the form definition.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpforms-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpforms</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man
page.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix616">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/forms/form-name/describe</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm>The form is added to the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/forms/</filename>
<replaceable>form-name</replaceable>
<filename>/describe</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-117">
<para>Verify that the form was added by checking the
output of the following command:</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgs">

<title>Adding a Form</title>
<para>The following example shows how to add the <literal>medical</literal> form that
uses the <literal>medical.fmd</literal> form definition.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f medical -F /etc/lp/forms/medical.fmd</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<taskrelated role="see-also">

<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix618">
<primary>printers</primary>
<secondary>access to forms (example of)</secondary>
</indexterm>Before the form can be used, one or more printers must be given access
to the form. For more information, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12033">How to Limit Printer Access to a Form</olink>. </para>
</taskrelated>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-98930">

<title>How to Delete a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-88">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>deleting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-89">
<primary>deleting</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-55">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-56">
<para>Delete the form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-x</userinput>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Is the form to be deleted.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
x</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Deletes the specified form</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix621">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/forms/form-name</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm>The form is deleted from <filename>/etc/lp/forms/</filename>
<replaceable>form-name</replaceable> file. </para>
<para>For more information, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2240" targetptr="lpforms-1m">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>lpforms</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1M
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-112">
<para>Verify that the form was deleted.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
<para>You should receive an error indicating that a form by the specified name does
not exist.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgo">

<title>Deleting a Form</title>
<para>The following example shows how to delete the <literal>medical</literal> form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f medical -x</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-83300">
<title>Mounting Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix606">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>mounting (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix607">
<primary>mounting</primary>
<secondary>forms (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To print a form, you must load the paper in the printer and use a command to <emphasis>mount</emphasis> the form. This command notifies the LP print service that print requests
submitted to the printer are to be printed using the form definition. If you use one
printer for different types of printing, including forms, you should do the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Disable the printer before you load the paper and mount the form. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Re-enable the printer when the form is ready. Otherwise, the LP print
service will continue to print files that do not need the form on the printer. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>When you mount a form, ensure that it is aligned properly. If an alignment pattern
has been defined for the form, you can request that the pattern print repeatedly after
you have mounted the form. Let the pattern print repeatedly until you have adjusted
the printer so the alignment is correct.</para>
<para>When you want to change or discontinue using a form on a printer, you must notify
the LP print service by unmounting the form.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-31385">

<title>How to Unmount and Mount a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-90">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>unmounting and mounting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-91">
<primary>mounting</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-92">
<primary>unmounting</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-60">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-61">
<para>Stop accepting print requests on the printer on
which you are unmounting the current form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>reject</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> is the name of the printer on which
you are unmounting a form.</para>
<para>New print requests (which might not require
the form) are not allowed to enter the printer's queue.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-62">
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix626">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>mounting forms with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix627">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>unmounting forms with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>Unmount the current form. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-M -f none</userinput>
</screen>
<para>In this command, the variable <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> is the
same variable that is used in <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-step-61">Step 2</olink>.</para>
<para>The current form is deleted from the print server's  <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-63">
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix629">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>paper loading and removing</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix631">
<primary>changing</primary>
<secondary>forms paper</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix634">
<primary>alignment pattern</primary>
<secondary>printing</secondary>
</indexterm>Remove the form paper from the printer.  </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-64">
<para>Load the new form paper for the next print request. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-65">
<para>Mount the form. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-M -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable>[<userinput>-a -o filebreak</userinput>]</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the printer on which you are mounting a form.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
M</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the form to be mounted.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
a</option> <option>
o</option> <command>filebreak</command>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Optionally enables you to print a copy of the alignment pattern defined
for the form, if this definition exists.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Printer on which you are mounting a form.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
M</option> <option>
f</option> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Name of the form to be mounted.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The specified form is added in the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/configuration</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-66">
<para>Start accepting print requests on the printer. </para>
<screen># <userinput>accept</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>The printer is ready to print the form you just mounted.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-119">
<para>Verify that the form has been mounted.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpstat -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Otherwise, submit a print request that requires the new form and check the printer
for output.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgr">

<title>Unmounting a Form</title>
<para>The following example shows the process of unmounting the currently mounted
form on the printer <literal>luna</literal>.</para>
<screen># <userinput>reject luna</userinput>
destination "luna" will no longer accept requests
# <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -M f none</userinput>
# <userinput>accept luna</userinput>
destination "luna" now accepting requests</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embzo">

<title>Mounting a Form</title>
<para>The following example shows the process of mounting the <literal>medical</literal> form
on the printer <literal>luna</literal>.</para>
<screen># <userinput>reject luna</userinput>
destination "luna" will no longer accept requests
# <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -M f medical -a -o filebreak</userinput>
# <userinput>accept luna</userinput>
destination "luna" now accepting requests</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-45">
<title>Tracking Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printref-ix212">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>tracking mounting (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printref-ix213">
<primary>LP print service</primary>
<secondary>tracking forms (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-93">
<primary>tracking</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The LP print service helps you track which forms are mounted on each printer.
The print service also notifies you when it cannot find a description it needs to
print a form. You are responsible for creating form descriptions, and mounting and
unmounting form paper in each printer. You complete this task either as part of setting
up a printer or in response to alerts from the LP print service.</para>
<para>Users can specify the form on which they want a job to print. As superuser,
you can mount a specific form, then tell the LP print service that the form is available
and on which printer it is mounted. Users can submit print requests specifying a particular
form. When the LP print service receives the request, it sends an alert message to <literal>root</literal> requesting that you mount the form.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-30782">
<title>Defining Alerts for Mounting Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix608">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>alerts for mounting (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix609">
<primary>alerts</primary>
<secondary>for mounting forms (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>You request alerts for mounting forms in the same way that you request other
alerts from the LP print service. For general information about alerts, see <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printplan-23">Setting Up Printer Fault Alerts</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-44360">

<title>How to Set an Alert to Mount a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-94">
<primary>alerts</primary>
<secondary>set an alert to mount a form (How to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-95">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>setting alerts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-70">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-71">
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix640">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>setting alerts to mount forms with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>Set a request alert for mounting a form. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-A</userinput> <replaceable>alert</replaceable> [<userinput>-Q</userinput> <replaceable>requests</replaceable>] [<userinput>-W</userinput> <replaceable>minutes</replaceable>]</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the form for which you want to set a request alert.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
A</option> <replaceable>alert</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies what kind of alert will occur when a form is requested.
See <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-97091">Table 4–3</olink> for detailed information
about the valid values for <replaceable>alert</replaceable>. Some valid values are <literal>mail</literal>, <literal>write</literal>, and <literal>quiet</literal>. If you choose <literal>mail</literal> or <literal>write</literal>, a predefined alert message says to mount
the specified form. The message includes names of one or more printers that have been
set up to use the form.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
Q</option> <replaceable>requests</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies how many print requests that require the form must be in
the queue to trigger an alert. If you don't specify this option, an alert occurs with
just one print request in the queue.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
W</option> <replaceable>minutes</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies how often (in minutes) the alert will occur. If you don't
specify this option, the alert is sent one time.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The request alert is added to the print server's <filename>/etc/lp/forms/</filename>
<replaceable>form-name</replaceable>
<filename>/alert.sh</filename> file. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-114">
<para>Verify that the alert has been added for the
form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-A list</userinput>
</screen>
<para>Alternately, if you have set a low number of print requests to trigger the alert,
submit print requests to meet the minimum requirement. Ensure that you receive an
alert to mount the form.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgp">

<title>Setting an Alert to Mount a Form</title>
<para>This example shows how to set email alerts to occur every 5 minutes for the <literal>letterhead</literal> form when 10 print requests for <literal>letterhead</literal> reside
in the print queue.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f letterhead -A mail -Q 10 -W 5</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embzm">

<title>Setting a Console Window Alert</title>
<para>This example shows how to set console window alerts to occur every 10 minutes
for the <literal>letterhead</literal> form when 5 requests for <literal>letterhead</literal>reside in the print queue.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f letterhead -A write -Q 5 -W 10</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embyn">

<title>Setting up No Request Alerts</title>
<para>This example shows how to set no request alerts for the <literal>invoice</literal> form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f invoice -A none</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-55079">
<title>Checking Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix610">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>displaying attributes of (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-96">
<primary>checking forms</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>When you have defined a form for the LP print service, you can check the form
with either of two commands. Which command you choose depends on the type of information
you want to check.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>To show the attributes of the form, use the <command>lpforms</command> command.
You can also redirect the output of the command into a file to save it for future
reference.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix611">
<primary>alignment pattern</primary>
<secondary>protection of</secondary>
</indexterm>To display the current status of the form, use the <command>lpstat</command> command.
To protect potentially sensitive content, the alignment pattern is not shown. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix612">
<primary>
<filename>/etc/lp/forms</filename> directory</primary>
</indexterm>If you are not sure about the name of an existing form, you can view the
form names by listing the contents of the <filename>/etc/lp/forms</filename> directory. </para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-40098">

<title>How to View Information About a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-97">
<primary>form</primary>
<secondary>how to view information about</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-75">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-76">
<para>Request information about a form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the form for which you want to view information. Specify <literal>all</literal> for <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> to view information about all
the available forms.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
l</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Lists the specified form.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>Information about the specified form or forms is displayed.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgq">

<title>Viewing Information About a Form</title>
<para>The following example shows how to display information about the <literal>medical</literal> form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f medical -l</userinput>
Page length: 62
Page width: 72
Number of pages: 2
Line pitch: 6
Character pitch: 12
Character set choice: pica
Ribbon color: black
Comment:
Medical claim form</screen>
<para>The following example shows how to redirect the information about the <literal>medical</literal> form to a file. This command creates the form definition for the
form. This command is useful if a form definition is removed unintentionally.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f medical -l &gt; medical.fmd</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-67212">

<title>How to View the Current Status of a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-98">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>displaying current status</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-99">
<primary>displaying</primary>
<secondary>current status of forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-79">
<para>Log in on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-80">
<para>Request information about the current status of
a form.</para>
<screen>$ <userinput>lpstat -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>The <option>
f</option> option specifies the form for which you want to view
the current status. Specify <literal>all</literal> for <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> to
view the current status of all the forms.</para>
<para>Information about the current
status of the specified form or forms is displayed.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgt">

<title>Viewing the Current Status of a Form</title>
<para>This example shows how to display the status of the <literal>medical</literal> form.</para>
<screen>$ <userinput>lpstat -f medical</userinput>
form medical is available to you</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-91507">
<title>Limiting Access to Forms</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix613">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>controlling access to (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>You can control which printers and which users have access to some or all of
the forms available on the network. For example, you might want only the people in
the payroll or accounts payable department to be able to print check forms. In addition,
you might want the check forms to be available only on certain printers.</para>
<para>For more information, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12946">How to Limit User Access to a Form</olink>. To limit printer access to a form, see <olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12033">How to Limit Printer Access to a Form</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-12946">

<title>How to Limit User Access to a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-100">
<primary>limiting</primary>
<secondary>access to a form</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-101">
<primary>access</primary>
<secondary>limiting</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-102">
<primary>controlling</primary>
<secondary>access to a form</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-103">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>limiting access to</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-83">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-84">
<para>Allow or deny users access to a form.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-u allow</userinput>:<replaceable>user-list</replaceable> | <userinput>deny</userinput>:<replaceable>user-list</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the form for which the allow user access lists
or the deny user access list is being created.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<command>-u allow:</command>
<replaceable>user-list</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Represents users to be added to the allow user access list. Use a
comma or a space to separate user login IDs. If you use spaces, enclose the list of
IDs in quotation marks. </para>
<para>
<olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-55566">Table 4–5</olink> provides the valid
values for <replaceable>user-list</replaceable>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<command>-u deny:</command>
<replaceable>user-list</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Represents users to be added to the deny user access list. Use a comma
or a space to separate user login IDs. If you use spaces, enclose the list of IDs
in quotation marks. <olink remap="external" targetdoc="chapter-4.xml" targetptr="printadmin-55566">Table 4–5</olink> provides
the valid values for <replaceable>user-list</replaceable>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix650">
<primary>allow list</primary>
<secondary>for user access to forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix651">
<primary>deny list</primary>
<secondary>for user access to forms</secondary>
</indexterm>The specified users are added to the appropriate user access list for
the specified form in one of the following files on the print server: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>/etc/lp/forms/</filename>
<replaceable>form-name</replaceable>
<filename>/allow</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>/etc/lp/forms/</filename>
<replaceable>form-name</replaceable>
<filename>/deny</filename> </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-121">
<para>Verify that the allow user access list and deny
user access list are set up correctly.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f</userinput> <replaceable>form-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgw">

<title>Allowing User Access to a Form</title>
<para>This example shows how to allow only the users <literal>nathan</literal> and <literal>marcia</literal> access to the <literal>check</literal> form. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f check -u allow:nathan,marcia</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="emcab">

<title>Denying User Access to a Form</title>
<para>This example shows how to deny users <literal>jones</literal> and <literal>smith</literal> access to the <literal>dental</literal> form. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpforms -f dental -u deny:jones,smith</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-12033">

<title>How to Limit Printer Access to a Form</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-104">
<primary>printer access</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-105">
<primary>controlling</primary>
<secondary>printer access to a form</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-106">
<primary>forms</primary>
<secondary>how to limit printer access</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-107">
<primary>limiting</primary>
<secondary>printer access to a form</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-88">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-89">
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix659">
<primary>
<command>lpadmin</command> command</primary>
<secondary>limiting printer access to forms with (how to)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix660">
<primary>allow list</primary>
<secondary>for printer access to forms</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix661">
<primary>deny list</primary>
<secondary>for printer access to forms</secondary>
</indexterm>Allow or deny use of forms on a printer. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-f allow</userinput>:<replaceable>form-list</replaceable> | <userinput>deny</userinput>:<replaceable>form-list</replaceable>
</screen>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
p</option>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the name of the printer for which the allow forms list or
deny forms list is being created.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option> allow: <replaceable>form-list</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specifies the form name to be added to the allow list. Use a space
or a comma to separate multiple form names. If you use spaces to separate form names,
enclose the list of form names in quotation marks.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<option>
f</option> deny: <replaceable>form-list</replaceable>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Is the form name to be added to the deny list. Use a space or a comma
to separate multiple form names. If you use spaces to separate form names, enclose
the list of form names in quotation marks.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The specified form or forms are added to the allow forms list or the deny forms
list in one of the following files on the print server:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/form.allow</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
<filename>/form.deny</filename> </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-122">
<para>Verify that the allow forms list and the deny
forms list are set up correctly.</para>
<screen># <userinput>lpstat -p</userinput> <replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> <userinput>-l</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
<example xml:id="emjgy">

<title>Allowing Printer Access to a Form</title>
<para>This example shows how to allow the printer <literal>luna</literal> to access
only the <literal>medical</literal>, <literal>dental</literal>, and <literal>check</literal> forms. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -f allow:medical,dental,check</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
<example xml:id="embze">

<title>Limiting Printer Access to a Form</title>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix664">
<primary>administering</primary>
<secondary>forms</secondary>
</indexterm>This example shows how to deny the printer <literal>luna</literal> from
accessing the <literal>medical</literal>, <literal>dental</literal>, and <literal>check</literal> forms. </para>
<screen># <userinput>lpadmin -p luna -f deny:"medical dental check"</userinput>
</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="eojct">
<title>Managing Fonts (Task Map)</title>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colwidth="33*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Task</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Install downloaded PostScript fonts.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Permanently download a font if most print requests serviced by the printer use
that font. To avoid transmitting fonts across the network, add all the printer-resident
fonts.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-12681">How to Install Downloaded PostScript Fonts</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para>Install host-resident PostScript fonts.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Install host-resident fonts on a system that is shared by many users. Use this
method when numerous fonts are available, or when these fonts are not used by all
print requests.</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-5.xml" targetptr="printforms-34675">How to Install Host-Resident PostScript Fonts</olink>
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="printforms-26075">
<title>Managing Fonts</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix667">
<primary>managing</primary>
<secondary>fonts (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix668">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>PostScript</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix669">
<primary>PostScript fonts</primary>
</indexterm>If you have a laser printer, you might need to install and maintain PostScript
fonts. For many printers, the fonts are set up as part of the printer installation
process.  </para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix670">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>downloading (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix671">
<primary>downloading</primary>
<secondary>fonts (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>PostScript fonts are stored in outline form, either on the printer or
on a system that communicates with the printer. When a document is printed, the PostScript
interpreter generates each character as needed in the appropriate size from the outline
description of it. If a font required for a document is not stored on the printer
being used, the font must be transmitted to that printer before the document can be
printed. This transmission process is called <emphasis>downloading fonts</emphasis>.
 </para>
<para>Fonts are stored and accessed in several ways:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix672">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>printer-resident</secondary>
</indexterm>
<emphasis>Printer-resident</emphasis> <emphasis>fonts</emphasis> are stored
permanently on a printer. These fonts are installed in read-only memory (ROM) on the
printer by the manufacturer. If the printer has a disk, you can install fonts on that
disk. Most PostScript printers are shipped with 35 standard fonts. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix673">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>permanently downloaded</secondary>
</indexterm>A <emphasis>permanently downloaded</emphasis> <emphasis>font</emphasis> is
transmitted to a printer with a PostScript <command>exitserver</command> program.
A permanently downloaded font remains in printer memory until the printer is turned
off. Memory allocated to a downloaded font reduces the memory available on the server
for PostScript print requests. Use of an <command>exitserver</command> program requires
the printer system password and can be reserved for the printer administrator. You
should permanently download a font if most print requests serviced by the printer
use that font. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fonts that are used infrequently or for special purposes can be stored
on a user's system. The user can specify these fonts when submitting the print request.
The fonts are appended to the print request and transmitted to the printer. When the
print request is processed, the space allocated for the font is freed for other print
requests.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix674">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>host-resident</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-108">
<primary>host-resident</primary>
<secondary>fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<emphasis>Host-resident fonts</emphasis> are stored on a system that is
shared by many users. The system that stores the fonts can be a print server or a
print client. Each user can request fonts in the document to be printed. This method
is useful when numerous fonts are available, or when these fonts are not used by all
print requests. If the fonts will be used only on printers attached to a print server,
they should be stored on the print server. If the fonts will be used by the users
on one system and those users can submit requests to multiple printers on a network,
the fonts should be stored on the users' system. </para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix676">
<primary>filters</primary>
<secondary>download</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-109">
<primary>downloading</primary>
<secondary>filters</secondary>
</indexterm>The LP print service provides a special download filter to manage host-resident
fonts. The LP print service also supplies <literal>troff</literal> width tables for
the 35 standard PostScript fonts that reside on many PostScript printers. For more
information about the <literal>troff</literal> program, see the <olink remap="external" targetdoc="819-2239" targetptr="troff-1">
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>troff</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>
1
</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</olink> man page.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-92">
<title>Managing Printer-Resident Fonts</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix678">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>printer-resident (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix679">
<primary>printer-resident fonts (overview)</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>Most PostScript printers come equipped with fonts that are resident in the printer
ROM. Some printers have a disk on which additional fonts are stored. When a printer
is installed, you should add the list of printer-resident fonts to the font list for
that printer. By identifying printer-resident fonts, you prevent fonts from being
transmitted unnecessarily across a network. Each printer has its own list of resident
fonts, which is contained in this file:</para>
<screen>/etc/lp/printers/<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>/residentfonts</screen>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix698">
<primary>
<filename>residentfonts</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm>When the printer is attached to a print server, ensure that the list in
the <filename>residentfonts</filename> file includes fonts that are on the print server.
The file must also include fonts that are available for downloading to the printer.</para>
<para>You must edit the files that contain the list of printer-resident fonts by using
a text editor such as <command>vi</command>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-93">
<title>Downloading Host-Resident Fonts</title>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix681">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>host-resident (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix682">
<primary>host-resident fonts</primary>
<secondary>downloading (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix683">
<primary>downloading</primary>
<secondary>host-resident fonts (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix684">
<primary>filters</primary>
<secondary>downloading (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>When a PostScript document contains a request for fonts not loaded on
the printer, the download filter manages this request. The download filter uses PostScript
document structuring conventions to determine which fonts to download.  </para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix686">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>fast (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix687">
<primary>fast print filters (overview)</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix688">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>slow (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix689">
<primary>slow print filters</primary>
</indexterm>LP print filters are either fast or slow. A <emphasis>fast filter</emphasis> quickly
prepares a file for printing. Also, a fast filter must have access to the printer
while the filter is processing. A <emphasis>slow filter</emphasis> takes longer to
convert a file. However, a slow filter does not need to access the printer while the
filter is processing. An example of a slow filter is a filter that converts an ASCII
document to a PostScript document.</para>
<para>
<indexterm xml:id="printforms-ix690">
<primary>print filters</primary>
<secondary>download (overview)</secondary>
</indexterm>The <emphasis>download filter</emphasis> is a fast filter. This filter
downloads fonts automatically if the fonts are on the print server. The download filter
can also be used to send fonts to a print server. To do so, you can create a new filter
table entry that calls the download filter as a slow filter by using the <command>lp</command> <option>
y</option> command. Alternatively, you can force selection of
this filter by changing the input type. </para>
<para>The download filter performs five tasks:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The filter searches the PostScript document to determine which fonts
are requested. These requests are documented with the following PostScript structuring
comments: <literal>%%DocumentFonts:</literal> <replaceable>font1 font2 …</replaceable> in
the header comments.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The download filter searches the list of printer-resident fonts to
determine if the requested font must be downloaded.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the font is not resident on the printer, the download filter searches
the host-resident font directory table to determine if the requested font is available.
This filter performs this search by getting the appropriate file name from the map.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the font is available, the download filter takes the file for that
font and appends it to the file to be printed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The download filter sends the font definition file and the source
file to the PostScript printer. The <emphasis>source file</emphasis> is the file to
be printed.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="printforms-94">
<title>Installing and Maintaining Host-Resident Fonts</title>
<para>Some fonts reside on the host system and are transmitted to the printer as needed
for particular print requests. As the administrator, you make PostScript fonts available
to all users on a system. To do so, you must know how and where to install these fonts.
Because fonts are requested by name and stored in files, the LP print service keeps
a <emphasis>map file</emphasis>. A map file shows the correspondence between the names
of fonts and the names of the files that contain those fonts. Both the map file and
the font list must be updated when you install host-resident fonts.</para>
<para>The fonts available for use with PostScript printers are stored in directories
that you create. These directories are called <filename>/usr/share/lib/hostfontdir/</filename>
<replaceable>typeface</replaceable>
<filename>/</filename>
<replaceable>font</replaceable>. The variable <replaceable>typeface</replaceable> is replaced by
a name, such as <literal>palatino</literal> or <literal>helvetica</literal>. The variable <replaceable>font</replaceable> is replaced by a an attribute name, such as <literal>bold</literal> or <literal>italic</literal>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-12681">

<title>How to Install Downloaded PostScript Fonts</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-110">
<primary>installing downloaded PostScript fonts</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-111">
<primary>downloaded PostScript Fonts</primary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-96">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal> user,
or assume an equivalent role on the print server or print client.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-97">
<para>Change directory to the <filename>/etc/lp/printers/</filename>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable> directory.</para>
<screen># <userinput>cd /etc/lp/printers/</userinput>
<replaceable>printer-name</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>The variable <emphasis>printer-name</emphasis> specifies the name of the printer
on which you want to install downloaded PostScript fonts.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-98">
<para>Create the <filename>residentfonts</filename> file,
if this file does not already exist. </para>
<screen># <userinput>touch residentfonts</userinput>
</screen>
<para>This file might not exist if you are adding permanently downloaded fonts for
the first time. </para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-99">
<para>Edit the <filename>residentfonts</filename> file.
Add all the printer-resident fonts and the fonts to be permanently downloaded.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title/>
<task id="printforms-34675">

<title>How to Install Host-Resident PostScript Fonts</title>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-112">
<primary>installing</primary>
<secondary>host-resident PostScript fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-113">
<primary>fonts</primary>
<secondary>host-resident PostScript fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm xml:id="indexterm-114">
<primary>host-resident PostScript Fonts</primary>
<secondary>how to install</secondary>
</indexterm>
<procedure>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-102">
<para>Log in as superuser, <literal>lp</literal>, or
assume an equivalent role on the print server or print client.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-103">
<para>Create the <filename>hostfontdir</filename> directory.</para>
<screen># <userinput>cd /usr/share/lib</userinput>
</screen>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Change to the <filename>/usr/share/lib</filename>directory.</para>
<screen># <userinput>cd /usr/share/lib</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Create the <filename>hostfontdir</filename> directory, if this directory
does not already exist.</para>
<screen># <userinput>mkdir hostfontdir</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
<step>
<para>Change the permissions on the <filename>hostfontdir</filename> directory
to 775.</para>
<screen># <userinput>chmod 775 hostfontdir</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-104">
<para>Create a directory for a new typeface, if the
directory does not already exist. </para>
<screen># <userinput>mkdir</userinput> <replaceable>typeface</replaceable>
</screen>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-105">
<para>Copy the font file to the appropriate directory.</para>
<screen># <userinput>cp</userinput> <replaceable>filename</replaceable> <userinput>/usr/share/lib/hostfontdir</userinput>/<replaceable>typeface</replaceable>/<replaceable>font</replaceable>
</screen>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-106">
<para>Add to the map file the name of the font and
the name of the file in which it resides.</para>
<substeps>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-107">
<para>Change to the <filename>/usr/share/lib/hostfontdir</filename> directory.</para>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-108">
<para>Edit the <filename>map</filename> file by using
a text editor such as the <command>vi</command> editor.</para>
<para>Add a one-line
entry for each font that you want to add to the file. Put the font name first, followed
by a space, followed by the name of the file where the font resides. For example:</para>
<screen>
<userinput>Palatino-Bold /usr/share/lib/hostfontdir/palatino/bold</userinput>
</screen>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-109">
<para>Save the file.</para>
<para>When an example entry
exists in the map file on the appropriate system, users can apply the font (for example,
Palatino Bold) to their print jobs. When users submit a print request that contains
this font, the LP print service appends a copy of the <filename>/usr/share/lib/hostfontdir/palatino/bold</filename> file to that file before sending it to the printer.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step xml:id="printforms-step-110">
<para>If you are using the <command>troff</command> program,
you must create new width tables for this font in the standard <command>troff</command> font
directory. </para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
