<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="fpdeg">



<title>Installing the OpenSolaris Software</title>

<para>This document provides the procedures to install the OpenSolaris software distributed on the <command>i install</command> DVD.</para>
<para>The following topics are specific to an x86/x64 machine with multiple partitions:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<olink remap="internal" targetdoc="chapter-2.xml" targetptr="gbuan">Installing the OpenSolaris Software</olink>
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<sect1 xml:id="gbuan">
<title>Creating the OpenSolaris Installation Images</title>
<para>If you do not have a DVD drive, the following list provides utilities you may use to create an install image of the Solaris Express: Community Release pre-built archives located at http://www.opensolaris.org/os/downloads/on/.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Nero (Windows)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>ISO Recorder (Windows)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>K3B (Linux)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><command>cdrw</command>, <command>cdrecord</command> (Solaris)</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="gacqz">
<title>Installing the OpenSolaris Software</title>

<para>The following procedure describes installation from the <command>i install</command> DVD that is included with this kit. Be sure that you have completed the preparations required to successfully install.</para>
<figure xml:id="fxktf">

<title>Installation Process Overview</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/installation_process_overview.gif"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<simpara>Diagram provides an example of the process for installing.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<sect2>


<title>To Install the Solaris Express: Community Release Software</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>Insert the <command>i install</command> DVD into the DVD drive.</para>
<para>The GNU GRUB screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Press the Enter key to boot Solaris from the <command>i install</command> DVD.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select your prefered language.</para>
<para>The System Identification screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Complete the following System Identification sub-steps.</para> 
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Specify Yes or No for Network Connectivity.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify a host name.</para>
<para>Host name is the name of your laptop and should be unique.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify NFSv4 domain name.</para>
<para>The default is the NFSv4 domain that is derived by the system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify a time zone.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify country or region.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify date and time.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify root password.</para>
<para>Root password is the administrative password for this machine.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
<step>
<para>Choose Standard installation.</para>

</step>
<step>
<para>Read and accept the license agreement.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the geographic region.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the system locale.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select no additional products.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Entire Distribution.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Disk. Choose the disk where you created the new partition using QTParted.</para>
<para>The No Solaris fdisk Partition screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Press F2 to continue.</para>
<para>The Create Solaris fdisk Partition screen appears.</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Select Manually create fdisk partitions, and press F2 to continue.</para>
<para>The Customize fdisk Partitions for Disk screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the partition you created with QTParted and presss F3 to delete it. (You will re-create this in a following step).</para>
<para>A confirmation screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Press F2 to confirm deletion of the fdisk partition.</para>
<para>The Customize fdisk Partitions for Disk screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the unused fdisk partition and press F4 to create it.</para>
<para>The Fdisk Partition Type screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Choose SOLARIS as the partition type and press F2 to confirm it.</para>
<para>The Fdisk Partition Size screen appears.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type the desired size of the Solaris fdisk partition and press F2 to confirm it.</para>
<para>The Customize fdisk Partitions for Disk screen appears with the new partition listed.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Press F2 to continue.</para>
<para>The Select Disks screen appears.</para>
</step>
</substeps>

</step>
<step>
<para>Continue with the installation by completing the installation profile as follows:</para>
<substeps>
<step>
<para>Choose to automatically layout file systems.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Specify the file system and disk layout.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Confirm the root, swap, and overlap sizing.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Customize mounting of remote file systems if needed.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Confirm the Profile for your installation and press F2 to begin the installation.</para>
<para>The Preparing system for Solaris install message appears followed by the Specify Media dialog box.</para> 
</step>
<step>
<para>Select the CD/DVD radio button in the Specify Media dialog box.</para>
<para>The GNU GRUB boot menu appears.</para> 
</step>
<step>
<para>Select Solaris Nevada snv_XX X86, where XX is the number 41 or above.</para>
<para>OpenSolaris boots.</para> 
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</procedure>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<para>If Solaris does not boot, try to boot Windows or send email to the http://opensolaris.org/os/community/laptop/discussions Laptop Community discussion alias to request help with troubleshooting. If Windows will not boot, restore the Windows operating system by loading the g4u CD and type the following command:</para>
<screen>g4u > <command>slurpdisk <replaceable>IP address</replaceable> <filename>imagename.gz</filename> <literal>wd0</literal></command></screen>
<para>Where <replaceable>IP address</replaceable> is the IP address of the FTP server where you saved the image, <replaceable>imagename.gz</replaceable> is the name of the backup file, and <replaceable>wd0</replaceable> is the disk you want to restore.</para>
<para>At the prompt, type the password for the <literal>install</literal> user account.</para>
<para>Windows is restored to the whole disk and the partition you created with QTParted is overwritten.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Next Steps</title>
<para>If Solaris booted successfully, refer to the Configuration tab for further instructions about how to configure the OpenSolaris software.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>