<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML//EN" "docbook.dtd"[
	<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "xinclude.mod">
	%xinclude;
]>

<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" label="fcs" xml:lang="en" role="unnumbered" userlevel="admin">

<title>Solaris Volume Manager Administration Guide</title>
<info role="lot-lof">
<authorgroup>
<author>

<personname>Virginia Wray</personname>
</author>
</authorgroup>
<bilioid>
819-2789-01</bilioid>
<releaseinfo>
</releaseinfo>
<pubdate>June 2006</pubdate>
<publisher>
<publishername>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</publishername>
<address>
<street>4150 Network Circle</street>
<city>Santa Clara
</city>
<state>CA
</state>
<postcode>95054</postcode>
<country>U.S.A.</country>
</address>
</publisher>
<copyright>
<year>2006</year>
<holder>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</holder>
</copyright>
<abstract>
<para>The Solaris Volume Manager Administration Guide provides instructions
on using Solaris Volume Manager to manage disk storage, including creating, modifying,
and using RAID-0 (concatenation and stripe) volumes, RAID-1 (mirror) volumes</para>
</abstract>
<legalnotice>
<para>The contents of this Documentation are subject to the 
Public Documentation License Version 1.01 (the "License"); 
you may only use this Documentation if you comply with the terms of this License. 
A copy of the License is available at 
http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/documentation/license.
            </para>
<para>This product or document is protected by copyright and distributed under licenses restricting its use, copying, distribution, and decompilation. No part of this product or document may be reproduced in any form by any means without prior written authorization of Sun and its licensors, if any. Third-party software, including font technology, is copyrighted and licensed from Sun suppliers.</para>
<para>Parts of the product may be derived from Berkeley BSD systems, licensed from the University of California. UNIX is a registered trademark in the U.S. and other countries, exclusively licensed through X/Open Company, Ltd.</para>
<para>Sun, Sun Microsystems, the Sun logo, docs.sun.com, AnswerBook, AnswerBook2, 


 and Solaris are trademarks or registered trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. in the U.S. and other countries. All SPARC trademarks are used under license and are trademarks or registered trademarks of SPARC International, Inc. in the U.S. and other countries. Products bearing SPARC trademarks are based upon an architecture developed by Sun Microsystems, Inc. </para>
<para>The OPEN LOOK and <trademark>Sun</trademark> Graphical User Interface was developed by Sun Microsystems, Inc. for its users and licensees. Sun acknowledges the pioneering efforts of Xerox in researching and developing the concept of visual or graphical user interfaces for the computer industry. Sun holds a non-exclusive license from Xerox to the Xerox Graphical User Interface, which license also covers Sun's licensees who implement OPEN LOOK GUIs and otherwise comply with Sun's written license agreements.</para>
<para>U.S. Government Rights – Commercial software.  Government users are subject to the Sun Microsystems, Inc. standard license agreement and applicable provisions of the FAR and its supplements.</para>
<para>DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED “AS IS” AND ALL EXPRESS OR IMPLIED CONDITIONS, REPRESENTATIONS AND WARRANTIES, INCLUDING ANY IMPLIED WARRANTY OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR NON-INFRINGEMENT, ARE DISCLAIMED, EXCEPT TO THE EXTENT THAT SUCH DISCLAIMERS ARE HELD TO BE LEGALLY INVALID.</para>
<para xml:lang="fr">
</para>
<para>Ce produit ou document est protégé par un copyright et distribué avec des licences qui en restreignent l'utilisation, la copie, la distribution, et la décompilation. Aucune partie de ce produit ou document ne peut être reproduite sous aucune forme, par quelque moyen que ce soit, sans l'autorisation préalable et écrite de Sun et de ses bailleurs de licence, s'il y en a. Le logiciel détenu par des tiers, et qui comprend la technologie relative aux polices de caractères, est protégé par un copyright et licencié par des fournisseurs de Sun.</para>
<para>Des parties de ce produit pourront être dérivées du système Berkeley BSD licenciés par l'Université de Californie. UNIX est une marque déposée aux Etats-Unis et dans d'autres pays et licenciée exclusivement par X/Open Company, Ltd. </para>
<para>Sun, Sun Microsystems, le logo Sun, docs.sun.com, AnswerBook, AnswerBook2, 


 et Solaris sont des marques de fabrique ou des marques déposées, de Sun Microsystems, Inc. aux Etats-Unis et dans d'autres pays. Toutes les marques SPARC sont utilisées sous licence et sont des marques de fabrique ou des marques déposées de SPARC International, Inc. aux Etats-Unis et dans d'autres pays. Les produits portant les marques SPARC sont basés sur une architecture développée par Sun Microsystems, Inc.</para>
<para>L'interface d'utilisation graphique OPEN LOOK et Sun a été développée par Sun Microsystems, Inc. pour ses utilisateurs et licenciés. Sun reconnaît les efforts de pionniers de Xerox pour la recherche et le développement du concept des interfaces d'utilisation visuelle ou graphique pour l'industrie de l'informatique. Sun détient une licence non exclusive de Xerox sur l'interface d'utilisation graphique Xerox, cette licence couvrant également les licenciés de Sun qui mettent en place l'interface d'utilisation graphique OPEN LOOK et qui en outre se conforment aux licences écrites de Sun.</para>
<para>CETTE PUBLICATION EST FOURNIE “EN L'ETAT” ET AUCUNE GARANTIE, EXPRESSE OU IMPLICITE, N'EST ACCORDEE, Y COMPRIS DES GARANTIES CONCERNANT LA VALEUR MARCHANDE, L'APTITUDE DE LA PUBLICATION A REPONDRE A UNE UTILISATION PARTICULIERE, OU LE FAIT QU'ELLE NE SOIT PAS CONTREFAISANTE DE PRODUIT DE TIERS. CE DENI DE GARANTIE NE S'APPLIQUERAIT PAS, DANS LA MESURE OU IL SERAIT TENU JURIDIQUEMENT NUL ET NON AVENU.</para>
</legalnotice>
<subjectset>
<subject>
<subjectterm>Introduction &amp; Overview</subjectterm>
<subjectterm>Other Reference</subjectterm>
<subjectterm>System Administration</subjectterm>
<subjectterm>Troubleshooting</subjectterm>
</subject>
</subjectset>
</info>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="preface-1.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-1.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-2.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-3.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-4.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-5.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-6.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-7.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-8.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-9.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-10.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-11.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-12.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-13.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-14.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-15.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-16.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-17.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-18.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-19.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-20.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-21.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-22.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-23.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-24.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="chapter-25.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="appendix-1.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="appendix-2.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="appendix-3.xml"/>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="index-1.xml"/>

</book>
